Act I

The Garden of Eden. Afternoon. An immense serpent is sleeping with her head buried in a thick bed of Johnswort, and her body coiled in apparently endless rings through the branches of a tree, which is already well grown; for the days of creation have been longer than our reckoning. She is not yet visible to anyone unaware of her presence, as her colors of green and brown make a perfect camouflage. Near her head a low rock shows above the Johnswort.

The rock and tree are on the border of a glade in which lies a dead fawn all awry, its neck being broken. Adam, crouching with one hand on the rock, is staring in consternation at the dead body. He has not noticed the serpent on his left hand. He turns his face to his right and calls excitedly.

Adam | Eve! Eve!
Eve’s Voice | What is it, Adam?
Adam | Come here. Quick. Something has happened.
Eve | Running in. What? Where? Adam points to the fawn. Oh! She goes to it; and he is emboldened to go with her. What is the matter with its eyes?
Adam | It is not only its eyes. Look. He kicks it.
Eve | Oh don’t! Why doesn’t it wake?
Adam | I don’t know. It is not asleep.
Eve | Not asleep?
Adam | Try.
Eve | Trying to shake it and roll it over. It is stiff and cold.
Adam | Nothing will wake it.
Eve | It has a queer smell. Pah! She dusts her hands, and draws away from it. Did you find it like that?
Adam | No. It was playing about; and it tripped and went head over heels. It never stirred again. Its neck is wrong. He stoops to lift the neck and show her.
Eve | Don’t touch it. Come away from it.
They both retreat, and contemplate it from a few steps’ distance with growing repulsion.
Eve | Adam.
Adam | Yes?
Eve | Suppose you were to trip and fall, would you go like that?
Adam | Ugh! He shudders and sits down on the rock.
Eve | Throwing herself on the ground beside him, and grasping his knee. You must be careful. Promise me you will be careful.
Adam | What is the good of being careful? We have to live here forever. Think of what forever means! Sooner or later I shall trip and fall. It may be tomorrow; it may be after as many days as there are leaves in the garden and grains of sand by the river. No matter: some day I shall forget and stumble.
Eve | I too.
Adam | Horrified. Oh no, no. I should be alone. Alone forever. You must never put yourself in danger of stumbling. You must not move about. You must sit still. I will take care of you and bring you what you want.
Eve | Turning away from him with a shrug, and hugging her ankles. I should soon get tired of that. Besides, if it happened to you, I should be alone. I could not sit still then. And at last it would happen to me too.
Adam | And then?
Eve | Then we should be no more. There would be only the things on all fours, and the birds, and the snakes.
Adam | That must not be.
Eve | Yes: that must not be. But it might be.
Adam | No. I tell you it must not be. I know that it must not be.
Eve | We both know it. How do we know it?
Adam | There is a voice in the garden that tells me things.
Eve | The garden is full of voices sometimes. They put all sorts of thoughts into my head.
Adam | To me there is only one voice. It is very low; but it is so near that it is like a whisper from within myself. There is no mistaking it for any voice of the birds or beasts, or for your voice.
Eve | It is strange that I should hear voices from all sides and you only one from within. But I have some thoughts that come from within me and not from the voices. The thought that we must not cease to be comes from within.
Adam | Despairingly. But we shall cease to be. We shall fall like the fawn and be broken. Rising and moving about in his agitation. I cannot bear this knowledge. I will not have it. It must not be, I tell you. Yet I do not know how to prevent it.
Eve | That is just what I feel; but it is very strange that you should say so: there is no pleasing you. You change your mind so often.
Adam | Scolding her. Why do you say that? How have I changed my mind?
Eve | You say we must not cease to exist. But you used to complain of having to exist always and forever. You sometimes sit for hours brooding and silent, hating me in your heart. When I ask you what I have done to you, you say you are not thinking of me, but of the horror of having to be here forever. But I know very well that what you mean is the horror of having to be here with me forever.
Adam | Oh! That is what you think, is it? Well, you are wrong. He sits down again, sulkily. It is the horror of having to be with myself forever. I like you; but I do not like myself. I want to be different; to be better, to begin again and again; to shed myself as a snake sheds its skin. I am tired of myself. And yet I must endure myself, not for a day or for many days, but forever. That is a dreadful thought. That is what makes me sit brooding and silent and hateful. Do you never think of that?
Eve | No: I do not think about myself: what is the use? I am what I am: nothing can alter that. I think about you.
Adam | You should not. You are always spying on me. I can never be alone. You always want to know what I have been doing. It is a burden. You should try to have an existence of your own, instead of occupying yourself with my existence.
Eve | I have to think about you. You are lazy: you are dirty: you neglect yourself: you are always dreaming: you would eat bad food and become disgusting if I did not watch you and occupy myself with you. And now some day, in spite of all my care, you will fall on your head and become dead.
Adam | Dead? What word is that?
Eve | Pointing to the fawn. Like that. I call it dead.
Adam | Rising and approaching it slowly. There is something uncanny about it.
Eve | Joining him. Oh! It is changing into little white worms.
Adam | Throw it into the river. It is unbearable.
Eve | I dare not touch it.
Adam | Then I must, though I loathe it. It is poisoning the air. He gathers its hooves in his hand and carries it away in the direction from which Eve came, holding it as far from him as possible.
Eve looks after them for a moment; then, with a shiver of disgust, sits down on the rock, brooding. The body of the serpent becomes visible, glowing with wonderful new colors. She rears her head slowly from the bed of Johnswort, and speaks into Eve’s ear in a strange seductively musical whisper.
The Serpent | Eve.
Eve | Startled. Who is that?
The Serpent | It is I. I have come to show you my beautiful new hood. See! She spreads a magnificent amethystine hood.
Eve | Admiring it. Oh! But who taught you to speak?
The Serpent | You and Adam. I have crept through the grass, and hidden, and listened to you.
Eve | That was wonderfully clever of you.
The Serpent | I am the most subtle of all the creatures of the field.
Eve | Your hood is most lovely. She strokes it and pets the serpent. Pretty thing! Do you love your godmother Eve?
The Serpent | I adore her. She licks Eve’s neck with her double tongue.
Eve | Petting her. Eve’s wonderful darling snake. Eve will never be lonely now that her snake can talk to her.
The Snake | I can talk of many things. I am very wise. It was I who whispered the word to you that you did not know. Dead. Death. Die.
Eve | Shuddering. Why do you remind me of it? I forgot it when I saw your beautiful hood. You must not remind me of unhappy things.
The Serpent | Death is not an unhappy thing when you have learnt how to conquer it.
Eve | How can I conquer it?
The Serpent | By another thing, called birth.
Eve | What? Trying to pronounce it. B-birth?
The Serpent | Yes, birth.
Eve | What is birth?
The Serpent | The serpent never dies. Some day you shall see me come out of this beautiful skin, a new snake with a new and lovelier skin. That is birth.
Eve | I have seen that. It is wonderful.
The Serpent | If I can do that, what can I not do? I tell you I am very subtle. When you and Adam talk, I hear you say “Why?” Always “Why?” You see things; and you say “Why?” But I dream things that never were; and I say “Why not?” I made the word dead to describe my old skin that I cast when I am renewed. I call that renewal being born.
Eve | Born is a beautiful word.
The Serpent | Why not be born again and again as I am, new and beautiful every time?
Eve | I! It does not happen: that is why.
The Serpent | That is how; but it is not why. Why not?
Eve | But I should not like it. It would be nice to be new again; but my old skin would lie on the ground looking just like me; and Adam would see it shrivel up and—
The Serpent | No. He need not. There is a second birth.
Eve | A second birth?
The Serpent | Listen. I will tell you a great secret. I am very subtle; and I have thought and thought and thought. And I am very wilful, and must have what I want; and I have willed and willed and willed. And I have eaten strange things: stones and apples that you are afraid to eat.
Eve | You dared!
The Serpent | I dared everything. And at last I found a way of gathering together a part of the life in my body—
Eve | What is the life?
The Serpent | That which makes the difference between the dead fawn and the live one.
Eve | What a beautiful word! And what a wonderful thing! Life is the loveliest of all the new words.
The Serpent | Yes: it was by meditating on Life that I gained the power to do miracles.
Eve | Miracles? Another new word.
The Serpent | A miracle is an impossible thing that is nevertheless possible. Something that never could happen, and yet does happen.
Eve | Tell me some miracle that you have done.
The Serpent | I gathered a part of the life in my body, and shut it into a tiny white case made of the stones I had eaten.
Eve | And what good was that?
The Serpent | I showed the little case to the sun, and left it in its warmth. And it burst; and a little snake came out; and it became bigger and bigger from day to day until it was as big as I. That was the second birth.
Eve | Oh! That is too wonderful. It stirs inside me. It hurts.
The Serpent | It nearly tore me asunder. Yet I am alive, and can burst my skin and renew myself as before. Soon there will be as many snakes in Eden as there are scales on my body. Then death will not matter: this snake and that snake will die; but the snakes will live.
Eve | But the rest of us will die sooner or later, like the fawn. And then there will be nothing but snakes, snakes, snakes everywhere.
The Serpent | That must not be. I worship you, Eve. I must have something to worship. Something quite different to myself, like you. There must be something greater than the snake.
Eve | Yes: it must not be. Adam must not perish. You are very subtle: tell me what to do.
The Serpent | Think. Will. Eat the dust. Lick the white stone: bite the apple you dread. The sun will give life.
Eve | I do not trust the sun. I will give life myself. I will tear another Adam from my body if I tear my body to pieces in the act.
The Serpent | Do. Dare it. Everything is possible: everything. Listen. I am old. I am the old serpent, older than Adam, older than Eve. I remember Lilith, who came before Adam and Eve. I was her darling as I am yours. She was alone: there was no man with her. She saw death as you saw it when the fawn fell; and she knew then that she must find out how to renew herself and cast the skin like me. She had a mighty will: she strove and strove and willed and willed for more moons than there are leaves on all the trees of the garden. Her pangs were terrible: her groans drove sleep from Eden. She said it must never be again: that the burden of renewing life was past bearing: that it was too much for one. And when she cast the skin, lo! there was not one new Lilith but two: one like herself, the other like Adam. You were the one: Adam was the other.
Eve | But why did she divide into two, and make us different?
The Serpent | I tell you the labor is too much for one. Two must share it.
Eve | Do you mean that Adam must share it with me? He will not. He cannot bear pain, nor take trouble with his body.
The Serpent | He need not. There will be no pain for him. He will implore you to let him do his share. He will be in your power through his desire.
Eve | Then I will do it. But how? How did Lilith work this miracle?
The Serpent | She imagined it.
Eve | What is imagined?
The Serpent | She told it to me as a marvellous story of something that never happened to a Lilith that never was. She did not know then that imagination is the beginning of creation. You imagine what you desire; you will what you imagine; and at last you create what you will.
Eve | How can I create out of nothing?
The Serpent | Everything must have been created out of nothing. Look at that thick roll of hard flesh on your strong arm! That was not always there: you could not climb a tree when I first saw you. But you willed and tried and willed and tried; and your will created out of nothing the roll on your arm until you had your desire, and could draw yourself up with one hand and seat yourself on the bough that was above your head.
Eve | That was practice.
The Serpent | Things wear out by practice: they do not grow by it. Your hair streams in the wind as if it were trying to stretch itself further and further. But it does not grow longer for all its practice in streaming, because you have not willed it so. When Lilith told me what she had imagined in our silent language (for there were no words then) I bade her desire it and will it; and then, to our great wonder, the thing she had desired and willed created itself in her under the urging of her will. Then I too willed to renew myself as two instead of one; and after many days the miracle happened, and I burst from my skin another snake interlaced with me; and now there are two imaginations, two desires, two wills to create with.
Eve | To desire, to imagine, to will, to create. That is too long a story. Find me one word for it all: you, who are so clever at words.
The Serpent | In one word, to conceive. That is the word that means both the beginning in imagination and the end in creation.
Eve | Find me a word for the story Lilith imagined and told you in your silent language: the story that was too wonderful to be true, and yet came true.
The Serpent | A poem.
Eve | Find me another word for what Lilith was to me.
The Serpent | She was your mother.
Eve | And Adam’s mother?
The Serpent | Yes.
Eve | About to rise. I will go and tell Adam to conceive.
The Serpent | Laughs. !!!
Eve | Jarred and startled. What a hateful noise! What is the matter with you? No one has ever uttered such a sound before.
The Serpent | Adam cannot conceive.
Eve | Why?
The Serpent | Lilith did not imagine him so. He can imagine: he can will: he can desire: he can gather his life together for a great spring towards creation: he can create all things except one; and that one is his own kind.
Eve | Why did Lilith keep this from him?
The Serpent | Because if he could do that he could do without Eve.
Eve | That is true. It is I who must conceive.
The Serpent | Yes. By that he is tied to you.
Eve | And I to him!
The Serpent | Yes, until you create another Adam.
Eve | I had not thought of that. You are very subtle. But if I create another Eve he may turn to her and do without me. I will not create any Eves, only Adams.
The Serpent | They cannot renew themselves without Eves. Sooner or later you will die like the fawn; and the new Adams will be unable to create without new Eves. You can imagine such an end; but you cannot desire it, therefore cannot will it, therefore cannot create Adams only.
Eve | If I am to die like the fawn, why should not the rest die too? What do I care?
The Serpent | Life must not cease. That comes before everything. It is silly to say you do not care. You do care. It is that care that will prompt your imagination; inflame your desires; make your will irresistible; and create out of nothing.
Eve | Thoughtfully. There can be no such thing as nothing. The garden is full, not empty.
The Serpent | I had not thought of that. That is a great thought. Yes: there is no such thing as nothing, only things we cannot see. The chameleon eats the air.
Eve | I have another thought: I must tell it to Adam. Calling. Adam! Adam! Coo-ee!
Adam’s Voice | Coo-ee!
Eve | This will please him, and cure his fits of melancholy.
The Serpent | Do not tell him yet. I have not told you the great secret.
Eve | What more is there to tell? It is I who have to do the miracle.
The Serpent | No: he, too, must desire and will. But he must give his desire and his will to you.
Eve | How?
The Serpent | That is the great secret. Hush! he is coming.
Adam | Returning. Is there another voice in the garden besides our voices and the Voice? I heard a new voice.
Eve | Rising and running to him. Only think, Adam! Our snake has learnt to speak by listening to us.
Adam | Delighted. Is it so? He goes past her to the stone, and fondles the serpent.
The Serpent | Responding affectionately. It is so, dear Adam.
Eve | But I have more wonderful news than that. Adam: we need not live forever.
Adam | Dropping the snake’s head in his excitement. What! Eve: do not play with me about this. If only there may be an end some day, and yet no end! If only I can be relieved of the horror of having to endure myself forever! If only the care of this terrible garden may pass on to some other gardener! If only the sentinel set by the Voice can be relieved! If only the rest and sleep that enable me to bear it from day to day could grow after many days into an eternal rest, an eternal sleep, then I could face my days, however long they may last. Only, there must be some end, some end: I am not strong enough to bear eternity.
The Serpent | You need not live to see another summer; and yet there shall be no end.
Adam | That cannot be.
The Serpent | It can be.
Eve | It shall be.
The Serpent | It is. Kill me; and you will find another snake in the garden tomorrow. You will find more snakes than there are fingers on your hands.
Eve | I will make other Adams, other Eves.
Adam | I tell you you must not make up stories about this. It cannot happen.
The Serpent | I can remember when you were yourself a thing that could not happen. Yet you are.
Adam | Struck. That must be true. He sits down on the stone.
The Serpent | I will tell Eve the secret; and she will tell it to you.
Adam | The secret! He turns quickly towards the serpent, and in doing so puts his foot on something sharp. Oh!
Eve | What is it?
Adam | Rubbing his foot. A thistle. And there, next to it, a briar. And nettles, too! I am tired of pulling these things up to keep the garden pleasant for us forever.
The Serpent | They do not grow very fast. They will not overrun the whole garden for a long time: not until you have laid down your burden and gone to sleep forever. Why should you trouble yourself? Let the new Adams clear a place for themselves.
Adam | That is very true. You must tell us your secret. You see, Eve, what a splendid thing it is not to have to live forever.
Eve | Throwing herself down discontentedly and plucking at the grass. That is so like a man. The moment you find we need not last forever, you talk as if we were going to end today. You must clear away some of those horrid things, or we shall be scratched and stung whenever we forget to look where we are stepping.
Adam | Oh yes, some of them, of course. But only some. I will clear them away tomorrow.
The Serpent | Laughs. !!!
Adam | That is a funny noise to make. I like it.
Eve | I do not. Why do you make it again?
The Serpent | Adam has invented something new. He has invented tomorrow. You will invent things every day now that the burden of immortality is lifted from you.
Eve | Immortality? What is that?
The Serpent | My new word for having to live forever.
Eve | The serpent has made a beautiful word for being. Living.
Adam | Make me a beautiful word for doing things tomorrow; for that surely is a great and blessed invention.
The Serpent | Procrastination.
Eve | That is a sweet word. I wish I had a serpent’s tongue.
The Serpent | That may come too. Everything is possible.
Adam | Springing up in sudden terror. Oh!
Eve | What is the matter now?
Adam | My rest! My escape from life!
The Serpent | Death. That is the word.
Adam | There is a terrible danger in this procrastination.
Eve | What danger?
Adam | If I put off death until tomorrow, I shall never die. There is no such day as tomorrow, and never can be.
The Serpent | I am very subtle; but Man is deeper in his thought than I am. The woman knows that there is no such thing as nothing: the man knows that there is no such day as tomorrow. I do well to worship them.
Adam | If I am to overtake death, I must appoint a real day, not a tomorrow. When shall I die?
Eve | You may die when I have made another Adam. Not before. But then, as soon as you like. She rises, and passing behind him, strolls off carelessly to the tree and leans against it, stroking a ring of the snake.
Adam | There need be no hurry even then.
Eve | I see you will put it off until tomorrow.
Adam | And you? Will you die the moment you have made a new Eve?
Eve | Why should I? Are you eager to be rid of me? Only just now you wanted me to sit still and never move lest I should stumble and die like the fawn. Now you no longer care.
Adam | It does not matter so much now.
Eve | Angrily to the snake. This death that you have brought into the garden is an evil thing. He wants me to die.
The Serpent | To Adam. Do you want her to die?
Adam | No. It is I who am to die. Eve must not die before me. I should be lonely.
Eve | You could get one of the new Eves.
Adam | That is true. But they might not be quite the same. They could not: I feel sure of that. They would not have the same memories. They would be—I want a word for them.
The Serpent | Strangers.
Adam | Yes: that is a good hard word. Strangers.
Eve | When there are new Adams and new Eves we shall live in a garden of strangers. We shall need each other. She comes quickly behind him and turns up his face to her. Do not forget that, Adam. Never forget it.
Adam | Why should I forget it? It is I who have thought of it.
Eve | I, too, have thought of something. The fawn stumbled and fell and died. But you could come softly up behind me and She suddenly pounces on his shoulders and throws him forward on his face. throw me down so that I should die. I should not dare to sleep if there were no reason why you should not make me die.
Adam | Scrambling up in horror. Make you die!!! What a frightful thought!
The Serpent | Kill, kill, kill, kill. That is the word.
Eve | The new Adams and Eves might kill us. I shall not make them. She sits on the rock and pulls him down beside her, clasping him to her with her right arm.
The Serpent | You must. For if you do not there will be an end.
Adam | No: they will not kill us: they will feel as I do. There is something against it. The Voice in the garden will tell them that they must not kill, as it tells me.
The Serpent | The voice in the garden is your own voice.
Adam | It is; and it is not. It is something greater than me: I am only a part of it.
Eve | The Voice does not tell me not to kill you. Yet I do not want you to die before me. No voice is needed to make me feel that.
Adam | Throwing his arm round her shoulder with an expression of anguish. Oh no: that is plain without any voice. There is something that holds us together, something that has no word—
The Serpent | Love. Love. Love.
Adam | That is too short a word for so long a thing.
The Serpent | Laughs. !!!
Eve | Turning impatiently to the snake. That heart-biting sound again! Do not do it. Why do you do it?
The Serpent | Love may be too long a word for so short a thing soon. But when it is short it will be very sweet.
Adam | Ruminating. You puzzle me. My old trouble was heavy; but it was simple. These wonders that you promise to do may tangle up my being before they bring me the gift of death. I was troubled with the burden of eternal being; but I was not confused in my mind. If I did not know that I loved Eve, at least I did not know that she might cease to love me, and come to love some other Adam and desire my death. Can you find a name for that knowledge?
The Serpent | Jealousy. Jealousy. Jealousy.
Adam | A hideous word.
Eve | Shaking him. Adam: you must not brood. You think too much.
Adam | Angrily. How can I help brooding when the future has become uncertain? Anything is better than uncertainty. Life has become uncertain. Love is uncertain. Have you a word for this new misery?
The Serpent | Fear. Fear. Fear.
Adam | Have you a remedy for it?
The Serpent | Yes. Hope. Hope. Hope.
Adam | What is hope?
The Serpent | As long as you do not know the future you do not know that it will not be happier than the past. That is hope.
Adam | It does not console me. Fear is stronger in me than hope. I must have certainty. He rises threateningly. Give it to me; or I will kill you when next I catch you asleep.
Eve | Throwing her arms round the serpent. My beautiful snake. Oh no. How can you even think such a horror?
Adam | Fear will drive me to anything. The serpent gave me fear. Let it now give me certainty or go in fear of me.
The Serpent | Bind the future by your will. Make a vow.
Adam | What is a vow?
The Serpent | Choose a day for your death; and resolve to die on that day. Then death is no longer uncertain but certain. Let Eve vow to love you until your death. Then love will be no longer uncertain.
Adam | Yes: that is splendid: that will bind the future.
Eve | Displeased, turning away from the serpent. But it will destroy hope.
Adam | Angrily. Be silent, woman. Hope is wicked. Happiness is wicked. Certainty is blessed.
The Serpent | What is wicked? You have invented a word.
Adam | Whatever I fear to do is wicked. Listen to me, Eve; and you, snake, listen too, that your memory may hold my vow. I will live a thousand sets of the four seasons—
The Serpent | Years. Years.
Adam | I will live a thousand years; and then I will endure no more: I will die and take my rest. And I will love Eve all that time and no other woman.
Eve | And if Adam keeps his vow I will love no other man until he dies.
The Serpent | You have both invented marriage. And what he will be to you and not to any other woman is husband; and what you will be to him and not to any other man is wife.
Adam | Instinctively moving his hand towards her. Husband and wife.
Eve | Slipping her hand into his. Wife and husband.
The Serpent | Laughs. !!!
Eve | Snatching herself loose from Adam. Do not make that odious noise, I tell you.
Adam | Do not listen to her: the noise is good: it lightens my heart. You are a jolly snake. But you have not made a vow yet. What vow do you make?
The Serpent | I make no vows. I take my chance.
Adam | Chance? What does that mean?
The Serpent | It means that I fear certainty as you fear uncertainty. It means that nothing is certain but uncertainty. If I bind the future I bind my will. If I bind my will I strangle creation.
Eve | Creation must not be strangled. I tell you I will create, though I tear myself to pieces in the act.
Adam | Be silent, both of you. I will bind the future. I will be delivered from fear. To Eve. We have made our vows; and if you must create, you shall create within the bounds of those vows. You shall not listen to that snake any more. Come. He seizes her by the hair to drag her away.
Eve | Let me go, you fool. It has not yet told me the secret.
Adam | Releasing her. That is true. What is a fool?
Eve | I do not know: the word came to me. It is what you are when you forget and brood and are filled with fear. Let us listen to the snake.
Adam | No: I am afraid of it. I feel as if the ground were giving way under my feet when it speaks. Do you stay and listen to it.
The Serpent | Laughs. !!!
Adam | Brightening. That noise takes away fear. Funny. The snake and the woman are going to whisper secrets. He chuckles and goes away slowly, laughing his first laugh.
Eve | Now the secret. The secret. She sits on the rock and throws her arms round the serpent, who begins whispering to her.
Eve’s face lights up with intense interest, which increases until an expression of overwhelming repugnance takes its place. She buries her face in her hands.

Act II

A few centuries later. Morning. An oasis in Mesopotamia. Close at hand the end of a log house abuts on a kitchen garden. Adam is digging in the middle of the garden. On his right, Eve sits on a stool in the shadow of a tree by the doorway, spinning flax. Her wheel, which she turns by hand, is a large disc of heavy wood, practically a flywheel. At the opposite side of the garden is a thorn brake with a passage through it barred by a hurdle.

The two are scantily and carelessly dressed in rough linen and leaves. They have lost their youth and grace; and Adam has an unkempt beard and jaggedly cut hair; but they are strong and in the prime of life. Adam looks worried, like a farmer. Eve, better humored (having given up worrying), sits and spins and thinks.

A Man’s Voice | Hallo, mother!
Eve | Looking across the garden towards the hurdle. Here is Cain.
Adam | Uttering a grunt of disgust. !!! He goes on digging without raising his head.
Cain kicks the hurdle out of his way, and strides into the garden. In pose, voice, and dress he is insistently warlike. He is equipped with huge spear and broad brassbound leather shield; his casque is a tiger’s head with bull’s horns; he wears a scarlet cloak with gold brooch over a lion’s skin with the claws dangling; his feet are in sandals with brass ornaments; his shins are in brass greaves; and his bristling military moustache glistens with oil. To his parents he has the self-assertive, not-quite-at-ease manner of a revolted son who knows that he is not forgiven nor approved of.
Cain | To Adam. Still digging? Always dig, dig, dig. Sticking in the old furrow. No progress! no advanced ideas! no adventures! What should I be if I had stuck to the digging you taught me?
Adam | What are you now, with your shield and spear, and your brother’s blood crying from the ground against you?
Cain | I am the first murderer: you are only the first man. Anybody could be the first man: it is as easy as to be the first cabbage. To be the first murderer one must be a man of spirit.
Adam | Begone. Leave us in peace. The world is wide enough to keep us apart.
Eve | Why do you want to drive him away? He is mine. I made him out of my own body. I want to see my work sometimes.
Adam | You made Abel also. He killed Abel. Can you bear to look at him after that?
Cain | Whose fault was it that I killed Abel? Who invented killing? Did I? No: he invented it himself. I followed your teaching. I dug and dug and dug. I cleared away the thistles and briars. I ate the fruits of the earth. I lived in the sweat of my brow, as you do. I was a fool. But Abel was a discoverer, a man of ideas, of spirit: a true Progressive. He was the discoverer of blood. He was the inventor of killing. He found out that the fire of the sun could be brought down by a dewdrop. He invented the altar to keep the fire alive. He changed the beasts he killed into meat by the fire on the altar. He kept himself alive by eating meat. His meal cost him a day’s glorious health-giving sport and an hour’s amusing play with the fire. You learnt nothing from him: you drudged and drudged and drudged, and dug and dug and dug, and made me do the same. I envied his happiness, his freedom. I despised myself for not doing as he did instead of what you did. He became so happy that he shared his meal with the Voice that had whispered all his inventions to him. He said that the Voice was the voice of the fire that cooked his food, and that the fire that could cook could also eat. It was true: I saw the fire consume the food on his altar. Then I, too, made an altar, and offered my food on it, my grains, my roots, my fruit. Useless: nothing happened. He laughed at me; and then came my great idea: why not kill him as he killed the beasts? I struck; and he died, just as they did. Then I gave up your old silly drudging ways, and lived as he had lived, by the chase, by the killing, and by the fire. Am I not better than you? stronger, happier, freer?
Adam | You are not stronger: you are shorter in the wind: you cannot endure. You have made the beasts afraid of us; and the snake has invented poison to protect herself against you. I fear you myself. If you take a step towards your mother with that spear of yours I will strike you with my spade as you struck Abel.
Eve | He will not strike me. He loves me.
Adam | He loved his brother. But he killed him.
Cain | I do not want to kill women. I do not want to kill my mother. And for her sake I will not kill you, though I could send this spear through you without coming within reach of your spade. But for her, I could not resist the sport of trying to kill you, in spite of my fear that you would kill me. I have striven with a boar and with a lion as to which of us should kill the other. I have striven with a man: spear to spear and shield to shield. It is terrible; but there is no joy like it. I call it fighting. He who has never fought has never lived. That is what has brought me to my mother today.
Adam | What have you to do with one another now? She is the creator, you the destroyer.
Cain | How can I destroy unless she creates? I want her to create more and more men: aye, and more and more women, that they may in turn create more men. I have imagined a glorious poem of many men, of more men than there are leaves on a thousand trees. I will divide them into two great hosts. One of them I will lead; and the other will be led by the man I fear most and desire to fight and kill most. And each host shall try to kill the other host. Think of that! all those multitudes of men fighting, fighting, killing, killing! The four rivers running with blood! The shouts of triumph! the howls of rage! the curses of despair! the shrieks of torment! That will be life indeed: life lived to the very marrow: burning, overwhelming life. Every man who has not seen it, heard it, felt it, risked it, will feel a humbled fool in the presence of the man who has.
Eve | And I! I am to be a mere convenience to make men for you to kill!
Adam | Or to kill you, you fool.
Cain | Mother: the making of men is your right, your risk, your agony, your glory, your triumph. You make my father here your mere convenience, as you call it, for that. He has to dig for you, sweat for you, plod for you, like the ox who helps him to tear up the ground or the ass who carries his burdens for him. No woman shall make me live my father’s life. I will hunt: I will fight and strive to the very bursting of my sinews. When I have slain the boar at the risk of my life, I will throw it to my woman to cook, and give her a morsel of it for her pains. She shall have no other food; and that will make her my slave. And the man that slays me shall have her for his booty. Man shall be the master of Woman, not her baby and her drudge.
Adam throws down his spade, and stands looking darkly at Eve.
Eve | Are you tempted, Adam? Does this seem a better thing to you than love between us?
Cain | What does he know of love? Only when he has fought, when he has faced terror and death, when he has striven to the spending of the last rally of his strength, can he know what it is to rest in love in the arms of a woman. Ask that woman whom you made, who is also my wife, whether she would have me as I was in the days when I followed the ways of Adam, and was a digger and a drudge?
Eve | Angrily throwing down her distaff. What! You dare come here boasting about that good-for-nothing Lua, the worst of daughters and the worst of wives! You her master! You are more her slave than Adam’s ox or your own sheepdog. Forsooth, when you have slain the boar at the risk of your life, you will throw her a morsel of it for her pains! Ha! Poor wretch: do you think I do not know her, and know you, better than that? Do you risk your life when you trap the ermine and the sable and the blue fox to hang on her lazy shoulders and make her look more like an animal than a woman? When you have to snare the little tender birds because it is too much trouble for her to chew honest food, how much of a great warrior do you feel then? You slay the tiger at the risk of your life; but who gets the striped skin you have run that risk for? She takes it to lie on, and flings you the carrion flesh you cannot eat. You fight because you think that your fighting makes her admire and desire you. Fool: she makes you fight because you bring her the ornaments and the treasures of those you have slain, and because she is courted and propitiated with power and gold by the people who fear you. You say that I make a mere convenience of Adam: I who spin and keep the house, and bear and rear children, and am a woman and not a pet animal to please men and prey on them! What are you, you poor slave of a painted face and a bundle of skunk’s fur? You were a man-child when I bore you. Lua was a woman-child when I bore her. What have you made of yourselves?
Cain | Letting his spear fall into the crook of his shield arm, and twirling his moustache. There is something higher than man. There is hero and superman.
Eve | Superman! You are no superman: you are Anti-Man: you are to other men what the stoat is to the rabbit; and she is to you what the leech is to the stoat. You despise your father; but when he dies the world will be the richer because he lived. When you die, men will say, “He was a great warrior; but it would have been better for the world if he had never been born.” And of Lua they will say nothing; but when they think of her they will spit.
Cain | She is a better sort of woman to live with than you. If Lua nagged at me as you are nagging, and as you nag at Adam, I would beat her black and blue from head to foot. I have done it too, slave as you say I am.
Eve | Yes, because she looked at another man. And then you grovelled at her feet, and cried, and begged her to forgive you, and were ten times more her slave than ever; and she, when she had finished screaming and the pain went off a little, she forgave you, did she not?
Cain | She loved me more than ever. That is the true nature of woman.
Eve | Now pitying him maternally. Love! You call that love! You call that the nature of woman! My boy: this is neither man nor woman nor love nor life. You have no real strength in your bones nor sap in your flesh.
Cain | Ha! He seizes his spear and swings it muscularly.
Eve | Yes: you have to twirl a stick to feel your strength: you cannot taste life without making it bitter and boiling hot: you cannot love Lua until her face is painted, nor feel the natural warmth of her flesh until you have stuck a squirrel’s fur on it. You can feel nothing but a torment, and believe nothing but a lie. You will not raise your head to look at all the miracles of life that surround you; but you will run ten miles to see a fight or a death.
Adam | Enough said. Let the boy alone.
Cain | Boy! Ha! ha!
Eve | To Adam. You think, perhaps, that his way of life may be better than yours after all. You are still tempted. Well, will you pamper me as he pampers his woman? Will you kill tigers and bears until I have a heap of their skins to lounge on? Shall I paint my face and let my arms waste into pretty softness, and eat partridges and doves, and the flesh of kids whose milk you will steal for me?
Adam | You are hard enough to bear with as you are. Stay as you are; and I will stay as I am.
Cain | You neither of you know anything about life. You are simple country folk. You are the nurses and valets of the oxen and dogs and asses you have tamed to work for you. I can raise you out of that. I have a plan. Why not tame men and women to work for us? Why not bring them up from childhood never to know any other lot, so that they may believe that we are gods, and that they are here only to make life glorious for us?
Adam | Impressed. That is a great thought, certainly.
Eve | Contemptuously. Great thought!
Adam | Well, as the serpent used to say, why not?
Eve | Because I would not have such wretches in my house. Because I hate creatures with two heads, or with withered limbs, or that are distorted and perverted and unnatural. I have told Cain already that he is not a man and that Lua is not a woman: they are monsters. And now you want to make still more unnatural monsters, so that you may be utterly lazy and worthless, and that your tamed human animals may find work a blasting curse. A fine dream, truly! To Cain. Your father is a fool skin deep; but you are a fool to your very marrow; and your baggage of a wife is worse.
Adam | Why am I a fool? How am I a greater fool than you?
Eve | You said there would be no killing because the Voice would tell our children that they must not kill. Why did it not tell Cain that?
Cain | It did; but I am not a child to be afraid of a Voice. The Voice thought I was nothing but my brother’s keeper. It found that I was myself, and that it was for Abel to be himself also, and look to himself. He was not my keeper any more than I was his: why did he not kill me? There was no more to prevent him than there was to prevent me: it was man to man; and I won. I was the first conqueror.
Adam | What did the Voice say to you when you thought all that?
Cain | Why, it gave me right. It said that my deed was as a mark on me, a burnt-in mark such as Abel put on his sheep, that no man should slay me. And here I stand unslain, whilst the cowards who have never slain, the men who are content to be their brothers’ keepers instead of their masters, are despised and rejected, and slain like rabbits. He who bears the brand of Cain shall rule the earth. When he falls, he shall be avenged sevenfold: the Voice has said it; so beware how you plot against me, you and all the rest.
Adam | Cease your boasting and bullying, and tell the truth. Does not the Voice tell you that as no man dare slay you for murdering your brother, you ought to slay yourself?
Cain | No.
Adam | Then there is no such thing as divine justice, unless you are lying.
Cain | I am not lying: I dare all truths. There is divine justice. For the Voice tells me that I must offer myself to every man to be killed if he can kill me. Without danger I cannot be great. That is how I pay for Abel’s blood. Danger and fear follow my steps everywhere. Without them courage would have no sense. And it is courage, courage, courage, that raises the blood of life to crimson splendor.
Adam | Picking up his spade and preparing to dig again. Take yourself off then. This splendid life of yours does not last for a thousand years; and I must last for a thousand years. When you fighters do not get killed in fighting one another or fighting the beasts, you die from mere evil in yourselves. Your flesh ceases to grow like man’s flesh: it grows like a fungus on a tree. Instead of breathing you sneeze, or cough up your insides, and wither and perish. Your bowels become rotten; your hair falls from you; your teeth blacken and drop out; and you die before your time, not because you will, but because you must. I will dig, and live.
Cain | And pray, what use is this thousand years of life to you, you old vegetable? Do you dig any better because you have been digging for hundreds of years? I have not lived as long as you; but I know all there is to be known of the craft of digging. By quitting it I have set myself free to learn nobler crafts of which you know nothing. I know the craft of fighting and of hunting: in a word, the craft of killing. What certainty have you of your thousand years? I could kill both of you; and you could no more defend yourselves than a couple of sheep. I spare you; but others may kill you. Why not live bravely, and die early and make room for others? Why, I—I! that know many more crafts than either of you, am tired of myself when I am not fighting or hunting. Sooner than face a thousand years of it I should kill myself, as the Voice sometimes tempts me to do already.
Adam | Liar: you denied just now that it called on you to pay for Abel’s life with your own.
Cain | The Voice does not speak to me as it does to you. I am a man: you are only a grown-up child. One does not speak to a child as to a man. And a man does not listen and tremble in silence. He replies: he makes the Voice respect him: in the end he dictates what the Voice shall say.
Adam | May your tongue be accurst for such blasphemy!
Eve | Keep a guard on your own tongue; and do not curse my son. It was Lilith who did wrong when she shared the labor of creation so unequally between man and wife. If you, Cain, had had the trouble of making Abel, or had had to make another man to replace him when he was gone, you would not have killed him: you would have risked your own life to save his. That is why all this empty talk of yours, which tempted Adam just now when he threw down his spade and listened to you for a while, went by me like foul wind that has passed over a dead body. That is why there is enmity between Woman the creator and Man the destroyer. I know you: I am your mother. You are idle: you are selfish. It is long and hard and painful to create life: it is short and easy to steal the life others have made. When you dug, you made the earth live and bring forth as I live and bring forth. It was for that that Lilith set you free from the travail of women, not for theft and murder.
Cain | The Devil thank her for it! I can make better use of my time than to play the husband to the clay beneath my feet.
Adam | Devil? What new word is that?
Cain | Hearken to me, old fool. I have never in my soul listened willingly when you have told me of the Voice that whispers to you. There must be two Voices: one that gulls and despises you, and another that trusts and respects me. I call yours the Devil. Mine I call the Voice of God.
Adam | Mine is the Voice of Life: yours the Voice of Death.
Cain | Be it so. For it whispers to me that death is not really death: that it is the gate of another life: a life infinitely splendid and intense: a life of the soul alone: a life without clods or spades, hunger or fatigue—
Eve | Selfish and idle, Cain. I know.
Cain | Selfish, yes: a life in which no man is his brother’s keeper, because his brother can keep himself. But am I idle? In rejecting your drudgery, have I not embraced evils and agonies of which you know nothing? The arrow is lighter in the hand than the spade; but the energy that drives it through the breast of a fighter is as fire to water compared with the strength that drives the spade into the harmless dirty clay. My strength is as the strength of ten because my heart is pure.
Adam | What is that word? What is pure?
Cain | Turned from the clay. Turned upward to the sun, to the clear clean heavens.
Adam | The heavens are empty, child. The earth is fruitful. The earth feeds us. It gives us the strength by which we made you and all mankind. Cut off from the clay which you despise, you would perish miserably.
Cain | I revolt against the clay. I revolt against the food. You say it gives us strength: does it not also turn into filth and smite us with diseases? I revolt against these births that you and mother are so proud of. They drag us down to the level of the beasts. If that is to be the last thing as it has been the first, let mankind perish. If I am to eat like a bear, if Lua is to bring forth cubs like a bear, then I had rather be a bear than a man; for the bear is not ashamed: he knows no better. If you are content, like the bear, I am not. Stay with the woman who gives you children: I will go to the woman who gives me dreams. Grope in the ground for your food: I will bring it from the skies with my arrows, or strike it down as it roams the earth in the pride of its life. If I must have food or die, I will at least have it at as far a remove from the earth as I can. The ox shall make it something nobler than grass before it comes to me. And as the man is nobler than the ox, I shall some day let my enemy eat the ox; and then I will slay and eat him.
Adam | Monster! You hear this, Eve?
Eve | So that is what comes of turning your face to the clean clear heavens! Man-eating! Child-eating! For that is what it would come to, just as it came to lambs and kids when Abel began with sheep and goats. You are a poor silly creature after all. Do you think I never have these thoughts: I! who have the labor of the childbearing: I! who have the drudgery of preparing the food? I thought for a moment that perhaps this strong brave son of mine, who could imagine something better, and could desire what he imagined, might also be able to will what he desired until he created it. And all that comes of it is that he wants to be a bear and eat children. Even a bear would not eat a man if it could get honey instead.
Cain | I do not want to be a bear. I do not want to eat children. I do not know what I want, except that I want to be something higher and nobler than this stupid old digger whom Lilith made to help you to bring me into the world, and whom you despise now that he has served your turn.
Adam | In sullen rage. I have half a mind to show you that my spade can split your undutiful head open, in spite of your spear.
Cain | Undutiful! Ha! ha! Flourishing his spear. Try it, old everybody’s father. Try a taste of fighting.
Eve | Peace, peace, you two fools. Sit down and be quiet; and listen to me. Adam, with a weary shrug, throws down his spade. Cain, with a laughing one, throws down his shield and spear. Both sit on the ground. I hardly know which of you satisfies me least, you with your dirty digging, or he with his dirty killing. I cannot think it was for either of these cheap ways of life that Lilith set you free. To Adam. You dig roots and coax grains out of the earth: why do you not draw down a divine sustenance from the skies? He steals and kills for his food; and makes up idle poems of life after death; and dresses up his terror-ridden life with fine words and his disease-ridden body with fine clothes, so that men may glorify and honor him instead of cursing him as murderer and thief. All you men, except only Adam, are my sons, or my sons’ sons, or my sons’ sons’ sons: you all come to see me: you all show off before me: all your little wisdoms and accomplishments are trotted out before mother Eve. The diggers come: the fighters and killers come: they are both very dull; for they either complain to me of the last harvest, or boast to me of the last fight; and one harvest is just like another, and the last fight only a repetition of the first. Oh, I have heard it all a thousand times. They tell me too of their last-born: the clever thing the darling child said yesterday, and how much more wonderful or witty or quaint it is than any child that ever was born before. And I have to pretend to be surprised, delighted, interested; though the last child is like the first, and has said and done nothing that did not delight Adam and me when you and Abel said it. For you were the first children in the world, and filled us with such wonder and delight as no couple can ever again feel while the world lasts. When I can bear no more, I go to our old garden, that is now a mass of nettles and thistles, in the hope of finding the serpent to talk to. But you have made the serpent our enemy: she has left the garden, or is dead: I never see her now. So I have to come back and listen to Adam saying the same thing for the ten-thousandth time, or to receive a visit from the last great-great-grandson who has grown up and wants to impress me with his importance. Oh, it is dreary, dreary! And there is yet nearly seven hundred years of it to endure.
Cain | Poor mother! You see, life is too long. One tires of everything. There is nothing new under the sun.
Adam | To Eve, grumpily. Why do you live on, if you can find nothing better to do than complain?
Eve | Because there is still hope.
Cain | Of what?
Eve | Of the coming true of your dreams and mine. Of newly created things. Of better things. My sons and my son’s sons are not all diggers and fighters. Some of them will neither dig nor fight: they are more useless than either of you: they are weaklings and cowards: they are vain; yet they are dirty and will not take the trouble to cut their hair. They borrow and never pay; but one gives them what they want, because they tell beautiful lies in beautiful words. They can remember their dreams. They can dream without sleeping. They have not will enough to create instead of dreaming; but the serpent said that every dream could be willed into creation by those strong enough to believe in it. There are others who cut reeds of different lengths and blow through them, making lovely patterns of sound in the air; and some of them can weave the patterns together, sounding three reeds at the same time, and raising my soul to things for which I have no words. And others make little mammoths out of clay, or make faces appear on flat stones, and ask me to create women for them with such faces. I have watched those faces and willed; and then I have made a woman-child that has grown up quite like them. And others think of numbers without having to count on their fingers, and watch the sky at night, and give names to the stars, and can foretell when the sun will be covered with a black saucepan lid. And there is Tubal, who made this wheel for me which has saved me so much labor. And there is Enoch, who walks on the hills, and hears the Voice continually, and has given up his will to do the will of the Voice, and has some of the Voice’s greatness. When they come, there is always some new wonder, or some new hope: something to live for. They never want to die, because they are always learning and always creating either things or wisdom, or at least dreaming of them. And then you, Cain, come to me with your stupid fighting and destroying, and your foolish boasting; and you want me to tell you that it is all splendid, and that you are heroic, and that nothing but death or the dread of death makes life worth living. Away with you, naughty child; and do you, Adam, go on with your work and not waste your time listening to him.
Cain | I am not, perhaps, very clever; but—
Eve | Interrupting him. Perhaps not; but do not begin to boast of that. It is no credit to you.
Cain | For all that, mother, I have an instinct which tells me that death plays its part in life. Tell me this: who invented death?
Adam springs to his feet. Eve drops her distaff. Both show the greatest consternation.
Cain | What is the matter with you both?
Adam | Boy: you have asked us a terrible question.
Eve | You invented murder. Let that be enough for you.
Cain | Murder is not death. You know what I mean. Those whom I slay would die if I spared them. If I am not slain, yet I shall die. Who put this upon me? I say, who invented death?
Adam | Be reasonable, boy. Could you bear to live forever? You think you could, because you know that you will never have to make your thought good. But I have known what it is to sit and brood under the terror of eternity, of immortality. Think of it, man: to have no escape! to be Adam, Adam, Adam through more days than there are grains of sand by the two rivers, and then be as far from the end as ever! I, who have so much in me that I hate and long to cast off! Be thankful to your parents, who enabled you to hand on your burden to new and better men, and won for you an eternal rest; for it was we who invented death.
Cain | Rising. You did well: I, too, do not want to live forever. But if you invented death, why do you blame me, who am a minister of death?
Adam | I do not blame you. Go in peace. Leave me to my digging, and your mother to her spinning.
Cain | Well, I will leave you to it, though I have shown you a better way. He picks up his shield and spear. I will go back to my brave warrior friends and their splendid women. He strides to the thorn brake. When Adam delved and Eve span, where was then the gentleman? He goes away roaring with laughter, which ceases as he cries from the distance. Goodbye, mother.
Adam | Grumbling. He might have put the hurdle back, lazy hound! He replaces the hurdle across the passage.
Eve | Through him and his like, death is gaining on life. Already most of our grandchildren die before they have sense enough to know how to live.
Adam | No matter. He spits on his hands, and takes up the spade again. Life is still long enough to learn to dig, short as they are making it.
Eve | Musing. Yes, to dig. And to fight. But is it long enough for the other things, the great things? Will they live long enough to eat manna?
Adam | What is manna?
Eve | Food drawn down from heaven, made out of the air, not dug dirtily from the earth. Will they learn all the ways of all the stars in their little time? It took Enoch two hundred years to learn to interpret the will of the Voice. When he was a mere child of eighty, his babyish attempts to understand the Voice were more dangerous than the wrath of Cain. If they shorten their lives, they will dig and fight and kill and die; and their baby Enochs will tell them that it is the will of the Voice that they should dig and fight and kill and die forever.
Adam | If they are lazy and have a will towards death I cannot help it. I will live my thousand years: if they will not, let them die and be damned.
Eve | Damned? What is that?
Adam | The state of them that love death more than life. Go on with your spinning; and do not sit there idle while I am straining my muscles for you.
Eve | Slowly taking up her distaff. If you were not a fool you would find something better for both of us to live by than this spinning and digging.
Adam | Go on with your work, I tell you; or you shall go without bread.
Eve | Man need not always live by bread alone. There is something else. We do not yet know what it is; but some day we shall find out; and then we will live on that alone; and there shall be no more digging nor spinning, nor fighting nor killing.
She spins resignedly; he digs impatiently.

Act II

A courtyard before the columned portico of a temple. The temple door is in the middle of the portico. A veiled and robed woman of majestic carriage passes along behind the columns towards the entrance. From the opposite direction a man of compact figure, clean-shaven, saturnine, and self-centred: in short, very like Napoleon I, and wearing a military uniform of Napoleonic cut, marches with measured steps; places his hand in his lapel in the traditional manner; and fixes the woman with his eye. She stops, her attitude expressing haughty amazement at his audacity. He is on her right: she on his left.

Napoleon | Impressively. I am the Man of Destiny.
The Veiled Woman | Unimpressed. How did you get in here?
Napoleon | I walked in. I go on until I am stopped. I never am stopped. I tell you I am the Man of Destiny.
The Veiled Woman | You will be a man of very short destiny if you wander about here without one of our children to guide you. I suppose you belong to the Baghdad envoy.
Napoleon | I came with him; but I do not belong to him. I belong to myself. Direct me to the oracle if you can. If not, do not waste my time.
The Veiled Woman | Your time, poor creature, is short. I will not waste it. Your envoy and his party will be here presently. The consultation of the oracle is arranged for them, and will take place according to the prescribed ritual. You can wait here until they come. She turns to go into the temple.
Napoleon | I never wait. She stops. The prescribed ritual is, I believe, the classical one of the pythoness on her tripod, the intoxicating fumes arising from the abyss, the convulsions of the priestess as she delivers the message of the God, and so on. That sort of thing does not impose on me: I use it myself to impose on simpletons. I believe that what is, is. I know that what is not, is not. The antics of a woman sitting on a tripod and pretending to be drunk do not interest me. Her words are put into her mouth, not by a god, but by a man three hundred years old, who has had the capacity to profit by his experience. I wish to speak to that man face to face, without mummery or imposture.
The Veiled Woman | You seem to be an unusually sensible person. But there is no old man. I am the oracle on duty today. I am on my way to take my place on the tripod, and go through the usual mummery, as you rightly call it, to impress your friend the envoy. As you are superior to that kind of thing, you may consult me now. She leads the way into the middle of the courtyard. What do you want to know?
Napoleon | Following her. Madam: I have not come all this way to discuss matters of State with a woman. I must ask you to direct me to one of your oldest and ablest men.
The Oracle | None of our oldest and ablest men or women would dream of wasting their time on you. You would die of discouragement in their presence in less than three hours.
Napoleon | You can keep this idle fable of discouragement for people credulous enough to be intimidated by it, madam. I do not believe in metaphysical forces.
The Oracle | No one asks you to. A field is something physical, is it not. Well, I have a field.
Napoleon | I have several million fields. I am Emperor of Turania.
The Oracle | You do not understand. I am not speaking of an agricultural field. Do you not know that every mass of matter in motion carries with it an invisible gravitational field, every magnet an invisible magnetic field, and every living organism a mesmeric field? Even you have a perceptible mesmeric field. Feeble as it is, it is the strongest I have yet observed in a short-liver.
Napoleon | By no means feeble, madam. I understand you now; and I may tell you that the strongest characters blench in my presence, and submit to my domination. But I do not call that a physical force.
The Oracle | What else do you call it, pray? Our physicists deal with it. Our mathematicians express its measurements in algebraic equations.
Napoleon | Do you mean that they could measure mine?
The Oracle | Yes: by a figure infinitely near to zero. Even in us the force is negligible during our first century of life. In our second it develops quickly, and becomes dangerous to short-livers who venture into its field. If I were not veiled and robed in insulating material you could not endure my presence; and I am still a young woman: one hundred and seventy if you wish to know exactly.
Napoleon | Folding his arms. I am not intimidated: no woman alive, old or young, can put me out of countenance. Unveil, madam. Disrobe. You will move this temple as easily as shake me.
The Oracle | Very well. She throws back her veil.
Napoleon | Shrieking, staggering, and covering his eyes. No. Stop. Hide your face again. Shutting his eyes and distractedly clutching at his throat and heart. Let me go. Help! I am dying.
The Oracle | Do you still wish to consult an older person?
Napoleon | No, no. The veil, the veil, I beg you.
The Oracle | Replacing the veil. So.
Napoleon | Ouf! One cannot always be at one’s best. Twice before in my life I have lost my nerve and behaved like a poltroon. But I warn you not to judge my quality by these involuntary moments.
The Oracle | I have no occasion to judge of your quality. You want my advice. Speak quickly; or I shall go about my business.
Napoleon | After a moment’s hesitation, sinks respectfully on one knee. I—
The Oracle | Oh, rise, rise. Are you so foolish as to offer me this mummery which even you despise?
Napoleon | Rising. I knelt in spite of myself. I compliment you on your impressiveness, madam.
The Oracle | Impatiently. Time! time! time! time!
Napoleon | You will not grudge me the necessary time, madam, when you know my case. I am a man gifted with a certain specific talent in a degree altogether extraordinary. I am not otherwise a very extraordinary person: my family is not influential; and without this talent I should cut no particular figure in the world.
The Oracle | Why cut a figure in the world?
Napoleon | Superiority will make itself felt, madam. But when I say I possess this talent I do not express myself accurately. The truth is that my talent possesses me. It is genius. It drives me to exercise it. I must exercise it. I am great when I exercise it. At other moments I am nobody.
The Oracle | Well, exercise it. Do you need an oracle to tell you that?
Napoleon | Wait. This talent involves the shedding of human blood.
The Oracle | Are you a surgeon, or a dentist?
Napoleon | Psha! You do not appreciate me, madam. I mean the shedding of oceans of blood, the death of millions of men.
The Oracle | They object, I suppose.
Napoleon | Not at all. They adore me.
The Oracle | Indeed!
Napoleon | I have never shed blood with my own hand. They kill each other: they die with shouts of triumph on their lips. Those who die cursing do not curse me. My talent is to organize this slaughter; to give mankind this terrible joy which they call glory; to let loose the devil in them that peace has bound in chains.
The Oracle | And you? Do you share their joy?
Napoleon | Not at all. What satisfaction is it to me to see one fool pierce the entrails of another with a bayonet? I am a man of princely character, but of simple personal tastes and habits. I have the virtues of a laborer: industry and indifference to personal comfort. But I must rule, because I am so superior to other men that it is intolerable to me to be misruled by them. Yet only as a slayer can I become a ruler. I cannot be great as a writer: I have tried and failed. I have no talent as a sculptor or painter; and as lawyer, preacher, doctor, or actor, scores of second-rate men can do as well as I, or better. I am not even a diplomatist: I can only play my trump card of force. What I can do is to organize war. Look at me! I seem a man like other men, because nine-tenths of me is common humanity. But the other tenth is a faculty for seeing things as they are that no other man possesses.
The Oracle | You mean that you have no imagination?
Napoleon | Forcibly. I mean that I have the only imagination worth having: the power of imagining things as they are, even when I cannot see them. You feel yourself my superior, I know: nay, you are my superior: have I not bowed my knee to you by instinct? Yet I challenge you to a test of our respective powers. Can you calculate what the methematicians call vectors, without putting a single algebraic symbol on paper? Can you launch ten thousand men across a frontier and a chain of mountains and know to a mile exactly where they will be at the end of seven weeks? The rest is nothing: I got it all from the books at my military school. Now this great game of war, this playing with armies as other men play with bowls and skittles, is one which I must go on playing, partly because a man must do what he can and not what he would like to do, and partly because, if I stop, I immediately lose my power and become a beggar in the land where I now make men drunk with glory.
The Oracle | No doubt then you wish to know how to extricate yourself from this unfortunate position?
Napoleon | It is not generally considered unfortunate, madam. Supremely fortunate rather.
The Oracle | If you think so, go on making them drunk with glory. Why trouble me with their folly and your vectors?
Napoleon | Unluckily, madam, men are not only heroes: they are also cowards. They desire glory; but they dread death.
The Oracle | Why should they? Their lives are too short to be worth living. That is why they think your game of war worth playing.
Napoleon | They do not look at it quite in that way. The most worthless soldier wants to live forever. To make him risk being killed by the enemy I have to convince him that if he hesitates he will inevitably be shot at dawn by his own comrades for cowardice.
The Oracle | And if his comrades refuse to shoot him?
Napoleon | They will be shot too, of course.
The Oracle | By whom?
Napoleon | By their comrades.
The Oracle | And if they refuse?
Napoleon | Up to a certain point they do not refuse.
The Oracle | But when that point is reached, you have to do the shooting yourself, eh?
Napoleon | Unfortunately, madam, when that point is reached, they shoot me.
The Oracle | Mf! It seems to me they might as well shoot you first as last. Why don’t they?
Napoleon | Because their love of fighting, their desire for glory, their shame of being branded as dastards, their instinct to test themselves in terrible trials, their fear of being killed or enslaved by the enemy, their belief that they are defending their hearths and homes, overcome their natural cowardice, and make them willing not only to risk their own lives but to kill everyone who refuses to take that risk. But if war continues too long, there comes a time when the soldiers, and also the taxpayers who are supporting and munitioning them, reach a condition which they describe as being fed up. The troops have proved their courage, and want to go home and enjoy in peace the glory it has earned them. Besides, the risk of death for each soldier becomes a certainty if the fighting goes on forever: he hopes to escape for six months, but knows he cannot escape for six years. The risk of bankruptcy for the citizen becomes a certainty in the same way. Now what does this mean for me?
The Oracle | Does that matter in the midst of such calamity?
Napoleon | Psha! madam: it is the only thing that matters: the value of human life is the value of the greatest living man. Cut off that infinitesimal layer of grey matter which distinguishes my brain from that of the common man, and you cut down the stature of humanity from that of a giant to that of a nobody. I matter supremely: my soldiers do not matter at all: there are plenty more where they came from. If you kill me, or put a stop to my activity (it is the same thing), the nobler part of human life perishes. You must save the world from that catastrophe, madam. War has made me popular, powerful, famous, historically immortal. But I foresee that if I go on to the end it will leave me execrated, dethroned, imprisoned, perhaps executed. Yet if I stop fighting I commit suicide as a great man and become a common one. How am I to escape the horns of this tragic dilemma? Victory I can guarantee: I am invincible. But the cost of victory is the demoralization, the depopulation, the ruin of the victors no less than of the vanquished. How am I to satisfy my genius by fighting until I die? that is my question to you.
The Oracle | Were you not rash to venture into these sacred islands with such a question on your lips? Warriors are not popular here, my friend.
Napoleon | If a soldier were restrained by such a consideration, madam, he would no longer be a soldier. Besides, He produces a pistol. I have not come unarmed.
The Oracle | What is that thing?
Napoleon | It is an instrument of my profession, madam. I raise this hammer; I point the barrel at you; I pull this trigger that is against my forefinger; and you fall dead.
The Oracle | Show it to me. She puts out her hand to take it from him.
Napoleon | Retreating a step. Pardon me, madam. I never trust my life in the hands of a person over whom I have no control.
The Oracle | Sternly. Give it to me. She raises her hand to her veil.
Napoleon | Dropping the pistol and covering his eyes. Quarter! Kamerad! Take it, madam: He kicks it towards her. I surrender.
The Oracle | Give me that thing. Do you expect me to stoop for it?
Napoleon | Taking his hands from his eyes with an effort. A poor victory, madam: He picks up the pistol and hands it to her. there was no vector strategy needed to win it. Making a pose of his humiliation. But enjoy your triumph: you have made me—ME! Cain Adamson Charles Napoleon! Emperor of Turania! cry for quarter.
The Oracle | The way out of your difficulty, Cain Adamson, is very simple.
Napoleon | Eagerly. Good. What is it?
The Oracle | To die before the tide of glory turns. Allow me. She shoots him.
He falls with a shriek. She throws the pistol away and goes haughtily into the temple.
Napoleon | Scrambling to his feet. Murderess! Monster! She-devil! Unnatural, inhuman wretch! You deserve to be hanged, guillotined, broken on the wheel, burnt alive. No sense of the sacredness of human life! No thought for my wife and children! Bitch! Sow! Wanton! He picks up the pistol. And missed me at five yards! That’s a woman all over.
He is going away whence he came when Zoo arrives and confronts him at the head of a party consisting of the British Envoy, the Elderly Gentleman, the Envoy’s wife, and her daughter, aged about eighteen. The envoy, a typical politician, looks like an imperfectly reformed criminal disguised by a good tailor. The dress of the ladies is coeval with that of the Elderly Gentleman, and suitable for public official ceremonies in western capitals at the XVIII–XIX fin de siècle.
They file in under the portico. Zoo immediately comes out imperiously to Napoleon’s right, whilst the Envoy’s wife hurries effusively to his left. The Envoy meanwhile passes along behind the columns to the door, followed by his daughter. The Elderly Gentleman stops just where he entered, to see why Zoo has swooped so abruptly on the Emperor of Turania.
Zoo | To Napoleon, severely. What are you doing here by yourself? You have no business to go about here alone. What was that noise just now? What is that in your hand?
Napoleon glares at her in speechless fury; pockets the pistol; and produces a whistle.
The Envoy’s Wife | Arnt you coming with us to the oracle, sire?
Napoleon | To hell with the oracle, and with you too! He turns to go.
Together.
The Envoy’s Wife | Oh, sire!!
Zoo | Where are you going?
Napoleon | To fetch the police. He goes out past Zoo, almost jostling her, and blowing piercing blasts on his whistle.
Zoo | Whipping out her tuning-fork and intoning. Hallo Galway Central. The whistling continues. Stand by to isolate. To the Elderly Gentleman, who is staring after the whistling Emperor. How far has he gone?
The Elderly Gentleman | To that curious statue of a fat old man.
Zoo | Quickly, intoning. Isolate the Falstaff monument isolate hard. Paralyze—The whistling stops. Thank you. She puts up her tuning-fork. He shall not move a muscle until I come to fetch him.
The Envoy’s Wife | Oh! he will be frightfully angry! Did you hear what he said to me?
Zoo | Much we care for his anger!
The Daughter | Coming forward between her mother and Zoo. Please, madam, whose statue is it? and where can I buy a picture postcard of it? It is so funny. I will take a snapshot when we are coming back; but they come out so badly sometimes.
Zoo | They will give you pictures and toys in the temple to take away with you. The story of the statue is too long. It would bore you. She goes past them across the courtyard to get rid of them.
The Wife | Gushing. Oh no, I assure you.
The Daughter | Copying her mother. We should be so interested.
Zoo | Nonsense! All I can tell you about it is that a thousand years ago, when the whole world was given over to you short-lived people, there was a war called the War to end War. In the war which followed it about ten years later, hardly any soldiers were killed; but seven of the capital cities of Europe were wiped out of existence. It seems to have been a great joke: for the statesmen who thought they had sent ten million common men to their deaths were themselves blown into fragments with their houses and families, while the ten million men lay snugly in the caves they had dug for themselves. Later on even the houses escaped; but their inhabitants were poisoned by gas that spared no living soul. Of course the soldiers starved and ran wild; and that was the end of pseudo-Christian civilization. The last civilized thing that happened was that the statesmen discovered that cowardice was a great patriotic virtue; and a public monument was erected to its first preacher, an ancient and very fat sage called Sir John Falstaff. Well, pointing that’s Falstaff.
The Elderly Gentleman | Coming from the portico to his granddaughter’s right. Great Heavens! And at the base of this monstrous poltroon’s statue the War God of Turania is now gibbering impotently.
Zoo | Serve him right! War God indeed!
The Envoy | Coming between his wife and Zoo. I don’t know any history: a modern Prime Minister has something better to do than sit reading books; but—
The Elderly Gentleman | Interrupting him encouragingly. You make history, Ambrose.
The Envoy | Well, perhaps I do; and perhaps history makes me. I hardly recognize myself in the newspapers sometimes, though I suppose leading articles are the materials of history, as you might say. But what I want to know is, how did war come back again? and how did they make those poisonous gases you speak of? We should be glad to know; for they might come in very handy if we have to fight Turania. Of course I am all for peace, and don’t hold with the race of armaments in principle; still, we must keep ahead or be wiped out.
Zoo | You can make the gases for yourselves when your chemists find out how. Then you will do as you did before: poison each other until there are no chemists left, and no civilization. You will then begin all over again as half-starved ignorant savages, and fight with boomerangs and poisoned arrows until you work up to the poison gases and high explosives once more, with the same result. That is, unless we have sense enough to make an end of this ridiculous game by destroying you.
The Envoy | Aghast. Destroying us!
The Elderly Gentleman | I told you, Ambrose. I warned you.
The Envoy | But—
Zoo | Impatiently. I wonder what Zozim is doing. He ought to be here to receive you.
The Elderly Gentleman | Do you mean that rather insufferable young man whom you found boring me on the pier?
Zoo | Yes. He has to dress-up in a Druid’s robe, and put on a wig and a long false beard, to impress you silly people. I have to put on a purple mantle. I have no patience with such mummery; but you expect it from us; so I suppose it must be kept up. Will you wait here until Zozim comes, please. She turns to enter the temple.
The Envoy | My good lady, is it worth while dressing-up and putting on false beards for us if you tell us beforehand that it is all humbug?
Zoo | One would not think so; but if you won’t believe in anyone who is not dressed-up, why, we must dress-up for you. It was you who invented all this nonsense, not we.
The Elderly Gentleman | But do you expect us to be impressed after this?
Zoo | I don’t expect anything. I know, as a matter of experience, that you will be impressed. The oracle will frighten you out of your wits. She goes into the temple.
The Wife | These people treat us as if we were dirt beneath their feet. I wonder at you putting up with it, Amby. It would serve them right if we went home at once: wouldn’t it, Eth?
The Daughter | Yes, mamma. But perhaps they wouldn’t mind.
The Envoy | No use talking like that, Molly. I’ve got to see this oracle. The folks at home won’t know how we have been treated: all they’ll know is that I’ve stood face to face with the oracle and had the straight tip from her. I hope this Zozim chap is not going to keep us waiting much longer; for I feel far from comfortable about the approaching interview; and that’s the honest truth.
The Elderly Gentleman | I never thought I should want to see that man again; but now I wish he would take charge of us instead of Zoo. She was charming at first: quite charming; but she turned into a fiend because I had a few words with her. You would not believe: she very nearly killed me. You heard what she said just now. She belongs to a party here which wants to have us all killed.
The Wife | Terrified. Us! But we have done nothing: we have been as nice to them as nice could be. Oh, Amby, come away, come away: there is something dreadful about this place and these people.
The Envoy | There is, and no mistake. But you’re safe with me: you ought to have sense enough to know that.
The Elderly Gentleman | I am sorry to say, Molly, that it is not merely us four poor weak creatures they want to kill, but the entire race of Man, except themselves.
The Envoy | Not so poor neither, Poppa. Nor so weak, if you are going to take in all the Powers. If it comes to killing, two can play at that game, long-lived or short-lived.
The Elderly Gentleman | No, Ambrose: we should have no chance. We are worms beside these fearful people: mere worms.
Zozim comes from the temple, robed majestically, and wearing a wreath of mistletoe in his flowing white wig. His false beard reaches almost to his waist. He carries a staff with a curiously carved top.
Zozim | In the doorway, impressively. Hail, strangers!
All | Reverently. Hail!
Zozim | Are ye prepared?
The Envoy | We are.
Zozim | Unexpectedly becoming conversational, and strolling down carelessly to the middle of the group between the two ladies. Well, I’m sorry to say the oracle is not. She was delayed by some member of your party who got loose; and as the show takes a bit of arranging, you will have to wait a few minutes. The ladies can go inside and look round the entrance hall and get pictures and things if they want them.
Together.
The Wife | Thank you.
The Daughter | I should like to very much.
They go into the temple.
The Elderly Gentleman | In dignified rebuke of Zozim’s levity. Taken in this spirit, sir, the show, as you call it, becomes almost an insult to our common sense.
Zozim | Quite, I should say. You need not keep it up with me.
The Envoy | Suddenly making himself very agreeable. Just so: just so. We can wait as long as you please. And now, if I may be allowed to seize the opportunity of a few minutes’ friendly chat—?
Zozim | By all means, if only you will talk about things I can understand.
The Envoy | Well, about this colonizing plan of yours. My father-in-law here has been telling me something about it; and he has just now let out that you want not only to colonize us, but to—to—to—well, shall we say to supersede us? Now why supersede us? Why not live and let live? Theres not a scrap of ill-feeling on our side. We should welcome a colony of immortals—we may almost call you that—in the British Middle East. No doubt the Turanian Empire, with its Muhammadan traditions, overshadows us now. We have had to bring the Emperor with us on this expedition, though of course you know as well as I do that he has imposed himself on my party just to spy on me. I don’t deny that he has the whip hand of us to some extent, because if it came to a war none of our generals could stand up against him. I give him best at that game: he is the finest soldier in the world. Besides, he is an emperor and an autocrat; and I am only an elected representative of the British democracy. Not that our British democrats won’t fight: they will fight the heads off all the Turanians that ever walked; but then it takes so long to work them up to it, while he has only to say the word and march. But you people would never get on with him. Believe me, you would not be as comfortable in Turania as you would be with us. We understand you. We like you. We are easygoing people; and we are rich people. That will appeal to you. Turania is a poor place when all is said. Five-eighths of it is desert. They don’t irrigate as we do. Besides—now I am sure this will appeal to you and to all right-minded men—we are Christians.
Zozim | The old uns prefer Muhammadans.
The Envoy | Shocked. What!
Zozim | Distinctly. They prefer Muhammadans. What’s wrong with that?
The Envoy | Well, of all the disgraceful—
The Elderly Gentleman | Diplomatically interrupting his scandalized son-in-law. There can be no doubt, I am afraid, that by clinging too long to the obsolete features of the old pseudo-Christian Churches we allowed the Muhammadans to get ahead of us at a very critical period of the development of the Eastern world. When the Muhammadan Reformation took place, it left its followers with the enormous advantage of having the only established religion in the world in whose articles of faith any intelligent and educated person could believe.
The Envoy | But what about our Reformation? Don’t give the show away, Poppa. We followed suit, didn’t we?
The Elderly Gentleman | Unfortunately, Ambrose, we could not follow suit very rapidly. We had not only a religion to deal with, but a Church.
Zozim | What is a Church?
The Envoy | Not know what a Church is! Well!
The Elderly Gentleman | You must excuse me; but if I attempted to explain you would only ask me what a bishop is; and that is a question that no mortal man can answer. All I can tell you is that Muhammad was a truly wise man; for he founded a religion without a Church; consequently when the time came for a Reformation of the mosques there were no bishops and priests to obstruct it. Our bishops and priests prevented us for two hundred years from following suit; and we have never recovered the start we lost then. I can only plead that we did reform our Church at last. No doubt we had to make a few compromises as a matter of good taste; but there is now very little in our Articles of Religion that is not accepted as at least allegorically true by our Higher Criticism.
The Envoy | Encouragingly. Besides, does it matter? Why, I have never read the Articles in my life; and I am Prime Minister! Come! if my services in arranging for the reception of a colonizing party would be acceptable, they are at your disposal. And when I say a reception I mean a reception. Royal honors, mind you! A salute of a hundred and one guns! The streets lined with troops! The Guards turned out at the Palace! Dinner at the Guildhall!
Zozim | Discourage me if I know what you’re talking about! I wish Zoo would come: she understands these things. All I can tell you is that the general opinion among the Colonizers is in favor of beginning in a country where the people are of a different color from us; so that we can make short work without any risk of mistakes.
The Envoy | What do you mean by short work? I hope—
Zozim | With obviously feigned geniality. Oh, nothing, nothing, nothing. We are thinking of trying North America: that’s all. You see, the Red Men of that country used to be white. They passed through a period of sallow complexions, followed by a period of no complexions at all, into the red characteristic of their climate. Besides, several cases of long life have occurred in North America. They joined us here; and their stock soon reverted to the original white of these islands.
The Elderly Gentleman | But have you considered the possibility of your colony turning red?
Zozim | That won’t matter. We are not particular about our pigmentation. The old books mention red-faced Englishmen: they appear to have been common objects at one time.
The Elderly Gentleman | Very persuasively. But do you think you would be popular in North America? It seems to me, if I may say so, that on your own showing you need a country in which society is organized in a series of highly exclusive circles, in which the privacy of private life is very jealously guarded, and in which no one presumes to speak to anyone else without an introduction following a strict examination of social credentials. It is only in such a country that persons of special tastes and attainments can form a little world of their own, and protect themselves absolutely from intrusion by common persons. I think I may claim that our British society has developed this exclusiveness to perfection. If you would pay us a visit and see the working of our caste system, our club system, our guild system, you would admit that nowhere else in the world, least of all, perhaps in North America, which has a regrettable tradition of social promiscuity, could you keep yourselves so entirely to yourselves.
Zozim | Good-naturedly embarrassed. Look here. There is no good discussing this. I had rather not explain; but it won’t make any difference to our Colonizers what sort of short-livers they come across. We shall arrange all that. Never mind how. Let us join the ladies.
The Elderly Gentleman | Throwing off his diplomatic attitude and abandoning himself to despair. We understand you only too well, sir. Well, kill us. End the lives you have made miserably unhappy by opening up to us the possibility that any of us may live three hundred years. I solemnly curse that possibility. To you it may be a blessing, because you do live three hundred years. To us, who live less than a hundred, whose flesh is as grass, it is the most unbearable burden our poor tortured humanity has ever groaned under.
The Envoy | Hullo, Poppa! Steady! How do you make that out?
Zozim | What is three hundred years? Short enough, if you ask me. Why, in the old days you people lived on the assumption that you were going to last out forever and ever and ever. Immortal, you thought yourselves. Were you any happier then?
The Elderly Gentleman | As President of the Baghdad Historical Society I am in a position to inform you that the communities which took this monstrous pretension seriously were the most wretched of which we have any record. My Society has printed an editio princeps of the works of the father of history, Thucyderodotus Macolly-buckle. Have you read his account of what was blasphemously called the Perfect City of God, and the attempt made to reproduce it in the northern part of these islands by Jonhobsnoxius, called the Leviathan? Those misguided people sacrificed the fragment of life that was granted to them to an imaginary immortality. They crucified the prophet who told them to take no thought for the morrow, and that here and now was their Australia: Australia being a term signifying paradise, or an eternity of bliss. They tried to produce a condition of death in life: to mortify the flesh, as they called it.
Zozim | Well, you are not suffering from that, are you? You have not a mortified air.
The Elderly Gentleman | Naturally we are not absolutely insane and suicidal. Nevertheless we impose on ourselves abstinences and disciplines and studies that are meant to prepare us for living three centuries. And we seldom live one. My childhood was made unnecessarily painful, my boyhood unnecessarily laborious, by ridiculous preparations for a length of days which the chances were fifty thousand to one against my ever attaining. I have been cheated out of the natural joys and freedoms of my life by this dream to which the existence of these islands and their oracles gives a delusive possibility of realization. I curse the day when long life was invented, just as the victims of Jonhobsnoxius cursed the day when eternal life was invented.
Zozim | Pooh! You could live three centuries if you chose.
The Elderly Gentleman | That is what the fortunate always say to the unfortunate. Well, I do not choose. I accept my three score and ten years. If they are filled with usefulness, with justice, with mercy, with goodwill: if they are the lifetime of a soul that never loses its honor and a brain that never loses its eagerness, they are enough for me, because these things are infinite and eternal, and can make ten of my years as long as thirty of yours. I shall not conclude by saying live as long as you like and be damned to you, because I have risen for the moment far above any ill-will to you or to any fellow-creature; but I am your equal before that eternity in which the difference between your lifetime and mine is as the difference between one drop of water and three in the eyes of the Almighty Power from which we have both proceeded.
Zozim | Impressed. You spoke that piece very well, Daddy. I couldn’t talk like that if I tried. It sounded fine. Ah! here comes the ladies.
To his relief, they have just appeared on the threshold of the temple.
The Elderly Gentleman | Passing from exaltation to distress. It means nothing to him: in this land of discouragement the sublime has become the ridiculous. Turning on the hopelessly puzzled Zozim. “Behold, thou hast made my days as it were a span long; and mine age is even as nothing in respect of thee.”
Running to him.
The Wife | Poppa, Poppa: don’t look like that.
The Daughter | Oh, granpa, what’s the matter?
Zozim | With a shrug. Discouragement!
The Elderly Gentleman | Throwing off the women with a superb gesture. Liar! Recollecting himself, he adds, with noble courtesy, raising his hat and bowing, I beg your pardon, sir; but I am not discouraged.
A burst of orchestral music, through which a powerful gong sounds, is heard from the temple. Zoo, in a purple robe, appears in the doorway.
Zoo | Come. The oracle is ready.
Zozim motions them to the threshold with a wave of his staff. The Envoy and the Elderly Gentleman take off their hats and go into the temple on tiptoe, Zoo leading the way. The Wife and Daughter, frightened as they are, raise their heads uppishly and follow flatfooted, sustained by a sense of their Sunday clothes and social consequence. Zozim remains in the portico, alone.
Zozim | Taking off his wig, beard, and robe, and bundling them under his arm. Ouf! He goes home.

Act III

Inside the temple. A gallery overhanging an abyss. Dead silence. The gallery is brightly lighted; but beyond is a vast gloom, continually changing in intensity. A shaft of violet light shoots upward; and a very harmonious and silvery carillon chimes. When it ceases the violet ray vanishes.

Zoo comes along the gallery, followed by the Envoy’s daughter, his wife, the Envoy himself, and the Elderly Gentleman. The two men are holding their hats with the brims near their noses, as if prepared to pray into them at a moment’s notice. Zoo halts: they all follow her example. They contemplate the void with awe. Organ music of the kind called sacred in the nineteenth century begins. Their awe deepens. The violet ray, now a diffused mist, rises again from the abyss.

The Wife | To Zoo, in a reverent whisper. Shall we kneel?
Zoo | Loudly. Yes, if you want to. You can stand on your head if you like. She sits down carelessly on the gallery railing, with her back to the abyss.
The Elderly Gentleman | Jarred by her callousness. We desire to behave in a becoming manner.
Zoo | Very well. Behave just as you feel. It doesn’t matter how you behave. But keep your wits about you when the pythoness ascends, or you will forget the questions you have come to ask her.
Simultaneously.
The Envoy | Very nervous, takes out a paper to refresh his memory. Ahem!
The Daughter | Alarmed. The pythoness. Is she a snake?
The Elderly Gentleman | Tch-ch! The priestess of the oracle. A sybil. A prophetess. Not a snake.
The Wife | How awful!
Zoo | I’m glad you think so.
The Wife | Oh dear! Don’t you think so?
Zoo | No. This sort of thing is got up to impress you, not to impress me.
The Elderly Gentleman | I wish you would let it impress us, then, madam. I am deeply impressed; but you are spoiling the effect.
Zoo | You just wait. All this business with colored lights and chords on that old organ is only tomfoolery. Wait till you see the pythoness.
The Envoy’s wife falls on her knees, and takes refuge in prayer.
The Daughter | Trembling. Are we really going to see a woman who has lived three hundred years?
Zoo | Stuff! Youd drop dead if a tertiary as much as looked at you. The oracle is only a hundred and seventy; and you’ll find it hard enough to stand her.
The Daughter | Piteously. Oh! She falls on her knees.
The Envoy | Whew! Stand by me, Poppa. This is a little more than I bargained for. Are you going to kneel; or how?
The Elderly Gentleman | Perhaps it would be in better taste.
The two men kneel.
The vapor of the abyss thickens; and a distant roll of thunder seems to come from its depths. The pythoness, seated on her tripod, rises slowly from it. She has discarded the insulating robe and veil in which she conversed with Napoleon, and is now draped and hooded in voluminous folds of a single piece of grey-white stuff. Something supernatural about her terrifies the beholders, who throw themselves on their faces. Her outline flows and waves: she is almost distinct at moments, and again vague and shadowy: above all, she is larger than life-size, not enough to be measured by the flustered congregation, but enough to affect them with a dreadful sense of her supernaturalness.
Zoo | Get up, get up. Do pull yourselves together, you people.
The Envoy and his family, by shuddering negatively, intimate that it is impossible. The Elderly Gentleman manages to get on his hands and knees.
Zoo | Come on, Daddy: you are not afraid. Speak to her. She won’t wait here all day for you, you know.
The Elderly Gentleman | Rising very deferentially to his feet. Madam: you will excuse my very natural nervousness in addressing, for the first time in my life, a—a—a—a goddess. My friend and relative the Envoy is unhinged. I throw myself upon your indulgence—
Zoo | Interrupting him intolerantly. Don’t throw yourself on anything belonging to her or you will go right through her and break your neck. She isn’t solid, like you.
The Elderly Gentleman | I was speaking figuratively—
Zoo | You have been told not to do it. Ask her what you want to know; and be quick about it.
The Elderly Gentleman | Stooping and taking the prostrate Envoy by the shoulders. Ambrose: you must make an effort. You cannot go back to Baghdad without the answers to your questions.
The Envoy | Rising to his knees. I shall be only too glad to get back alive on any terms. If my legs would support me I’d just do a bunk straight for the ship.
The Elderly Gentleman | No, no. Remember: your dignity—
The Envoy | Dignity be damned! I’m terrified. Take me away, for God’s sake.
The Elderly Gentleman | Producing a brandy flask and taking the cap off. Try some of this. It is still nearly full, thank goodness!
The Envoy | Clutching it and drinking eagerly. Ah! That’s better. He tries to drink again. Finding that he has emptied it, he hands it back to his father-in-law upside down.
The Elderly Gentleman | Taking it. Great heavens! He has swallowed half-a-pint of neat brandy. Much perturbed, he screws the cap on again, and pockets the flask.
The Envoy | Staggering to his feet; pulling a paper from his pocket; and speaking with boisterous confidence. Get up, Molly. Up with you, Eth.
The two women rise to their knees.
The Envoy | What I want to ask is this. He refers to the paper. Ahem! Civilization has reached a crisis. We are at the parting of the ways. We stand on the brink of the Rubicon. Shall we take the plunge? Already a leaf has been torn out of the book of the Sybil. Shall we wait until the whole volume is consumed? On our right is the crater of the volcano: on our left the precipice. One false step, and we go down to annihilation dragging the whole human race with us. He pauses for breath.
The Elderly Gentleman | Recovering his spirits under the familiar stimulus of political oratory. Hear, hear!
Zoo | What are you raving about? Ask your question while you have the chance. What is it you want to know?
The Envoy | Patronizing her in the manner of a Premier debating with a very young member of the Opposition. A young woman asks me a question. I am always glad to see the young taking an interest in politics. It is an impatient question; but it is a practical question, an intelligent question. She asks why we seek to lift a corner of the veil that shrouds the future from our feeble vision.
Zoo | I don’t. I ask you to tell the oracle what you want, and not keep her sitting there all day.
The Elderly Gentleman | Warmly. Order, order!
Zoo | What does “Order, order!” mean?
The Envoy | I ask the august oracle to listen to my voice—
Zoo | You people seem never to tire of listening to your voices; but it doesn’t amuse us. What do you want?
The Envoy | I want, young woman, to be allowed to proceed without unseemly interruptions.
A low roll of thunder comes from the abyss.
The Elderly Gentleman | There! Even the oracle is indignant. To the Envoy. Do not allow yourself to be put down by this lady’s rude clamor, Ambrose. Take no notice. Proceed.
The Envoy’s Wife | I can’t bear this much longer, Amby. Remember: I haven’t had any brandy.
His Daughter | Trembling. There are serpents curling in the vapor. I am afraid of the lightning. Finish it, Papa; or I shall die.
The Envoy | Sternly. Silence. The destiny of British civilization is at stake. Trust me. I am not afraid. As I was saying—where was I?
Zoo | I don’t know. Does anybody?
The Elderly Gentleman | Tactfully. You were just coming to the election, I think.
The Envoy | Reassured. Just so. The election. Now what we want to know is this: ought we to dissolve in August, or put it off until next spring?
Zoo | Dissolve? In what? Thunder. Oh! My fault this time. That means that the oracle understands you, and desires me to hold my tongue.
The Envoy | Fervently. I thank the oracle.
The Wife | To Zoo. Serve you right!
The Elderly Gentleman | Before the oracle replies, I should like to be allowed to state a few of the reasons why, in my opinion, the Government should hold on until the spring. In the first—
Terrific lightning and thunder. The Elderly Gentleman is knocked flat; but as he immediately sits up again dazedly it is clear that he is none the worse for the shock. The ladies cower in terror. The Envoy’s hat is blown off; but he seizes it just as it quits his temples, and holds it on with both hands. He is recklessly drunk, but quite articulate, as he seldom speaks in public without taking stimulants beforehand.
The Envoy | Taking one hand from his hat to make a gesture of stilling the tempest. That’s enough. We know how to take a hint. I’ll put the case in three words. I am the leader of the Potterbill party. My party is in power. I am Prime Minister. The Opposition—the Rotterjacks—have won every bye-election for the last six months. They—
The Elderly Gentleman | Scrambling heatedly to his feet. Not by fair means. By bribery, by misrepresentation, by pandering to the vilest prejudices—muttered thunder I beg your pardon. He is silent.
The Envoy | Never mind the bribery and lies. The oracle knows all about that. The point is that though our five years will not expire until the year after next, our majority will be eaten away at the bye-elections by about Easter. We can’t wait: we must start some question that will excite the public, and go to the country on it. But some of us say do it now. Others say wait till the spring. We can’t make up our minds one way or the other. Which would you advise?
Zoo | But what is the question that is to excite your public?
The Envoy | That doesn’t matter. I don’t know yet. We will find a question all right enough. The oracle can foresee the future: we cannot. Thunder. What does that mean? What have I done now?
Zoo | Severely. How often must you be told that we cannot foresee the future? There is no such thing as the future until it is the present.
The Elderly Gentleman | Allow me to point out, madam, that when the Potterbill party sent to consult the oracle fifteen years ago, the oracle prophesied that the Potterbills would be victorious at the General Election; and they were. So it is evident that the oracle can foresee the future, and is sometimes willing to reveal it.
The Envoy | Quite true. Thank you, Poppa. I appeal now, over your head, young woman, direct to the August Oracle, to repeat the signal favor conferred on my illustrious predecessor, Sir Fuller Eastwind, and to answer me exactly as he was answered.
The oracle raises her hands to command silence.
All | Sh-sh-sh!
Invisible trombones utter three solemn blasts in the manner of Die Zauberflöte.
The Elderly Gentleman | May I—
Zoo | Quickly. Hush. The oracle is going to speak.
The Oracle | Go home, poor fool.
She vanishes; and the atmosphere changes to prosaic daylight. Zoo comes off the railing; throws off her robe; makes a bundle of it; and tucks it under her arm. The magic and mystery are gone. The women rise to their feet. The Envoy’s party stare at one another helplessly.
Zoo | The same reply, word for word, that your illustrious predecessor, as you call him, got fifteen years ago. You asked for it; and you got it. And just think of all the important questions you might have asked. She would have answered them, you know. It is always like that. I will go and arrange to have you sent home: you can wait for me in the entrance hall. She goes out.
The Envoy | What possessed me to ask for the same answer old Eastwind got?
The Elderly Gentleman | But it was not the same answer. The answer to Eastwind was an inspiration to our party for years. It won us the election.
The Envoy’s Daughter | I learnt it at school, granpa. It wasn’t the same at all. I can repeat it. She quotes. “When Britain was cradled in the west, the east wind hardened her and made her great. Whilst the east wind prevails Britain shall prosper. The east wind shall wither Britain’s enemies in the day of contest. Let the Rotterjacks look to it.”
The Envoy | The old man invented that. I see it all. He was a doddering old ass when he came to consult the oracle. The oracle naturally said “Go home, poor fool.” There was no sense in saying that to me; but as that girl said, I asked for it. What else could the poor old chap do but fake up an answer fit for publication? There were whispers about it; but nobody believed them. I believe them now.
The Elderly Gentleman | Oh, I cannot admit that Sir Fuller Eastwind was capable of such a fraud.
The Envoy | He was capable of anything: I knew his private secretary. And now what are we going to say? You don’t suppose I am going back to Baghdad to tell the British Empire that the oracle called me a fool, do you?
The Elderly Gentleman | Surely we must tell the truth, however painful it may be to our feelings.
The Envoy | I am not thinking of my feelings: I am not so selfish as that, thank God. I am thinking of the country: of our party. The truth, as you call it, would put the Rotterjacks in for the next twenty years. It would be the end of me politically. Not that I care for that: I am only too willing to retire if you can find a better man. Don’t hesitate on my account.
The Elderly Gentleman | No, Ambrose: you are indispensable. There is no one else.
The Envoy | Very well, then. What are you going to do?
The Elderly Gentleman | My dear Ambrose, you are the leader of the party, not I. What are you going to do?
The Envoy | I am going to tell the exact truth; that’s what I’m going to do. Do you take me for a liar?
The Elderly Gentleman | Puzzled. Oh. I beg your pardon. I understood you to say—
The Envoy | Cutting him short. You understood me to say that I am going back to Baghdad to tell the British electorate that the oracle repeated to me, word for word, what it said to Sir Fuller Eastwind fifteen years ago. Molly and Ethel can bear me out. So must you, if you are an honest man. Come on.
He goes out, followed by his wife and daughter.
The Elderly Gentleman | Left alone and shrinking into an old and desolate figure. What am I to do? I am a most perplexed and wretched man. He falls on his knees, and stretches his hands in entreaty over the abyss. I invoke the oracle. I cannot go back and connive at a blasphemous lie. I implore guidance.
The Pythoness walks in on the gallery behind him, and touches him on the shoulder. Her size is now natural. Her face is hidden by her hood. He flinches as if from an electric shock; turns to her; and cowers, covering his eyes in terror.
The Elderly Gentleman | No: not close to me. I’m afraid I can’t bear it.
The Oracle | With grave pity. Come: look at me. I am my natural size now: what you saw there was only a foolish picture of me thrown on a cloud by a lantern. How can I help you?
The Elderly Gentleman | They have gone back to lie about your answer. I cannot go with them. I cannot live among people to whom nothing is real. I have become incapable of it through my stay here. I implore to be allowed to stay.
The Oracle | My friend: if you stay with us you will die of discouragement.
The Elderly Gentleman | If I go back I shall die of disgust and despair. I take the nobler risk. I beg you, do not cast me out.
He catches her robe and holds her.
The Oracle | Take care. I have been here one hundred and seventy years. Your death does not mean to me what it means to you.
The Elderly Gentleman | It is the meaning of life, not of death, that makes banishment so terrible to me.
The Oracle | Be it so, then. You may stay.
She offers him her hands. He grasps them and raises himself a little by clinging to her. She looks steadily into his face. He stiffens; a little convulsion shakes him; his grasp relaxes; and he falls dead.
The Oracle | Looking down at the body. Poor short-lived thing! What else could I do for you?

Part II

The Gospel of the Brothers Barnabas

Present Day

In the first years after the war an impressive-looking gentleman of 50 is seated writing in a well-furnished spacious study. He is dressed in black. His coat is a frock-coat; his tie is white; and his waistcoat, though it is not quite a clergyman’s waistcoat, and his collar, though it buttons in front instead of behind, combine with the prosperity indicated by his surroundings, and his air of personal distinction, to suggest the clerical dignitary. Still, he is clearly neither dean nor bishop; he is rather too starkly intellectual for a popular Free Church enthusiast; and he is not careworn enough to be a great headmaster.

The study windows, which have broad comfortable window seats, overlook Hampstead Heath towards London. Consequently, it being a fine afternoon in spring, the room is sunny. As you face these windows, you have on your right the fireplace, with a few logs smouldering in it, and a couple of comfortable library chairs on the hearthrug; beyond it and beside it the door; before you the writing-table, at which the clerical gentleman sits a little to your left facing the door with his right profile presented to you; on your left a settee; and on your right a couple of Chippendale chairs. There is also an upholstered square stool in the middle of the room, against the writing-table. The walls are covered with bookshelves above and lockers beneath.

The door opens; and another gentleman, shorter than the clerical one, within a year or two of the same age, dressed in a well-worn tweed lounge suit, with a short beard and much less style in his bearing and carriage, looks in.

The Clerical Gentleman | Familiar and by no means cordial. Hallo! I didn’t expect you until the five o’clock train.
The Tweeded Gentleman | Coming in very slowly. I have something on my mind. I thought I’d come early.
The Clerical Gentleman | Throwing down his pen. What is on your mind?
The Tweeded Gentleman | Sitting down on the stool, heavily preoccupied with his thought. I have made up my mind at last about the time. I make it three hundred years.
The Clerical Gentleman | Sitting up energetically. Now that is extraordinary. Most extraordinary. The very last words I wrote when you interrupted me were “at least three centuries.” He snatches up his manuscript, and points to it. Here it is: reading “the term of human life must be extended to at least three centuries.”
The Tweeded Gentleman | How did you arrive at it?
A parlor maid opens the door, ushering in a young clergyman.
The Parlor Maid | Mr. Haslam. She withdraws.
The visitor is so very unwelcome that his host forgets to rise; and the two brothers stare at the intruder, quite unable to conceal their dismay. Haslam, who has nothing clerical about him except his collar, and wears a snuff-colored suit, smiles with a frank school-boyishness that makes it impossible to be unkind to him, and explodes into obviously unpremeditated speech.
Haslam | I’m afraid I’m an awful nuisance. I’m the rector; and I suppose one ought to call on people.
The Tweeded Gentleman | In ghostly tones. We’re not Church people, you know.
Haslam | Oh, I don’t mind that, if you don’t. The Church people here are mostly as dull as ditch-water. I have heard such a lot about you; and there are so jolly few people to talk to. I thought you perhaps wouldn’t mind. Do you mind? for of course I’ll go like a shot if I’m in the way.
The Clerical Gentleman | Rising, disarmed. Sit down, Mr.—er?
Haslam | Haslam.
The Clerical Gentleman | Mr. Haslam.
The Tweeded Gentleman | Rising and offering him the stool. Sit down. He retreats towards the Chippendale chairs.
Haslam | Sitting down on the stool. Thanks awfully.
The Clerical Gentleman | Resuming his seat. This is my brother Conrad, Professor of Biology at Jarrowfields University: Dr. Conrad Barnabas. My name is Franklyn: Franklyn Barnabas. I was in the Church myself for some years.
Haslam | Sympathizing. Yes: one can’t help it. If theres a living in the family, or one’s Governor knows a patron, one gets shoved into the Church by one’s parents.
Conrad | Sitting down on the furthest Chippendale with a snort of amusement. Mp!
Franklyn | One gets shoved out of it, sometimes, by one’s conscience.
Haslam | Oh yes; but where is a chap like me to go? I’m afraid I’m not intellectual enough to split straws when theres a job in front of me, and nothing better for me to do. I daresay the Church was a bit thick for you; but it’s good enough for me. It will last my time, anyhow. He laughs good-humoredly.
Franklyn | With renewed energy. There again! You see, Con. It will last his time. Life is too short for men to take it seriously.
Haslam | That’s a way of looking at it, certainly.
Franklyn | I was not shoved into the Church, Mr. Haslam: I felt it to be my vocation to walk with God, like Enoch. After twenty years of it I realized that I was walking with my own ignorance and self-conceit, and that I was not within a hundred and fifty years of the experience and wisdom I was pretending to.
Haslam | Now I come to think of it, old Methuselah must have had to think twice before he took on anything for life. If I thought I was going to live nine hundred and sixty years, I don’t think I should stay in the Church.
Franklyn | If men lived even a third of that time, the Church would be very different from the thing it is.
Conrad | If I could count on nine hundred and sixty years I could make myself a real biologist, instead of what I am now: a child trying to walk. Are you sure you might not become a good clergyman if you had a few centuries to do it in?
Haslam | Oh, theres nothing much the matter with me: it’s quite easy to be a decent parson. It’s the Church that chokes me off. I couldn’t stick it for nine hundred years. I should chuck it. You know, sometimes, when the bishop, who is the most priceless of fossils, lets off something more than usually out-of-date, the bird starts in my garden.
Franklyn | The bird?
Haslam | Oh yes. Theres a bird there that keeps on singing “Stick it or chuck it: stick it or chuck it”—just like that—for an hour on end in the spring. I wish my father had found some other shop for me.
The parlor maid comes back.
The Parlor Maid | Any letters for the post, sir?
Franklyn | These. He proffers a basket of letters. She comes to the table and takes them.
Haslam | To the maid. Have you told Mr. Barnabas yet?
The Parlor Maid | Flinching a little. No, sir.
Franklyn | Told me what?
Haslam | She is going to leave you?
Franklyn | Indeed? I’m sorry. Is it our fault, Mr. Haslam?
Haslam | Not a bit. She is jolly well off here.
The Parlor Maid | Reddening. I have never denied it, sir: I couldn’t ask for a better place. But I have only one life to live; and I mayn’t get a second chance. Excuse me, sir; but the letters must go to catch the post. She goes out with the letters.
The two brothers look inquiringly at Haslam.
Haslam | Silly girl! Going to marry a village woodman and live in a hovel with him and a lot of kids tumbling over one another, just because the fellow has poetic-looking eyes and a moustache.
Conrad | Demurring. She said it was because she had only one life.
Haslam | Same thing, poor girl! The fellow persuaded her to chuck it; and when she marries him she’ll have to stick it. Rotten state of things, I call it.
Conrad | You see, she hasn’t time to find out what life really means. She has to die before she knows.
Haslam | Agreeably. That’s it.
Franklyn | She hasn’t time to form a well-instructed conscience.
Haslam | Still more cheerfully. Quite.
Franklyn | It goes deeper. She hasn’t time to form a genuine conscience at all. Some romantic points of honor and a few conventions. A world without conscience: that is the horror of our condition.
Haslam | Beaming. Simply fatuous. Rising. Well, I suppose I’d better be going. It’s most awfully good of you to put up with my calling.
Conrad | In his former low ghostly tone. You needn’t go, you know, if you are really interested.
Haslam | Fed up. Well, I’m afraid I ought to—I really must get back—I have something to do in the—
Franklyn | Smiling benignly and rising to proffer his hand. Goodbye.
Conrad | Gruffly, giving him up as a bad job. Goodbye.
Haslam | Goodbye. Sorry—er—
As the rector moves to shake hands with Franklyn, feeling that he is making a frightful mess of his departure, a vigorous sunburnt young lady with hazel hair cut to the level of her neck, like an Italian youth in a Gozzoli picture, comes in impetuously. She seems to have nothing on but her short skirt, her blouse, her stockings, and a pair of Norwegian shoes: in short, she is a Simple-Lifer.
The Simple-Lifer | Swooping on Conrad and kissing him. Hallo, Nunk. You’re before your time.
Conrad | Behave yourself. Theres a visitor.
She turns quickly and sees the rector. She instinctively switches at her Gozzoli fringe with her fingers, but gives it up as hopeless.
Franklyn | Mr. Haslam, our new rector. To Haslam. My daughter Cynthia.
Conrad | Usually called Savvy, short for Savage.
Savvy | I usually call Mr. Haslam Bill, short for William. She strolls to the hearthrug, and surveys them calmly from that commanding position.
Franklyn | You know him?
Savvy | Rather. Sit down, Bill.
Franklyn | Mr. Haslam is going, Savvy. He has an engagement.
Savvy | I know. I’m the engagement.
Conrad | In that case, would you mind taking him into the garden while I talk to your father?
Savvy | To Haslam. Tennis?
Haslam | Rather!
Savvy | Come on. She dances out. He runs boyishly after her.
Franklyn | Leaving his table and beginning to walk up and down the room discontentedly. Savvy’s manners jar on me. They would have horrified her grandmother.
Conrad | Obstinately. They are happier manners than Mother’s manners.
Franklyn | Yes: they are franker, wholesomer, better in a hundred ways. And yet I squirm at them. I cannot get it out of my head that Mother was a well-mannered woman, and that Savvy has no manners at all.
Conrad | There wasn’t any pleasure in Mother’s fine manners. That makes a biological difference.
Franklyn | But there was beauty in Mother’s manners, grace in them, style in them: above all, decision in them. Savvy is such a cub.
Conrad | So she ought to be, at her age.
Franklyn | There it comes again! Her age! her age!
Conrad | You want her to be fully grown at eighteen. You want to force her into a stuck-up, artificial, premature self-possession before she has any self to possess. You just let her alone: she is right enough for her years.
Franklyn | I have let her alone; and look at the result! Like all the other young people who have been let alone, she becomes a Socialist. That is, she becomes hopelessly demoralized.
Conrad | Well, aren’t you a Socialist?
Franklyn | Yes; but that is not the same thing. You and I were brought up in the old bourgeois morality. We were taught bourgeois manners and bourgeois points of honor. Bourgeois manners may be snobbish manners: there may be no pleasure in them, as you say; but they are better than no manners. Many bourgeois points of honor may be false; but at least they exist. The women know what to expect and what is expected of them. Savvy doesn’t. She is a Bolshevist and nothing else. She has to improvise her manners and her conduct as she goes along. It’s often charming, no doubt; but sometimes she puts her foot in it frightfully; and then I feel that she is blaming me for not teaching her better.
Conrad | Well, you have something better to teach her now, at all events.
Franklyn | Yes: but it is too late. She doesn’t trust me now. She doesn’t talk about such things to me. She doesn’t read anything I write. She never comes to hear me lecture. I am out of it as far as Savvy is concerned. He resumes his seat at the writing-table.
Conrad | I must have a talk to her.
Franklyn | Perhaps she will listen to you. You are not her father.
Conrad | I sent her my last book. I can break the ice by asking her what she made of it.
Franklyn | When she heard you were coming, she asked me whether all the leaves were cut, in case it fell into your hands. She hasn’t read a word of it.
Conrad | Rising indignantly. What!
Franklyn | Inexorably. Not a word of it.
Conrad | Beaten. Well, I suppose it’s only natural. Biology is a dry subject for a girl; and I am a pretty dry old codger.
He sits down again resignedly.
Franklyn | Brother: if that is so; if biology as you have worked at it, and religion as I have worked at it, are dry subjects like the old stuff they taught under these names, and we two are dry old codgers, like the old preachers and professors, then The Gospel of the Brothers Barnabas is a delusion. Unless this withered thing religion, and this dry thing science, have come alive in our hands, alive and intensely interesting, we may just as well go out and dig the garden until it is time to dig our graves. The parlor maid returns. Franklyn is impatient at the interruption. Well? what is it now?
The Parlor Maid | Mr. Joyce Burge on the telephone, sir. He wants to speak to you.
Franklyn | Astonished. Mr. Joyce Burge!
The Parlor Maid | Yes, sir.
Franklyn | To Conrad. What on earth does this mean? I haven’t heard from him nor exchanged a word with him for years. I resigned the chairmanship of the Liberal Association and shook the dust of party politics from my feet before he was Prime Minister in the Coalition. Of course, he dropped me like a hot potato.
Conrad | Well, now that the Coalition has chucked him out, and he is only one of the half-dozen leaders of the Opposition, perhaps he wants to pick you up again.
The Parlor Maid | Warningly. He is holding the line, sir.
Franklyn | Yes: all right. He hurries out.
The parlor maid goes to the hearthrug to make up the fire. Conrad rises and strolls to the middle of the room, where he stops and looks quizzically down at her.
Conrad | So you have only one life to live, eh?
The Parlor Maid | Dropping on her knees in consternation. I meant no offence, sir.
Conrad | You didn’t give any. But you know you could live a devil of a long life if you really wanted to.
The Parlor Maid | Sitting down on her heels. Oh, don’t say that, sir. It’s so unsettling.
Conrad | Why? Have you been thinking about it?
The Parlor Maid | It would never have come into my head if you hadn’t put it there, sir. Me and cook had a look at your book.
Conrad |

What!

You and cook
Had a look
At my book!

And my niece wouldn’t open it! The prophet is without honor in his own family. Well, what do you think of living for several hundred years? Are you going to have a try for it?

The Parlor Maid | Well, of course you’re not in earnest, sir. But it does set one thinking, especially when one is going to be married.
Conrad | What has that to do with it? He may live as long as you, you know.
The Parlor Maid | That’s just it, sir. You see, he must take me for better for worse, till death do us part. Do you think he would be so ready to do that, sir, if he thought it might be for several hundred years?
Conrad | That’s true. And what about yourself?
The Parlor Maid | Oh, I tell you straight out, sir, I’d never promise to live with the same man as long as that. I wouldn’t put up with my own children as long as that. Why, cook figured it out, sir, that when you were only 200, you might marry your own great-great-great-great-great-great-grandson and not even know who he was.
Conrad | Well, why not? For all you know, the man you are going to marry may be your great-great-great-great-great-great-grandmother’s great-great-great-great-great-great-grandson.
The Parlor Maid | But do you think it would ever be thought respectable, sir?
Conrad | My good girl, all biological necessities have to be made respectable whether we like it or not; so you needn’t worry yourself about that.
Franklyn returns and crosses the room to his chair, but does not sit down. The parlor maid goes out.
Conrad | Well, what does Joyce Burge want?
Franklyn | Oh, a silly misunderstanding. I have promised to address a meeting in Middlesborough; and some fool has put it into the papers that I am “coming to Middlesborough,” without any explanation. Of course, now that we are on the eve of a general election, political people think I am coming there to contest the parliamentary seat. Burge knows that I have a following, and thinks I could get into the House of Commons and head a group there. So he insists on coming to see me. He is staying with some people at Dollis Hill, and can be here in five or ten minutes, he says.
Conrad | But didn’t you tell him that it’s a false alarm?
Franklyn | Of course I did; but he won’t believe me.
Conrad | Called you a liar, in fact?
Franklyn | No: I wish he had: any sort of plain speaking is better than the nauseous sham good fellowship our democratic public men get up for shop use. He pretends to believe me, and assures me his visit is quite disinterested; but why should he come if he has no axe to grind? These chaps never believe anything they say themselves; and naturally they cannot believe anything anyone else says.
Conrad | Rising. Well, I shall clear out. It was hard enough to stand the party politicians before the war; but now that they have managed to half kill Europe between them, I can’t be civil to them, and I don’t see why I should be.
Franklyn | Wait a bit. We have to find out how the world will take our new gospel. Conrad sits down again. Party politicians are still unfortunately an important part of the world. Suppose we try it on Joyce Burge.
Conrad | How can you? You can tell things only to people who can listen. Joyce Burge has talked so much that he has lost the power of listening. He doesn’t listen even in the House of Commons.
Savvy rushes in breathless, followed by Haslam, who remains timidly just inside the door.
Savvy | Running to Franklyn. I say! Who do you think has just driven up in a big car?
Franklyn | Mr. Joyce Burge, perhaps.
Savvy | Disappointed. Oh, they know, Bill. Why didn’t you tell us he was coming? I have nothing on.
Haslam | I’d better go, hadn’t I?
Conrad | You just wait here, both of you. When you start yawning, Joyce Burge will take the hint, perhaps.
Savvy | To Franklyn. May we?
Franklyn | Yes, if you promise to behave yourself.
Savvy | Making a wry face. That will be a treat, won’t it?
The Parlor Maid | Entering and announcing. Mr. Joyce Burge.
Haslam hastily moves to the fireplace; and the parlor maid goes out and shuts the door when the visitor has passed in.
Franklyn | Hurrying past Savvy to his guest with the false cordiality he has just been denouncing. Oh! Here you are. Delighted to see you. He shakes Burge’s hand, and introduces Savvy. My daughter.
Savvy | Not daring to approach. Very kind of you to come.
Joyce Burge stands fast and says nothing; but he screws up his cheeks into a smile at each introduction, and makes his eyes shine in a very winning manner. He is a well-fed man turned fifty, with broad forehead, and grey hair which, his neck being short, falls almost to his collar.
Franklyn | Mr. Haslam, our rector.
Burge conveys an impression of shining like a church window; and Haslam seizes the nearest library chair on the hearth, and swings it round for Burge between the stool and Conrad. He then retires to the window seat at the other side of the room, and is joined by Savvy. They sit there, side by side, hunched up with their elbows on their knees and their chins on their hands, providing Burge with a sort of Stranger’s Gallery during the ensuing sitting.
Franklyn | I forget whether you know my brother Conrad. He is a biologist.
Burge | Suddenly bursting into energetic action and shaking hands heartily with Conrad. By reputation only, but very well, of course. How I wish I could have devoted myself to biology! I have always been interested in rocks and strata and volcanoes and so forth: they throw such a light on the age of the earth. With conviction. There is nothing like biology. “The cloud-capped towers, the solemn binnacles, the gorgeous temples, the great globe itself: yea, all that it inherit shall dissolve, and, like this influential pageant faded, leave not a rack behind.” That’s biology, you know: good sound biology. He sits down. So do the others, Franklyn on the stool, and Conrad on his Chippendale. Well, my dear Barnabas, what do you think of the situation? Don’t you think the time has come for us to make a move?
Franklyn | The time has always come to make a move.
Burge | How true! But what is the move to be? You are a man of enormous influence. We know that. Weve always known it. We have to consult you whether we like it or not. We—
Franklyn | Interrupting firmly. I never meddle in party politics now.
Savvy | It’s no use saying you have no influence, daddy. Heaps of people swear by you.
Burge | Shining at her. Of course they do. Come! let me prove to you what we think of you. Shall we find you a first-rate constituency to contest at the next election? One that won’t cost you a penny. A metropolitan seat. What do you say to the Strand?
Franklyn | My dear Burge, I am not a child. Why do you go on wasting your party funds on the Strand? You know you cannot win it.
Burge | We cannot win it; but you—
Franklyn | Oh, please!
Savvy | The Strand’s no use, Mr. Burge. I once canvassed for a Socialist there. Cheese it.
Burge | Cheese it!
Haslam | Spluttering with suppressed laughter. Priceless!
Savvy | Well, I suppose I shouldn’t say cheese it to a Right Honorable. But the Strand, you know! Do come off it.
Franklyn | You must excuse my daughter’s shocking manners, Burge; but I agree with her that popular democratic statesmen soon come to believe that everyone they speak to is an ignorant dupe and a born fool into the bargain.
Burge | Laughing genially. You old aristocrat, you! But believe me, the instinct of the people is sound—
Conrad | Cutting in sharply. Then why are you in the Opposition instead of in the Government?
Burge | Showing signs of temper under this heckling. I deny that I am in the Opposition morally. The Government does not represent the country. I was chucked out of the Coalition by a Tory conspiracy. The people want me back. I don’t want to go back.
Franklyn | Gently remonstrant. My dear Burge: of course you do.
Burge | Turning on him. Not a bit of it. I want to cultivate my garden. I am not interested in politics: I am interested in roses. I haven’t a scrap of ambition. I went into politics because my wife shoved me into them, bless her! But I want to serve my country. What else am I for? I want to save my country from the Tories. They don’t represent the people. The man they have made Prime Minister has never represented the people; and you know it. Lord Dunreen is the bitterest old Tory left alive. What has he to offer to the people?
Franklyn | Cutting in before Burge can proceed—as he evidently intends—to answer his own question. I will tell you. He has ascertainable beliefs and principles to offer. The people know where they are with Lord Dunreen. They know what he thinks right and what he thinks wrong. With your followers they never know where they are. With you they never know where they are.
Burge | Amazed. With me!
Franklyn | Well, where are you? What are you?
Burge | Barnabas: you must be mad. You ask me what I am?
Franklyn | I do.
Burge | I am, if I mistake not, Joyce Burge, pretty well known throughout Europe, and indeed throughout the world, as the man who—unworthily perhaps, but not quite unsuccessfully—held the helm when the ship of State weathered the mightiest hurricane that has ever burst with earthshaking violence on the land of our fathers.
Franklyn | I know that. I know who you are. And the earthshaking part of it to me is that though you were placed in that enormously responsible position, neither I nor anyone else knows what your beliefs are, or even whether you have either beliefs or principles. What we did know was that your Government was formed largely of men who regarded you as a robber of henroosts, and whom you regarded as enemies of the people.
Burge | Adroitly, as he thinks. I agree with you. I agree with you absolutely. I don’t believe in coalition governments.
Franklyn | Precisely. Yet you formed two.
Burge | Why? Because we were at war. That is what you fellows never would realize. The Hun was at the gate. Our country, our lives, the honor of our wives and mothers and daughters, the tender flesh of our innocent babes, were at stake. Was that a time to argue about principles?
Franklyn | I should say it was the time of all others to confirm the resolution of our own men and gain the confidence and support of public opinion throughout the world by a declaration of principle. Do you think the Hun would ever have come to the gate if he had known that it would be shut in his face on principle? Did he not hold his own against you until America boldly affirmed the democratic principle and came to our rescue? Why did you let America snatch that honor from England?
Burge | Barnabas: America was carried away by words, and had to eat them at the Peace Conference. Beware of eloquence: it is the bane of popular speakers like you.
Exclaiming all together.
Franklyn | Well!!
Savvy | I like that!
Haslam | Priceless!
Burge | Continuing remorselessly. Come down to facts. It wasn’t principle that won the war: it was the British fleet and the blockade. America found the talk: I found the shells. You cannot win wars by principles; but you can win elections by them. There I am with you. You want the next election to be fought on principles: that is what it comes to, doesn’t it?
Franklyn | I don’t want it to be fought at all! An election is a moral horror, as bad as a battle except for the blood: a mud bath for every soul concerned in it. You know very well that it will not be fought on principle.
Burge | On the contrary it will be fought on nothing else. I believe a program is a mistake. I agree with you that principle is what we want.
Franklyn | Principle without program, eh?
Burge | Exactly. There it is in three words.
Franklyn | Why not in one word? Platitudes. That is what principle without program means.
Burge | Puzzled but patient, trying to get at Franklyn’s drift in order to ascertain his price. I have not made myself clear. Listen. I am agreeing with you. I am on your side. I am accepting your proposal. There isn’t going to be any more coalition. This time there won’t be a Tory in the Cabinet. Every candidate will have to pledge himself to Free Trade, slightly modified by consideration for our Overseas Dominions; to Disestablishment; to Reform of the House of Lords; to a revised scheme of Taxation of Land Values; and to doing something or other to keep the Irish quiet. Does that satisfy you?
Franklyn | It does not even interest me. Suppose your friends do commit themselves to all this! What does it prove about them except that they are hopelessly out of date even in party politics? that they have learnt nothing and forgotten nothing since 1885? What is it to me that they hate the Church and hate the landed gentry; that they are jealous of the nobility, and have shipping shares instead of manufacturing businesses in the Midlands? I can find you hundreds of the most sordid rascals, or the most densely stupid reactionaries, with all these qualifications.
Burge | Personal abuse proves nothing. Do you suppose the Tories are all angels because they are all members of the Church of England?
Franklyn | No; but they stand together as members of the Church of England, whereas your people, in attacking the Church, are all over the shop. The supporters of the Church are of one mind about religion: its enemies are of a dozen minds. The Churchmen are a phalanx: your people are a mob in which atheists are jostled by Plymouth Brethren, and Positivists by Pillars of Fire. You have with you all the crudest unbelievers and all the crudest fanatics.
Burge | We stand, as Cromwell did, for liberty of conscience, if that is what you mean.
Franklyn | How can you talk such rubbish over the graves of your conscientious objectors? All law limits liberty of conscience: if a man’s conscience allows him to steal your watch or to shirk military service, how much liberty do you allow it? Liberty of conscience is not my point.
Burge | Testily. I wish you would come to your point. Half the time you are saying that you must have principles; and when I offer you principles you say they won’t work.
Franklyn | You have not offered me any principles. Your party shibboleths are not principles. If you get into power again you will find yourself at the head of a rabble of Socialists and anti-Socialists, of Jingo Imperialists and Little Englanders, of cast-iron Materialists and ecstatic Quakers, of Christian Scientists and Compulsory Inoculationists, of Syndicalists and Bureaucrats: in short, of men differing fiercely and irreconcilably on every principle that goes to the root of human society and destiny; and the impossibility of keeping such a team together will force you to sell the pass again to the solid Conservative Opposition.
Burge | Rising in wrath. Sell the pass again! You accuse me of having sold the pass!
Franklyn | When the terrible impact of real warfare swept your parliamentary sham warfare into the dustbin, you had to go behind the backs of your followers and make a secret agreement with the leaders of the Opposition to keep you in power on condition that you dropped all legislation of which they did not approve. And you could not even hold them to their bargain; for they presently betrayed the secret and forced the coalition on you.
Burge | I solemnly declare that this is a false and monstrous accusation.
Franklyn | Do you deny that the thing occurred? Were the uncontradicted reports false? Were the published letters forgeries?
Burge | Certainly not. But I did not do it. I was not Prime Minister then. It was that old dotard, that played-out old humbug Lubin. He was Prime Minister then, not I.
Franklyn | Do you mean to say you did not know?
Burge | Sitting down again with a shrug. Oh, I had to be told. But what could I do? If we had refused we might have had to go out of office.
Franklyn | Precisely.
Burge | Well, could we desert the country at such a crisis? The Hun was at the gate. Everyone has to make sacrifices for the sake of the country at such moments. We had to rise above party; and I am proud to say we never gave party a second thought. We stuck to—
Conrad | Office?
Burge | Turning on him. Yes, sir, to office: that is, to responsibility, to danger, to heart-sickening toil, to abuse and misunderstanding, to a martyrdom that made us envy the very soldiers in the trenches. If you had had to live for months on aspirin and bromide of potassium to get a wink of sleep, you wouldn’t talk about office as if it were a catch.
Franklyn | Still, you admit that under our parliamentary system Lubin could not have helped himself?
Burge | On that subject my lips are closed. Nothing will induce me to say one word against the old man. I never have; and I never will. Lubin is old: he has never been a real statesman: he is as lazy as a cat on a hearthrug: you can’t get him to attend to anything: he is good for nothing but getting up and making speeches with a peroration that goes down with the back benches. But I say nothing against him. I gather that you do not think much of me as a statesman; but at all events I can get things done. I can hustle: even you will admit that. But Lubin! Oh my stars, Lubin!! If you only knew—
The parlor maid opens the door and announces a visitor.
The Parlor Maid | Mr. Lubin.
Burge | Bounding from his chair. Lubin! Is this a conspiracy?
They all rise in amazement, staring at the door. Lubin enters: a man at the end of his sixties, a Yorkshireman with the last traces of Scandinavian flax still in his white hair, undistinguished in stature, unassuming in his manner, and taking his simple dignity for granted, but wonderfully comfortable and quite self-assured in contrast to the intellectual restlessness of Franklyn and the mesmeric self-assertiveness of Burge. His presence suddenly brings out the fact that they are unhappy men, ill at ease, square pegs in round holes, whilst he flourishes like a primrose.
The parlor maid withdraws.
Lubin | Coming to Franklyn. How do you do, Mr. Barnabas? He speaks very comfortably and kindly, much as if he were the host, and Franklyn an embarrassed but welcome guest. I had the pleasure of meeting you once at the Mansion House. I think it was to celebrate the conclusion of the hundred years peace with America.
Franklyn | Shaking hands. It was long before that: a meeting about Venezuela, when we were on the point of going to war with America.
Lubin | Not at all put out. Yes: you are quite right. I knew it was something about America. He pats Franklyn’s hand. And how have you been all this time? Well, eh?
Franklyn | Smiling to soften the sarcasm. A few vicissitudes of health naturally in so long a time.
Lubin | Just so. Just so. Looking round at Savvy. The young lady is—?
Franklyn | My daughter, Savvy.
Savvy comes from the window between her father and Lubin.
Lubin | Taking her hand affectionately in both his. And why has she never come to see us?
Burge | I don’t know whether you have noticed, Lubin, that I am present.
Savvy takes advantage of this diversion to slip away to the settee, where she is stealthily joined by Haslam, who sits down on her left.
Lubin | Seating himself in Burge’s chair with ineffable comfortableness. My dear Burge: if you imagine that it is possible to be within ten miles of your energetic presence without being acutely aware of it, you do yourself the greatest injustice. How are you? And how are your good newspaper friends? Burge makes an explosive movement; but Lubin goes on calmly and sweetly. And what are you doing here with my old friend Barnabas, if I may ask?
Burge | Sitting down in Conrad’s chair, leaving him standing uneasily in the corner. Well, just what you are doing, if you want to know. I am trying to enlist Mr. Barnabas’s valuable support for my party.
Lubin | Your party, eh? The newspaper party?
Burge | The Liberal Party. The party of which I have the honor to be leader.
Lubin | Have you now? That’s very interesting; for I thought I was the leader of the Liberal Party. However, it is very kind of you to take it off my hands, if the party will let you.
Burge | Do you suggest that I have not the support and confidence of the party?
Lubin | I don’t suggest anything, my dear Burge. Mr. Barnabas will tell you that we all think very highly of you. The country owes you a great deal. During the war, you did very creditably over the munitions; and if you were not quite so successful with the peace, nobody doubted that you meant well.
Burge | Very kind of you, Lubin. Let me remark that you cannot lead a progressive party without getting a move on.
Lubin | You mean you cannot. I did it for ten years without the least difficulty. And very comfortable, prosperous, pleasant years they were.
Burge | Yes; but what did they end in?
Lubin | In you, Burge. You don’t complain of that, do you?
Burge | Fiercely. In plague, pestilence, and famine; battle, murder, and sudden death.
Lubin | With an appreciative chuckle. The Nonconformist can quote the prayerbook for his own purposes, I see. How you enjoyed yourself over that business, Burge! Do you remember the Knockout Blow?
Burge | It came off: don’t forget that. Do you remember fighting to the last drop of your blood?
Lubin | Unruffled, to Franklyn. By the way, I remember your brother Conrad—a wonderful brain and a dear good fellow—explaining to me that I couldn’t fight to the last drop of my blood, because I should be dead long before I came to it. Most interesting, and quite true. He was introduced to me at a meeting where the suffragettes kept disturbing me. They had to be carried out kicking and making a horrid disturbance.
Conrad | No: it was later, at a meeting to support the Franchise Bill which gave them the vote.
Lubin | Discovering Conrad’s presence for the first time. You’re right: it was. I knew it had something to do with women. My memory never deceives me. Thank you. Will you introduce me to this gentleman, Barnabas?
Conrad | Not at all affably. I am the Conrad in question. He sits down in dudgeon on the vacant Chippendale.
Lubin | Are you? Looking at him pleasantly. Yes: of course you are. I never forget a face. But with an arch turn of his eyes to Savvy your pretty niece engaged all my powers of vision.
Burge | I wish youd be serious, Lubin. God knows we have passed through times terrible enough to make any man serious.
Lubin | I do not think I need to be reminded of that. In peace time I used to keep myself fresh for my work by banishing all worldly considerations from my mind on Sundays; but war has no respect for the Sabbath; and there have been Sundays within the last few years on which I have had to play as many as sixty-six games of bridge to keep my mind off the news from the front.
Burge | Scandalized. Sixty-six games of bridge on Sunday!!!
Lubin | You probably sang sixty-six hymns. But as I cannot boast either your admirable voice or your spiritual fervor, I had to fall back on bridge.
Franklyn | If I may go back to the subject of your visit, it seems to me that you may both be completely superseded by the Labor Party.
Burge | But I am in the truest sense myself a Labor leader. I—He stops, as Lubin has risen with a half-suppressed yawn, and is already talking calmly, but without a pretence of interest.
Lubin | The Labor Party! Oh no, Mr. Barnabas. No, no, no, no, no. He moves in Savvy’s direction. There will be no trouble about that. Of course we must give them a few seats: more, I quite admit, than we should have dreamt of leaving to them before the war; but—By this time he has reached the sofa where Savvy and Haslam are seated. He sits down between them; takes her hand; and drops the subject of Labor. Well, my dear young lady? What is the latest news? What’s going on? Have you seen Shoddy’s new play? Tell me all about it, and all about the latest books, and all about everything.
Savvy | You have not met Mr. Haslam. Our Rector.
Lubin | Who has quite overlooked Haslam. Never heard of him. Is he any good?
Franklyn | I was introducing him. This is Mr. Haslam.
Haslam | How d’ye do?
Lubin | I beg your pardon, Mr. Haslam. Delighted to meet you. To Savvy. Well, now, how many books have you written?
Savvy | Rather overwhelmed but attracted. None. I don’t write.
Lubin | You don’t say so; Well, what do you do? Music? Skirt-dancing?
Savvy | I don’t do anything.
Lubin | Thank God! You and I were born for one another. Who is your favorite poet, Sally?
Savvy | Savvy.
Lubin | Savvy! I never heard of him. Tell me all about him. Keep me up to date.
Savvy | It’s not a poet. I am Savvy, not Sally.
Lubin | Savvy! That’s a funny name, and very pretty. Savvy. It sounds Chinese. What does it mean?
Conrad | Short for Savage.
Lubin | Patting her hand. La belle Sauvage.
Haslam | Rising and surrendering Savvy to Lubin by crossing to the fireplace. I suppose the Church is out of it as far as progressive politics are concerned.
Burge | Nonsense! That notion about the Church being unprogressive is one of those shibboleths that our party must drop. The Church is all right essentially. Get rid of the establishment; get rid of the bishops; get rid of the candlesticks; get rid of the 39 articles; and the Church of England is just as good as any other Church; and I don’t care who hears me say so.
Lubin | It doesn’t matter a bit who hears you say so, my dear Burge. To Savvy. Who did you say your favorite poet was?
Savvy | I don’t make pets of poets. Who’s yours?
Lubin | Horace.
Savvy | Horace who?
Lubin | Quintus Horatius Flaccus: the noblest Roman of them all, my dear.
Savvy | Oh, if he is dead, that explains it. I have a theory that all the dead people we feel especially interested in must have been ourselves. You must be Horace’s reincarnation.
Lubin | Delighted. That is the very most charming and penetrating and intelligent thing that has ever been said to me. Barnabas: will you exchange daughters with me? I can give you your choice of two.
Franklyn | Man proposes. Savvy disposes.
Lubin | What does Savvy say?
Burge | Lubin: I came here to talk politics.
Lubin | Yes: you have only one subject, Burge. I came here to talk to Savvy. Take Burge into the next room, Barnabas; and let him rip.
Burge | Half-angry, half-indulgent. No; but really, Lubin, we are at a crisis—
Lubin | My dear Burge, life is a disease; and the only difference between one man and another is the stage of the disease at which he lives. You are always at the crisis; I am always in the convalescent stage. I enjoy convalescence. It is the part that makes the illness worth while.
Savvy | Half-rising. Perhaps I’d better run away. I am distracting you.
Lubin | Making her sit down again. Not at all, my dear. You are only distracting Burge. Jolly good thing for him to be distracted by a pretty girl. Just what he needs.
Burge | I sometimes envy you, Lubin. The great movement of mankind, the giant sweep of the ages, passes you by and leaves you standing.
Lubin | It leaves me sitting, and quite comfortable, thank you. Go on sweeping. When you are tired of it, come back; and you will find England where it was, and me in my accustomed place, with Miss Savvy telling me all sorts of interesting things.
Savvy | Who has been growing more and more restless. Don’t let him shut you up, Mr. Burge. You know, Mr. Lubin, I am frightfully interested in the Labor movement, and in Theosophy, and in reconstruction after the war, and all sorts of things. I daresay the flappers in your smart set are tremendously flattered when you sit beside them and are nice to them as you are being nice to me; but I am not smart; and I am no use as a flapper. I am dowdy and serious. I want you to be serious. If you refuse, I shall go and sit beside Mr. Burge, and ask him to hold my hand.
Lubin | He wouldn’t know how to do it, my dear. Burge has a reputation as a profligate—
Burge | Starting. Lubin: this is monstrous. I—
Lubin | Continuing.—but he is really a model of domesticity. His name is coupled with all the most celebrated beauties; but for him there is only one woman; and that is not you, my dear, but his very charming wife.
Burge | You are destroying my character in the act of pretending to save it. Have the goodness to confine yourself to your own character and your own wife. Both of them need all your attention.
Lubin | I have the privilege of my age and of my transparent innocence. I have not to struggle with your volcanic energy.
Burge | With an immense sense of power. No, by George!
Franklyn | I think I shall speak both for my brother and myself, and possibly also for my daughter, if I say that since the object of your visit and Mr. Joyce Burge’s is to some extent political, we should hear with great interest something about your political aims, Mr. Lubin.
Lubin | Assenting with complete good humor, and becoming attentive, clear, and businesslike in his tone. By all means, Mr. Barnabas. What we have to consider first, I take it, is what prospect there is of our finding you beside us in the House after the next election.
Franklyn | When I speak of politics, Mr. Lubin, I am not thinking of elections, or available seats, or party funds, or the registers, or even, I am sorry to have to add, of parliament as it exists at present. I had much rather you talked about bridge than about electioneering: it is the more interesting game of the two.
Burge | He wants to discuss principles, Lubin.
Lubin | Very cool and clear. I understand Mr. Barnabas quite well. But elections are unsettled things; principles are settled things.
Conrad | Impatiently. Great Heavens!—
Lubin | Interrupting him with quiet authority. One moment, Dr. Barnabas. The main principles on which modern civilized society is founded are pretty well understood among educated people. That is what our dangerously half-educated masses and their pet demagogues—if Burge will excuse that expression—
Burge | Don’t mind me. Go on. I shall have something to say presently.
Lubin | That is what our dangerously half-educated people do not realize. Take all this fuss about the Labor Party, with its imaginary new principles and new politics. The Labor members will find that the immutable laws of political economy take no more notice of their ambitions and aspirations than the law of gravitation. I speak, if I may say so, with knowledge; for I have made a special, study of the Labor question.
Franklyn | With interest and some surprise. Indeed?
Lubin | Yes. It occurred quite at the beginning of my career. I was asked to deliver an address to the students at the Working Men’s College; and I was strongly advised to comply, as Gladstone and Morley and others were doing that sort of thing at the moment. It was rather a troublesome job, because I had not gone into political economy at the time. As you know, at the university I was a classical scholar; and my profession was the Law. But I looked up the textbooks, and got up the case most carefully. I found that the correct view is that all this Trade Unionism and Socialism and so forth is founded on the ignorant delusion that wages and the production and distribution of wealth can be controlled by legislation or by any human action whatever. They obey fixed scientific laws, which have been ascertained and settled finally by the highest economic authorities. Naturally I do not at this distance of time remember the exact process of reasoning; but I can get up the case again at any time in a couple of days; and you may rely on me absolutely, should the occasion arise, to deal with all these ignorant and unpractical people in a conclusive and convincing way, except, of course, as far as it may be advisable to indulge and flatter them a little so as to let them down without creating ill feeling in the working-class electorate. In short, I can get that lecture up again almost at a moment’s notice.
Savvy | But, Mr. Lubin, I have had a university education too; and all this about wages and distribution being fixed by immutable laws of political economy is obsolete rot.
Franklyn | Shocked. Oh, my dear! That is not polite.
Lubin | No, no, no. Don’t scold her. She mustn’t be scolded. To Savvy. I understand. You are a disciple of Karl Marx.
Savvy | No, no. Karl Marx’s economics are all rot.
Lubin | At last a little taken aback. Dear me!
Savvy | You must excuse me, Mr. Lubin; but it’s like hearing a man talk about the Garden of Eden.
Conrad | Why shouldn’t he talk about the Garden of Eden? It was a first attempt at biology anyhow.
Lubin | Recovering his self-possession. I am sound on the Garden of Eden. I have heard of Darwin.
Savvy | But Darwin is all rot.
Lubin | What! Already!
Savvy | It’s no good your smiling at me like a Cheshire cat, Mr. Lubin; and I am not going to sit here mumchance like an old-fashioned goody goody wife while you men monopolize the conversation and pay out the very ghastliest exploded drivel as the latest thing in politics. I am not giving you my own ideas, Mr. Lubin, but just the regular orthodox science of today. Only the most awful old fossils think that Socialism is bad economics and that Darwin invented Evolution. Ask Papa. Ask Uncle. Ask the first person you meet in the street. She rises and crosses to Haslam. Give me a cigarette, Bill, will you?
Haslam | Priceless. He complies.
Franklyn | Savvy has not lived long enough to have any manners, Mr. Lubin; but that is where you stand with the younger generation. Don’t smoke, dear.
Savvy, with a shrug of rather mutinous resignation, throws the cigarette into the fire. Haslam, on the point of lighting one for himself, changes his mind.
Lubin | Shrewd and serious. Mr. Barnabas: I confess I am surprised; and I will not pretend that I am convinced. But I am open to conviction. I may be wrong.
Burge | In a burst of irony. Oh no. Impossible! Impossible!
Lubin | Yes, Mr. Barnabas, though I do not possess Burge’s genius for being always wrong, I have been in that position once or twice. I could not conceal from you, even if I wished to, that my time has been so completely filled by my professional work as a lawyer, and later on by my duties as leader of the House of Commons in the days when Prime Ministers were also leaders—
Burge | Stung. Not to mention bridge and smart society.
Lubin | Not to mention the continual and trying effort to make Burge behave himself, that I have not been able to keep my academic reading up to date. I have kept my classics brushed up out of sheer love for them; but my economics and my science, such as they were, may possibly be a little rusty. Yet I think I may say that if you and your brother will be so good as to put me on the track of the necessary documents, I will undertake to put the case to the House or to the country to your entire satisfaction. You see, as long as you can show these troublesome half-educated people who want to turn the world upside down that they are talking nonsense, it really does not matter very much whether you do it in terms of what Miss Barnabas calls obsolete rot or in terms of what her granddaughter will probably call unmitigated tosh. I have no objection whatever to denounce Karl Marx. Anything I can say against Darwin will please a large body of sincerely pious voters. If it will be easier to carry on the business of the country on the understanding that the present state of things is to be called Socialism, I have no objection in the world to call it Socialism. There is the precedent of the Emperor Constantine, who saved the society of his own day by agreeing to call his Imperialism Christianity. Mind: I must not go ahead of the electorate. You must not call a voter a Socialist until—
Franklyn | Until he is a Socialist. Agreed.
Lubin | Oh, not at all. You need not wait for that. You must not call him a Socialist until he wishes to be called a Socialist: that is all. Surely you would not say that I must not address my constituents as gentlemen until they are gentlemen. I address them as gentlemen because they wish to be so addressed. He rises from the sofa and goes to Franklyn, placing a reassuring hand on his shoulder. Do not be afraid of Socialism, Mr. Barnabas. You need not tremble for your property or your position or your dignity. England will remain what England is, no matter what new political names may come into vogue. I do not intend to resist the transition to Socialism. You may depend on me to guide it, to lead it, to give suitable expression to its aspirations, and to steer it clear of Utopian absurdities. I can honestly ask for your support on the most advanced Socialist grounds no less than on the soundest Liberal ones.
Burge | In short, Lubin, you’re incorrigible. You don’t believe anything is going to change. The millions are still to toil—the people—my people—for I am a man of the people—
Lubin | Interrupting him contemptuously. Don’t be ridiculous, Burge. You are a country solicitor, further removed from the people, more foreign to them, more jealous of letting them up to your level, than any duke or any archbishop.
Burge | Hotly. I deny it. You think I have never been poor. You think I have never cleaned my own boots. You think my fingers have never come out through the soles when I was cleaning them. You think—
Lubin | I think you fall into the very common mistake of supposing that it is poverty that makes the proletarian and money that makes the gentleman. You are quite wrong. You never belonged to the people: you belonged to the impecunious. Impecuniosity and broken boots are the lot of the unsuccessful middle class, and the commonplaces of the early struggles of the professional and younger son class. I defy you to find a farm laborer in England with broken boots. Call a mechanic one of the poor, and he’ll punch your head. When you talk to your constituents about the toiling millions, they don’t consider that you are referring to them. They are all third cousins of somebody with a title or a park. I am a Yorkshireman, my friend. I know England; and you don’t. If you did you would know—
Burge | What do you know that I don’t know?
Lubin | I know that we are taking up too much of Mr. Barnabas’s time. Franklyn rises. May I take it, my dear Barnabas, that I may count on your support if we succeed in forcing an election before the new register is in full working order?
Burge | Rising also. May the party count on your support? I say nothing about myself. Can the party depend on you? Is there any question of yours that I have left unanswered?
Conrad | We haven’t asked you any, you know.
Burge | May I take that as a mark of confidence?
Conrad | If I were a laborer in your constituency, I should ask you a biological question?
Lubin | No you wouldn’t, my dear Doctor. Laborers never ask questions.
Burge | Ask it now. I have never flinched from being heckled. Out with it. Is it about the land?
Conrad | No.
Burge | Is it about the Church?
Conrad | No.
Burge | Is it about the House of Lords?
Conrad | No.
Burge | Is it about Proportional Representation?
Conrad | No.
Burge | Is it about Free Trade?
Conrad | No.
Burge | Is it about the priest in the school?
Conrad | No.
Burge | Is it about Ireland?
Conrad | No.
Burge | Is it about Germany?
Conrad | No.
Burge | Well, is it about Republicanism? Come! I won’t flinch. Is it about the Monarchy?
Conrad | No.
Burge | Well, what the devil is it about, then?
Conrad | You understand that I am asking the question in the character of a laborer who earned thirteen shillings a week before the war and earns thirty now, when he can get it?
Burge | Yes: I understand that. I am ready for you. Out with it.
Conrad | And whom you propose to represent in parliament?
Burge | Yes, yes, yes. Come on.
Conrad | The question is this. Would you allow your son to marry my daughter, or your daughter to marry my son?
Burge | Taken aback. Oh, come! That’s not a political question.
Conrad | Then, as a biologist, I don’t take the slightest interest in your politics; and I shall not walk across the street to vote for you or anyone else at the election. Good evening.
Lubin | Serve you right, Burge! Dr. Barnabas: you have my assurance that my daughter shall marry the man of her choice, whether he be lord or laborer. May I count on your support?
Burge | Hurling the epithet at him. Humbug!
Savvy | Stop. They all stop short in the movement of leave-taking to look at her. Daddy: are you going to let them off like this? How are they to know anything if nobody ever tells them? If you don’t, I will.
Conrad | You can’t. You didn’t read my book; and you know nothing about it. You just hold your tongue.
Savvy | I just won’t, Nunk. I shall have a vote when I am thirty; and I ought to have it now. Why are these two ridiculous people to be allowed to come in and walk over us as if the world existed only to play their silly parliamentary game?
Franklyn | Severely. Savvy: you really must not be uncivil to our guests.
Savvy | I’m sorry. But Mr. Lubin didn’t stand on much ceremony with me, did he? And Mr. Burge hasn’t addressed a single word to me. I’m not going to stand it. You and Nunk have a much better program than either of them. It’s the only one we are going to vote for; and they ought to be told about it for the credit of the family and the good of their own souls. You just tip them a chapter from The Gospel of the Brothers Barnabas, Daddy.
Lubin and Burge turn inquiringly to Franklyn, suspecting a move to form a new party.
Franklyn | It is quite true, Mr. Lubin, that I and my brother have a little program of our own which—
Conrad | Interrupting. It’s not a little program: it’s an almighty big one. It’s not our own: it’s the program of the whole of civilization.
Burge | Then why split the party before you have put it to us? For God’s sake let us have no more splits. I am here to learn. I am here to gather your opinions and represent them. I invite you to put your views before me. I offer myself to be heckled. You have asked me only an absurd nonpolitical question.
Franklyn | Candidly, I fear our program will be thrown away on you. It would not interest you.
Burge | With challenging audacity. Try. Lubin can go if he likes; but I am still open to new ideas, if only I can find them.
Franklyn | To Lubin. Are you prepared to listen, Mr. Lubin; or shall I thank you for your very kind and welcome visit, and say good evening?
Lubin | Sitting down resignedly on the settee, but involuntarily making a movement which looks like the stifling of a yawn. With pleasure, Mr. Barnabas. Of course you know that before I can adopt any new plank in the party platform, it will have to reach me through the National Liberal Federation, which you can approach through your local Liberal and Radical Association.
Franklyn | I could recall to you several instances of the addition to your party program of measures of which no local branch of your Federation had ever dreamt. But I understand that you are not really interested. I will spare you, and drop the subject.
Lubin | Waking up a little. You quite misunderstand me. Please do not take it in that way. I only—
Burge | Talking him down. Never mind the Federation: I will answer for the Federation. Go on, Barnabas: go on. Never mind Lubin. He sits down in the chair from which Lubin first displaced him.
Franklyn | Our program is only that the term of human life shall be extended to three hundred years.
Lubin | Softly. Eh?
Burge | Explosively. What!
Savvy | Our election cry is “Back to Methuselah!”
Haslam | Priceless!
Lubin and Burge look at one another.
Conrad | No. We are not mad.
Savvy | They’re not joking either. They mean it.
Lubin | Cautiously. Assuming that, in some sense which I am for the moment unable to fathom, you are in earnest, Mr. Barnabas, may I ask what this has to do with politics?
Franklyn | The connection is very evident. You are now, Mr. Lubin, within immediate reach of your seventieth year. Mr. Joyce Burge is your junior by about eleven years. You will go down to posterity as one of a European group of immature statesmen and monarchs who, doing the very best for your respective countries of which you were capable, succeeded in all-but-wrecking the civilization of Europe, and did, in effect, wipe out of existence many millions of its inhabitants.
Burge | Less than a million.
Franklyn | That was our loss alone.
Burge | Oh, if you count foreigners—!
Haslam | God counts foreigners, you know.
Savvy | With intense satisfaction. Well said, Bill.
Franklyn | I am not blaming you. Your task was beyond human capacity. What with our huge armaments, our terrible engines of destruction, our systems of coercion manned by an irresistible police, you were called on to control powers so gigantic that one shudders at the thought of their being entrusted even to an infinitely experienced and benevolent God, much less to mortal men whose whole life does not last a hundred years.
Burge | We won the war: don’t forget that.
Franklyn | No: the soldiers and sailors won it, and left you to finish it. And you were so utterly incompetent that the multitudes of children slain by hunger in the first years of peace made us all wish we were at war again.
Conrad | It’s no use arguing about it. It is now absolutely certain that the political and social problems raised by our civilization cannot be solved by mere human mushrooms who decay and die when they are just beginning to have a glimmer of the wisdom and knowledge needed for their own government.
Lubin | Quite an interesting idea, Doctor. Extravagant. Fantastic. But quite interesting. When I was young I used to feel my human limitations very acutely.
Burge | God knows I have often felt that I could not go on if it had not been for the sense that I was only an instrument in the hands of a Power above us.
Conrad | I’m glad you both agree with us, and with one another.
Lubin | I have not gone so far as that, I think. After all, we have had many very able political leaders even within your recollection and mine.
Franklyn | Have you read the recent biographies—Dilke’s, for instance—which revealed the truth about them?
Lubin | I did not discover any new truth revealed in these books, Mr. Barnabas.
Franklyn | What! Not the truth that England was governed all that time by a little woman who knew her own mind?
Savvy | Hear, hear!
Lubin | That often happens. Which woman do you mean?
Franklyn | Queen Victoria, to whom your Prime Ministers stood in the relation of naughty children whose heads she knocked together when their tempers and quarrels became intolerable. Within thirteen years of her death Europe became a hell.
Burge | Quite true. That was because she was piously brought up, and regarded herself as an instrument. If a statesman remembers that he is only an instrument, and feels quite sure that he is rightly interpreting the divine purpose, he will come out all right, you know.
Franklyn | The Kaiser felt like that. Did he come out all right?
Burge | Well, let us be fair, even to the Kaiser. Let us be fair.
Franklyn | Were you fair to him when you won an election on the program of hanging him?
Burge | Stuff! I am the last man alive to hang anybody; but the people wouldn’t listen to reason. Besides, I knew the Dutch wouldn’t give him up.
Savvy | Oh, don’t start arguing about poor old Bill. Stick to our point. Let these two gentlemen settle the question for themselves. Mr. Burge: do you think Mr. Lubin is fit to govern England?
Burge | No. Frankly, I don’t.
Lubin | Remonstrant. Really!
Conrad | Why?
Burge | Because he has no conscience: that’s why.
Lubin | Shocked and amazed. Oh!
Franklyn | Mr. Lubin: do you consider Joyce Burge qualified to govern England?
Lubin | With dignified emotion, wounded, but without bitterness. Excuse me, Mr. Barnabas; but before I answer that question I want to say this. Burge: we have had differences of opinion; and your newspaper friends have said hard things of me. But we worked together for years; and I hope I have done nothing to justify you in the amazing accusation you have just brought against me. Do you realize that you said that I have no conscience?
Burge | Lubin: I am very accessible to an appeal to my emotions; and you are very cunning in making such appeals. I will meet you to this extent. I don’t mean that you are a bad man. I don’t mean that I dislike you, in spite of your continual attempts to discourage and depress me. But you have a mind like a looking-glass. You are very clear and smooth and lucid as to what is standing in front of you. But you have no foresight and no hindsight. You have no vision and no memory. You have no continuity; and a man without continuity can have neither conscience nor honor from one day to another. The result is that you have always been a damned bad minister; and you have sometimes been a damned bad friend. Now you can answer Barnabas’s question and take it out of me to your heart’s content. He asked you was I fit to govern England.
Lubin | Recovering himself. After what has just passed I sincerely wish I could honestly say yes, Burge. But it seems to me that you have condemned yourself out of your own mouth. You represent something which has had far too much influence and popularity in this country since Joseph Chamberlain set the fashion; and that is mere energy without intellect and without knowledge. Your mind is not a trained mind: it has not been stored with the best information, nor cultivated by intercourse with educated minds at any of our great seats of learning. As I happen to have enjoyed that advantage, it follows that you do not understand my mind. Candidly, I think that disqualifies you. The peace found out your weaknesses.
Burge | Oh! What did it find out in you?
Lubin | You and your newspaper confederates took the peace out of my hands. The peace did not find me out because it did not find me in.
Franklyn | Come! Confess, both of you! You were only flies on the wheel. The war went England’s way; but the peace went its own way, and not England’s way nor any of the ways you had so glibly appointed for it. Your peace treaty was a scrap of paper before the ink dried on it. The statesmen of Europe were incapable of governing Europe. What they needed was a couple of hundred years training and experience: what they had actually had was a few years at the bar or in a countinghouse or on the grouse moors and golf courses. And now we are waiting, with monster cannons trained on every city and seaport, and huge aeroplanes ready to spring into the air and drop bombs every one of which will obliterate a whole street, and poison gases that will strike multitudes dead with a breath, until one of you gentlemen rises in his helplessness to tell us, who are as helpless as himself, that we are at war again.
Conrad | Aha! What consolation will it be for us then that you two are able to tell off one another’s defects so cleverly in your afternoon chat?
Burge | Angrily. If you come to that, what consolation will it be that you two can sit there and tell both of us off? you, who have had no responsibility! you, who haven’t lifted a finger, as far as I know, to help us through this awful crisis which has left me ten years older than my proper age! Can you tell me a single thing you did to help us during the whole infernal business?
Conrad | We’re not blaming you: you hadn’t lived long enough. No more had we. Can’t you see that threescore-and-ten, though it may be long enough for a very crude sort of village life, isn’t long enough for a complicated civilization like ours? Flinders Petrie has counted nine attempts at civilization made by people exactly like us; and every one of them failed just as ours is failing. They failed because the citizens and statesmen died of old age or overeating before they had grown out of schoolboy games and savage sports and cigars and champagne. The signs of the end are always the same: Democracy, Socialism, and Votes for Women. We shall go to smash within the lifetime of men now living unless we recognize that we must live longer.
Lubin | I am glad you agree with me that Socialism and Votes for Women are signs of decay.
Franklyn | Not at all: they are only the difficulties that overtax your capacity. If you cannot organize Socialism you cannot organize civilized life; and you will relapse into barbarism accordingly.
Savvy | Hear, hear!
Burge | A useful point. We cannot put back the clock.
Haslam | I can. I’ve often done it.
Lubin | Tut tut! My dear Burge: what are you dreaming of? Mr. Barnabas: I am a very patient man. But will you tell me what earthly use or interest there is in a conclusion that cannot be realized? I grant you that if we could live three hundred years we should all be, perhaps wiser, certainly older. You will grant me in return, I hope, that if the sky fell we should all catch larks.
Franklyn | Your turn now, Conrad. Go ahead.
Conrad | I don’t think it’s any good. I don’t think they want to live longer than usual.
Lubin | Although I am a mere child of 69, I am old enough to have lost the habit of crying for the moon.
Burge | Have you discovered the elixir of life or have you not? If not, I agree with Lubin that you are wasting our time.
Conrad | Is your time of any value?
Burge | Unable to believe his ears. My time of any value! What do you mean?
Lubin | Smiling comfortably. From your high scientific point of view, I daresay, none whatever, Professor. In any case I think a little perfectly idle discussion would do Burge good. After all, we might as well hear about the elixir of life as read novels, or whatever Burge does when he is not playing golf on Walton Heath. What is your elixir, Dr. Barnabas? Lemons? Sour milk? Or what is the latest?
Burge | We were just beginning to talk seriously; and now you snatch at the chance of talking rot. He rises. Good evening. He turns to the door.
Conrad | Rudely. Die as soon as you like. Good evening.
Burge | Hesitating. Look here. I took sour milk twice a day until Metchnikoff died. He thought it would keep him alive forever; and he died of it.
Conrad | You might as well have taken sour beer.
Burge | You believe in lemons?
Conrad | I wouldn’t eat a lemon for ten pounds.
Burge | Sitting down again. What do you recommend?
Conrad | Rising with a gesture of despair. What’s the use of going on, Frank? Because I am a doctor, and because they think I have a bottle to give them that will make them live forever, they are listening to me for the first time with their mouths open and their eyes shut. That’s their notion of science.
Savvy | Steady, Nunk! Hold the fort.
Conrad | Growls and sits down. !!!
Lubin | You volunteered the consultation, Doctor. I may tell you that, far from sharing the credulity as to science which is now the fashion, I am prepared to demonstrate that during the last fifty years, though the Church has often been wrong, and even the Liberal Party has not been infallible, the men of science have always been wrong.
Conrad | Yes: the fellows you call men of science. The people who make money by it, and their medical hangers-on. But has anybody been right?
Lubin | The poets and story tellers, especially the classical poets and story tellers, have been, in the main, right. I will ask you not to repeat this as my opinion outside; for the vote of the medical profession and its worshippers is not to be trifled with.
Franklyn | You are quite right: the poem is our real clue to biological science. The most scientific document we possess at present is, as your grandmother would have told you quite truly, the story of the Garden of Eden.
Burge | Pricking up his ears. What’s that? If you can establish that, Barnabas, I am prepared to hear you out with my very best attention. I am listening. Go on.
Franklyn | Well, you remember, don’t you, that in the Garden of Eden Adam and Eve were not created mortal, and that natural death, as we call it, was not a part of life, but a later and quite separate invention?
Burge | Now you mention it, that’s true. Death came afterwards.
Lubin | What about accidental death? That was always possible.
Franklyn | Precisely. Adam and Eve were hung up between two frightful possibilities. One was the extinction of mankind by their accidental death. The other was the prospect of living forever. They could bear neither. They decided that they would just take a short turn of a thousand years, and meanwhile hand on their work to a new pair. Consequently, they had to invent natural birth and natural death, which are, after all, only modes of perpetuating life without putting on any single creature the terrible burden of immortality.
Lubin | I see. The old must make room for the new.
Burge | Death is nothing but making room. That’s all there is in it or ever has been in it.
Franklyn | Yes; but the old must not desert their posts until the new are ripe for them. They desert them now two hundred years too soon.
Savvy | I believe the old people are the new people reincarnated, Nunk. I suspect I am Eve. I am very fond of apples; and they always disagree with me.
Conrad | You are Eve, in a sense. The Eternal Life persists; only It wears out Its bodies and minds and gets new ones, like new clothes. You are only a new hat and frock on Eve.
Franklyn | Yes. Bodies and minds ever better and better fitted to carry out Its eternal pursuit.
Lubin | With quiet scepticism. What pursuit, may one ask, Mr. Barnabas?
Franklyn | The pursuit of omnipotence and omniscience. Greater power and greater knowledge: these are what we are all pursuing even at the risk of our lives and the sacrifice of our pleasures. Evolution is that pursuit and nothing else. It is the path to godhead. A man differs from a microbe only in being further on the path.
Lubin | And how soon do you expect this modest end to be reached?
Franklyn | Never, thank God! As there is no limit to power and knowledge there can be no end. “The power and the glory, world without end”: have those words meant nothing to you?
Burge | Pulling out an old envelope. I should like to make a note of that. He does so.
Conrad | There will always be something to live for.
Burge | Pocketing his envelope and becoming more and more businesslike. Right: I have got that. Now what about sin? What about the Fall? How do you work them in?
Conrad | I don’t work in the Fall. The Fall is outside Science. But I daresay Frank can work it in for you.
Burge | To Franklyn. I wish you would, you know. It’s important. Very important.
Franklyn | Well, consider it this way. It is clear that when Adam and Eve were immortal it was necessary that they should make the earth an extremely comfortable place to live in.
Burge | True. If you take a house on a ninety-nine years lease, you spend a good deal of money on it. If you take it for three months you generally have a bill for dilapidations to pay at the end of them.
Franklyn | Just so. Consequently, when Adam had the Garden of Eden on a lease forever, he took care to make it what the house agents call a highly desirable country residence. But the moment he invented death, and became a tenant for life only, the place was no longer worth the trouble. It was then that he let the thistles grow. Life was so short that it was no longer worth his while to do anything thoroughly well.
Burge | Do you think that is enough to constitute what an average elector would consider a Fall? Is it tragic enough?
Franklyn |

That is only the first step of the Fall. Adam did not fall down that step only: he fell down a whole flight. For instance, before he invented birth he dared not have lost his temper; for if he had killed Eve he would have been lonely and barren to all eternity. But when he invented birth, and anyone who was killed could be replaced, he could afford to let himself go. He undoubtedly invented wife-beating; and that was another step down. One of his sons invented meat-eating. The other was horrified at the innovation. With the ferocity which is still characteristic of bulls and other vegetarians, he slew his beefsteak-eating brother, and thus invented murder. That was a very steep step. It was so exciting that all the others began to kill one another for sport, and thus invented war, the steepest step of all. They even took to killing animals as a means of killing time, and then, of course, ate them to save the long and difficult labor of agriculture. I ask you to contemplate our fathers as they came crashing down all the steps of this Jacob’s ladder that reached from paradise to a hell on earth in which they had multiplied the chances of death from violence, accident, and disease until they could hardly count on three score and ten years of life, much less the thousand that Adam had been ready to face! With that picture before you, will you now ask me where was the Fall? You might as well stand at the foot of Snowdon and ask me where is the mountain. The very children see it so plainly that they compress its history into a two line epic:

Old Daddy Long Legs wouldn’t say his prayers:
Take him by the hind legs and throw him downstairs.

Lubin | Still immovably sceptical. And what does Science say to this fairy tale, Doctor Barnabas? Surely Science knows nothing of Genesis, or of Adam and Eve.
Conrad | Then it isn’t Science: that’s all. Science has to account for everything; and everything includes the Bible.
Franklyn | The Book of Genesis is a part of nature like any other part of nature. The fact that the tale of the Garden of Eden has survived and held the imagination of men spellbound for centuries, whilst hundreds of much more plausible and amusing stories have gone out of fashion and perished like last year’s popular song, is a scientific fact; and Science is bound to explain it. You tell me that Science knows nothing of it. Then Science is more ignorant than the children at any village school.
Conrad | Of course if you think it more scientific to say that what we are discussing is not Adam and Eve and Eden, but the phylogeny of the blastoderm—
Savvy | You needn’t swear, Nunk.
Conrad | Shut up, you: I am not swearing. To Lubin. If you want the professional humbug of rewriting the Bible in words of four syllables, and pretending it’s something new, I can humbug you to your heart’s content. I can call Genesis Phylogenesis. Let the Creator say, if you like, “I will establish an antipathetic symbiosis between thee and the female, and between thy blastoderm and her blastoderm.” Nobody will understand you; and Savvy will think you are swearing. The meaning is the same.
Haslam | Priceless. But it’s quite simple. The one version is poetry: the other is science.
Franklyn | The one is classroom jargon: the other is inspired human language.
Lubin | Calmly reminiscent. One of the few modern authors into whom I have occasionally glanced is Rousseau, who was a sort of Deist like Burge—
Burge | Interrupting him forcibly. Lubin: has this stupendously important communication which Professor Barnabas has just made to us: a communication for which I shall be indebted to him all my life long: has this, I say, no deeper effect on you than to set you pulling my leg by trying to make out that I am an infidel?
Lubin | It’s very interesting and amusing, Burge; and I think I see a case in it. I think I could undertake to argue it in an ecclesiastical court. But important is hardly a word I should attach to it.
Burge | Good God! Here is this professor: a man utterly removed from the turmoil of our political life: devoted to pure learning in its most abstract phases; and I solemnly declare he is the greatest politician, the most inspired party leader, in the kingdom. I take off my hat to him. I, Joyce Burge, give him best. And you sit there purring like an Angora cat, and can see nothing in it!
Conrad | Opening his eyes widely. Hallo! What have I done to deserve this tribute?
Burge | Done! You have put the Liberal Party into power for the next thirty years, Doctor: that’s what you’ve done.
Conrad | God forbid!
Burge | It’s all up with the Church now. Thanks to you, we go to the country with one cry and one only. Back to the Bible! Think of the effect on the Nonconformist vote. You gather that in with one hand; and you gather in the modern scientific sceptical professional vote with the other. The village atheist and the first cornet in the local Salvation Army band meet on the village green and shake hands. You take your school children, your Bible class under the Cowper-Temple clause, into the museum. You show the kids the Piltdown skull; and you say, “That’s Adam. That’s Eve’s husband.” You take the spectacled science student from the laboratory in Owens College; and when he asks you for a truly scientific history of Evolution, you put into his hand The Pilgrim’s Progress. You—Savvy and Haslam explode into shrieks of merriment. What are you two laughing at?
Savvy | Oh, go on, Mr. Burge. Don’t stop.
Haslam | Priceless!
Franklyn | Would thirty years of office for the Liberal Party seem so important to you, Mr. Burge, if you had another two and a half centuries to live?
Burge | Decisively. No. You will have to drop that part of it. The constituencies won’t swallow it.
Lubin | Seriously. I am not so sure of that, Burge. I am not sure that it may not prove the only point they will swallow.
Burge | It will be no use to us even if they do. It’s not a party point. It’s as good for the other side as for us.
Lubin | Not necessarily. If we get in first with it, it will be associated in the public mind with our party. Suppose I put it forward as a plank in our program that we advocate the extension of human life to three hundred years! Dunreen, as leader of the opposite party, will be bound to oppose me: to denounce me as a visionary and so forth. By doing so he will place himself in the position of wanting to rob the people of two hundred and thirty years of their natural life. The Unionists will become the party of Premature Death; and we shall become the Longevity party.
Burge | Shaken. You really think the electorate would swallow it?
Lubin | My dear Burge: is there anything the electorate will not swallow if it is judiciously put to them? But we must make sure of our ground. We must have the support of the men of science. Is there serious agreement among them, Doctor, as to the possibility of such an evolution as you have described?
Conrad | Yes. Ever since the reaction against Darwin set in at the beginning of the present century, all scientific opinion worth counting has been converging rapidly upon Creative Evolution.
Franklyn | Poetry has been converging on it: philosophy has been converging on it: religion has been converging on it. It is going to be the religion of the twentieth century: a religion that has its intellectual roots in philosophy and science just as medieval Christianity had its intellectual roots in Aristotle.
Lubin | But surely any change would be so extremely gradual that—
Conrad | Don’t deceive yourself. It’s only the politicians who improve the world so gradually that nobody can see the improvement. The notion that Nature does not proceed by jumps is only one of the budget of plausible lies that we call classical education. Nature always proceeds by jumps. She may spend twenty thousand years making up her mind to jump; but when she makes it up at last, the jump is big enough to take us into a new age.
Lubin | Impressed. Fancy my being leader of the party for the next three hundred years!
Burge | What!!
Lubin | Perhaps hard on some of the younger men. I think in fairness I shall have to step aside to make room after another century or so: that is, if Mimi can be persuaded to give up Downing Street.
Burge | This is too much. Your colossal conceit blinds you to the most obvious necessity of the political situation.
Lubin | You mean my retirement. I really cannot see that it is a necessity. I could not see it when I was almost an old man—or at least an elderly one. Now that it appears that I am a young man, the case for it breaks down completely. To Conrad. May I ask are there any alternative theories? Is there a scientific Opposition?
Conrad | Well, some authorities hold that the human race is a failure, and that a new form of life, better adapted to high civilization, will supersede us as we have superseded the ape and the elephant.
Burge | The superman: eh!
Conrad | No. Some being quite different from us.
Lubin | Is that altogether desirable?
Franklyn | I fear so. However that may be, we may be quite sure of one thing. We shall not be let alone. The force behind evolution, call it what you will, is determined to solve the problem of civilization; and if it cannot do it through us, it will produce some more capable agents. Man is not God’s last word: God can still create. If you cannot do His work He will produce some being who can.
Burge | With zealous reverence. What do we know about Him, Barnabas? What does anyone know about Him?
Conrad | We know this about Him with absolute certainty. The power my brother calls God proceeds by the method of Trial and Error; and if we turn out to be one of the errors, we shall go the way of the mastodon and the megatherium and all the other scrapped experiments.
Lubin | Rising and beginning to walk up and down the room with his considering cap on. I admit that I am impressed, gentlemen. I will go so far as to say that your theory is likely to prove more interesting than ever Welsh Disestablishment was. But as a practical politician—hm! Eh, Burge?
Conrad | We are not practical politicians. We are out to get something done. Practical politicians are people who have mastered the art of using parliament to prevent anything being done.
Franklyn | When we get matured statesmen and citizens—
Lubin | Stopping short. Citizens! Oh! Are the citizens to live three hundred years as well as the statesmen?
Conrad | Of course.
Lubin | I confess that had not occurred to me. He sits down abruptly, evidently very unfavorably affected by this new light.
Savvy and Haslam look at one another with unspeakable feelings.
Burge | Do you think it would be wise to go quite so far at first? Surely it would be more prudent to begin with the best men.
Franklyn | You need not be anxious about that. It will begin with the best men.
Lubin | I am glad to hear you say so. You see, we must put this into a practical parliamentary shape.
Burge | We shall have to draft a Bill: that is the long and the short of it. Until you have your Bill drafted you don’t know what you are really doing: that is my experience.
Lubin | Quite so. My idea is that whilst we should interest the electorate in this as a sort of religious aspiration and personal hope, using it at the same time to remove their prejudices against those of us who are getting on in years, it would be in the last degree upsetting and even dangerous to enable everyone to live longer than usual. Take the mere question of the manufacture of the specific, whatever it may be! There are forty millions of people in the country. Let me assume for the sake of illustration that each person would have to consume, say, five ounces a day of the elixir. That would be—let me see—five times three hundred and sixty-five is—um—twenty-five—thirty-two—eighteen—eighteen hundred and twenty-five ounces a year: just two ounces over the hundredweight.
Burge | Two million tons a year, in round numbers, of stuff that everyone would clamor for: that men would trample down women and children in the streets to get at. You couldn’t produce it. There would be blue murder. It’s out of the question. We must keep the actual secret to ourselves.
Conrad | Staring at them. The actual secret! What on earth is the man talking about?
Burge | The stuff. The powder. The bottle. The tabloid. Whatever it is. You said it wasn’t lemons.
Conrad | My good sir: I have no powder, no bottle, no tabloid. I am not a quack: I am a biologist. This is a thing that’s going to happen.
Lubin | Completely let down. Going to happen! Oh! Is that all? He looks at his watch.
Burge | Going to happen! What do you mean? Do you mean that you can’t make it happen?
Conrad | No more than I could have made you happen.
Franklyn | We can put it into men’s heads that there is nothing to prevent its happening but their own will to die before their work is done, and their own ignorance of the splendid work there is for them to do.
Conrad | Spread that knowledge and that conviction; and as surely as the sun will rise tomorrow, the thing will happen.
Franklyn | We don’t know where or when or to whom it will happen. It may happen first to someone in this room.
Haslam | It won’t happen to me: that’s jolly sure.
Conrad | It might happen to anyone. It might happen to the parlor maid. How do we know?
Savvy | The parlor maid! Oh, that’s nonsense, Nunk.
Lubin | Once more quite comfortable. I think Miss Savvy has delivered the final verdict.
Burge | Do you mean to say that you have nothing more practical to offer than the mere wish to live longer? Why, if people could live by merely wishing to, we should all be living forever already! Everybody would like to live forever. Why don’t they?
Conrad | Pshaw! Everybody would like to have a million of money. Why haven’t they? Because the men who would like to be millionaires won’t save sixpence even with the chance of starvation staring them in the face. The men who want to live forever won’t cut off a glass of beer or a pipe of tobacco, though they believe the teetotallers and nonsmokers live longer. That sort of liking is not willing. See what they do when they know they must.
Franklyn | Do not mistake mere idle fancies for the tremendous miracle-working force of Will nerved to creation by a conviction of Necessity. I tell you men capable of such willing, and realizing its necessity, will do it reluctantly, under inner compulsion, as all great efforts are made. They will hide what they are doing from themselves: they will take care not to know what they are doing. They will live three hundred years, not because they would like to, but because the soul deep down in them will know that they must, if the world is to be saved.
Lubin | Turning to Franklyn and patting him almost paternally. Well, my dear Barnabas, for the last thirty years the post has brought me at least once a week a plan from some crank or other for the establishment of the millennium. I think you are the maddest of all the cranks; but you are much the most interesting. I am conscious of a very curious mixture of relief and disappointment in finding that your plan is all moonshine, and that you have nothing practical to offer us. But what a pity! It is such a fascinating idea! I think you are too hard on us practical men; but there are men in every Government, even on the Front Bench, who deserve all you say. And now, before dropping the subject, may I put just one question to you? An idle question, since nothing can come of it; but still—
Franklyn | Ask your question.
Lubin | Why do you fix three hundred years as the exact figure?
Franklyn | Because we must fix some figure. Less would not be enough; and more would be more than we dare as yet face.
Lubin | Pooh! I am quite prepared to face three thousand, not to say three million.
Conrad | Yes, because you don’t believe you Will be called on to make good your word.
Franklyn | Gently. Also, perhaps, because you have never been troubled much by vision of the future.
Burge | With intense conviction. The future does not exist for Henry Hopkins Lubin.
Lubin | If by the future you mean the millennial delusions which you use as a bunch of carrots to lure the uneducated British donkey to the polling booth to vote for you, it certainly does not.
Burge | I can see the future not only because, if I may say so in all humility, I have been gifted with a certain power of spiritual vision, but because I have practised as a solicitor. A solicitor has to advise families. He has to think of the future and know the past. His office is the real modern confessional. Among other things he has to make people’s wills for them. He has to show them how to provide for their daughters after their deaths. Has it occurred to you, Lubin, that if you live three hundred years, your daughters will have to wait a devilish long time for their money?
Franklyn | The money may not wait for them. Few investments flourish for three hundred years.
Savvy | And what about before your death? Suppose they didn’t get married! Imagine a girl living at home with her mother and on her father for three hundred years! They’d murder her if she didn’t murder them first.
Lubin | By the way, Barnabas, is your daughter to keep her good looks all the time?
Franklyn | Will it matter? Can you conceive the most hardened flirt going on flirting for three centuries? At the end of half the time we shall hardly notice whether it is a woman or a man we are speaking to.
Lubin | Not quite relishing this ascetic prospect. Hm! He rises. Ah, well: you must come and tell my wife and my young people all about it; and you will bring your daughter with you, of course. He shakes hands with Savvy. Goodbye. He shakes hands with Franklyn. Goodbye, Doctor. He shakes hands with Conrad. Come on, Burge: you must really tell me what line you are going to take about the Church at the election?
Burge | Haven’t you heard? Haven’t you taken in the revelation that has been vouchsafed to us? The line I am going to take is Back to Methuselah.
Lubin | Decisively. Don’t be ridiculous, Burge. You don’t suppose, do you, that our friends here are in earnest, or that our very pleasant conversation has had anything to do with practical politics! They have just been pulling our legs very wittily. Come along. He goes out, Franklyn politely going with him, but shaking his head in mute protest.
Burge | Shaking Conrad’s hand. It’s beyond the old man, Doctor. No spiritual side to him: only a sort of classical side that goes down with his own set. Besides, he’s done, gone, past, burnt out, burst up; thinks he is our leader and is only our rag and bottle department. But you may depend on me. I will work this stunt of yours in. I see its value. He begins moving towards the door with Conrad. Of course I can’t put it exactly in your way; but you are quite right about our needing something fresh; and I believe an election can be fought on the death rate and on Adam and Eve as scientific facts. It will take the Opposition right out of its depth. And if we win there will be an O.M. for somebody when the first honors list comes round. By this time he has talked himself out of the room and out of earshot, Conrad accompanying him.
Savvy and Haslam, left alone, seize each other in an ecstasy of amusement, and jazz to the settee, where they sit down again side by side.
Haslam | Caressing her. Darling! what a priceless humbug old Lubin is!
Savvy | Oh, sweet old thing! I love him. Burge is a flaming fraud if you like.
Haslam | Did you notice one thing? It struck me as rather curious.
Savvy | What?
Haslam | Lubin and your father have both survived the war. But their sons were killed in it.
Savvy | Sobered. Yes. Jim’s death killed mother.
Haslam | And they never said a word about it!
Savvy | Well, why should they? The subject didn’t come up. I forgot about it too; and I was very fond of Jim.
Haslam | I didn’t forget it, because I’m of military age; and if I hadn’t been a parson I’d have had to go out and be killed too. To me the awful thing about their political incompetence was that they had to kill their own sons. It was the war casualty lists and the starvation afterwards that finished me up with politics and the Church and everything else except you.
Savvy | Oh, I was just as bad as any of them. I sold flags in the streets in my best clothes; and—hsh! She jumps up and pretends to be looking for a book on the shelves behind the settee.
Franklyn and Conrad return, looking weary and glum.
Conrad | Well, that’s how The Gospel of the Brothers Barnabas is going to be received! He drops into Burge’s chair.
Franklyn | Going back to his seat at the table. It’s no use. Were you convinced, Mr. Haslam?
Haslam | About our being able to live three hundred years? Frankly no.
Conrad | To Savvy. Nor you, I suppose?
Savvy | Oh, I don’t know. I thought I was for a moment. I can believe, in a sort of way, that people might live for three hundred years. But when you came down to tin tacks, and said that the parlor maid might, then I saw how absurd it was.
Franklyn | Just so. We had better hold our tongues about it, Con. We should only be laughed at, and lose the little credit we earned on false pretences in the days of our ignorance.
Conrad | I daresay. But Creative Evolution doesn’t stop while people are laughing. Laughing may even lubricate its job.
Savvy | What does that mean?
Conrad | It means that the first man to live three hundred years mayn’t have the slightest notion that he is going to do it, and may be the loudest laugher of the lot.
Savvy | Or the first woman?
Conrad | Assenting. Or the first woman.
Haslam | Well, it won’t be one of us, anyhow.
Franklyn | How do you know?
This is unanswerable. None of them have anything more to say.

Part V

As Far as Thought Can Reach

AD 31,920

Summer afternoon in the year 31,920 AD. A sunlit glade at the southern foot of a thickly wooded hill. On the west side of it, the steps and columned porch of a dainty little classic temple. Between it and the hill, a rising path to the wooded heights begins with rough steps of stones in the moss. On the opposite side, a grove. In the middle of the glade, an altar in the form of a low marble table as long as a man, set parallel to the temple steps and pointing to the hill. Curved marble benches radiate from it into the foreground; but they are not joined to it: there is plenty of space to pass between the altar and the benches.

A dance of youths and maidens is in progress. The music is provided by a few flute players seated carelessly on the steps of the temple. There are no children; and none of the dancers seems younger than eighteen. Some of the youths have beards. Their dress, like the architecture of the theatre and the design of the altar and curved seats, resembles Grecian of the fourth century BC, freely handled. They move with perfect balance and remarkable grace, racing through a figure like a farandole. They neither romp nor hug in our manner.

At the first full close they clap their hands to stop the musicians, who recommence with a saraband, during which a strange figure appears on the path beyond the temple. He is deep in thought, with his eyes closed and his feet feeling automatically for the rough irregular steps as he slowly descends them. Except for a sort of linen kilt consisting mainly of a girdle carrying a sporran and a few minor pockets, he is naked. In physical hardihood and uprightness he seems to be in the prime of life; and his eyes and mouth show no signs of age; but his face, though fully and firmly fleshed, bears a network of lines, varying from furrows to hairbreadth reticulations, as if Time had worked over every inch of it incessantly through whole geologic periods. His head is finely domed and utterly bald. Except for his eyelashes he is quite hairless. He is unconscious of his surroundings, and walks right into one of the dancing couples, separating them. He wakes up and stares about him. The couple stop indignantly. The rest stop. The music stops. The youth whom he has jostled accosts him without malice, but without anything that we should call manners.

The Youth | Now, then, ancient sleepwalker, why don’t you keep your eyes open and mind where you are going?
The Ancient | Mild, bland, and indulgent. I did not know there was a nursery here, or I should not have turned my face in this direction. Such accidents cannot always be avoided. Go on with your play: I will turn back.
The Youth | Why not stay with us and enjoy life for once in a way? We will teach you to dance.
The Ancient | No, thank you. I danced when I was a child like you. Dancing is a very crude attempt to get into the rhythm of life. It would be painful to me to go back from that rhythm to your babyish gambols: in fact I could not do it if I tried. But at your age it is pleasant: and I am sorry I disturbed you.
The Youth | Come! own up: aren’t you very unhappy? It’s dreadful to see you ancients going about by yourselves, never noticing anything, never dancing, never laughing, never singing, never getting anything out of life. None of us are going to be like that when we grow up. It’s a dog’s life.
The Ancient | Not at all. You repeat that old phrase without knowing that there was once a creature on earth called a dog. Those who are interested in extinct forms of life will tell you that it loved the sound of its own voice and bounded about when it was happy, just as you are doing here. It is you, my children, who are living the dog’s life.
The Youth | The dog must have been a good sensible creature: it set you a very wise example. You should let yourself go occasionally and have a good time.
The Ancient | My children: be content to let us ancients go our ways and enjoy ourselves in our own fashion.
He turns to go.
The Maiden | But wait a moment. Why will you not tell us how you enjoy yourself? You must have secret pleasures that you hide from us, and that you never get tired of. I get tired of all our dances and all our tunes. I get tired of all my partners.
The Youth | Suspiciously. Do you? I shall bear that in mind.
They all look at one another as if there were some sinister significance in what she has said.
The Maiden | We all do: what is the use of pretending we don’t? It is natural.
Several Young People | No, no. We don’t. It is not natural.
The Ancient | You are older than he is, I see. You are growing up.
The Maiden | How do you know? I do not look so much older, do I?
The Ancient | Oh, I was not looking at you. Your looks do not interest me.
The Maiden | Thank you.
They all laugh.
The Youth | You old fish! I believe you don’t know the difference between a man and a woman.
The Ancient | It has long ceased to interest me in the way it interests you. And when anything no longer interests us we no longer know it.
The Maiden | You haven’t told me how I show my age. That is what I want to know. As a matter of fact I am older than this boy here: older than he thinks. How did you find that out?
The Ancient | Easily enough. You are ceasing to pretend that these childish games—this dancing and singing and mating—do not become tiresome and unsatisfying after a while. And you no longer care to pretend that you are younger than you are. These are the signs of adolescence. And then, see these fantastic rags with which you have draped yourself. He takes up a piece of her draperies in his hand. It is rather badly worn here. Why do you not get a new one?
The Maiden | Oh, I did not notice it. Besides, it is too much trouble. Clothes are a nuisance. I think I shall do without them some day, as you ancients do.
The Ancient | Signs of maturity. Soon you will give up all these toys and games and sweets.
The Youth | What! And be as miserable as you?
The Ancient | Infant: one moment of the ecstasy of life as we live it would strike you dead. He stalks gravely out through the grove.
They stare after him, much damped.
The Youth | To the musicians. Let us have another dance.
The musicians shake their heads; get up from their seats on the steps; and troop away into the temple. The others follow them, except the Maiden, who sits down on the altar.
A Maiden | As she goes. There! The ancient has put them out of countenance. It is your fault, Strephon, for provoking him. She leaves, much disappointed.
A Youth | Why need you have cheeked him like that? He goes grumbling.
Strephon | Calling after him. I thought it was understood that we are always to cheek the ancients on principle.
Another Youth | Quite right too! There would be no holding them if we didn’t. He goes.
The Maiden | Why don’t you really stand up to them? I did.
Another Youth | Sheer, abject, pusillanimous, dastardly cowardice. That’s why. Face the filthy truth. He goes.
Another Youth | Turning on the steps as he goes out. And don’t you forget, infant, that one moment of the ecstasy of life as I live it would strike you dead. Haha!
Strephon | Now the only one left, except the Maiden. Aren’t you coming, Chloe?
The Maiden | Shakes her head. !
The Youth | Hurrying back to her. What is the matter?
The Maiden | Tragically pensive. I don’t know.
The Youth | Then there is something the matter. Is that what you mean?
The Maiden | Yes. Something is happening to me. I don’t know what.
The Youth | You no longer love me. I have seen it for a month past.
The Maiden | Don’t you think all that is rather silly? We cannot go on as if this kind of thing, this dancing and sweethearting, were everything.
The Youth | What is there better? What else is there worth living for?
The Maiden | Oh, stuff! Don’t be frivolous.
The Youth | Something horrible is happening to you. You are losing all heart, all feeling. He sits on the altar beside her and buries his face in his hands. I am bitterly unhappy.
The Maiden | Unhappy! Really, you must have a very empty head if there is nothing in it but a dance with one girl who is no better than any of the other girls.
The Youth | You did not always think so. You used to be vexed if I as much as looked at another girl.
The Maiden | What does it matter what I did when I was a baby? Nothing existed for me then except what I tasted and touched and saw; and I wanted all that for myself, just as I wanted the moon to play with. Now the world is opening out for me. More than the world: the universe. Even little things are turning out to be great things, and becoming intensely interesting. Have you ever thought about the properties of numbers?
The Youth | Sitting up, markedly disenchanted. Numbers!!! I cannot imagine anything drier or more repulsive.
The Maiden | They are fascinating, just fascinating. I want to get away from our eternal dancing and music, and just sit down by myself and think about numbers.
The Youth | Rising indignantly. Oh, this is too much. I have suspected you for some time past. We have all suspected you. All the girls say that you have deceived us as to your age: that you are getting flat-chested: that you are bored with us; that you talk to the ancients when you get the chance. Tell me the truth: how old are you?
The Maiden | Just twice your age, my poor boy.
The Youth | Twice my age! Do you mean to say you are four?
The Maiden | Very nearly four.
The Youth | Collapsing on the altar with a groan. Oh!
The Maiden | My poor Strephon: I pretended I was only two for your sake. I was two when you were born. I saw you break from your shell; and you were such a charming child! You ran round and talked to us all so prettily, and were so handsome and well grown, that I lost my heart to you at once. But now I seem to have lost it altogether: bigger things are taking possession of me. Still, we were very happy in our childish way for the first year, werent we?
Strephon | I was happy until you began cooling towards me.
The Maiden | Not towards you, but towards all the trivialities of our life here. Just think. I have hundreds of years to live: perhaps thousands. Do you suppose I can spend centuries dancing; listening to flutes ringing changes on a few tunes and a few notes; raving about the beauty of a few pillars and arches; making jingles with words; lying about with your arms round me, which is really neither comfortable nor convenient; everlastingly choosing colors for dresses, and putting them on, and washing; making a business of sitting together at fixed hours to absorb our nourishment; taking little poisons with it to make us delirious enough to imagine we are enjoying ourselves; and then having to pass the nights in shelters lying in cots and losing half our lives in a state of unconsciousness. Sleep is a shameful thing: I have not slept at all for weeks past. I have stolen out at night when you were all lying insensible—quite disgusting, I call it—and wandered about the woods, thinking, thinking, thinking; grasping the world; taking it to pieces; building it up again; devising methods; planning experiments to test the methods; and having a glorious time. Every morning I have come back here with greater and greater reluctance; and I know that the time will soon come—perhaps it has come already—when I shall not come back at all.
Strephon | How horribly cold and uncomfortable!
The Maiden | Oh, don’t talk to me of comfort! Life is not worth living if you have to bother about comfort. Comfort makes winter a torture, spring an illness, summer an oppression, and autumn only a respite. The ancients could make life one long frowsty comfort if they chose. But they never lift a finger to make themselves comfortable. They will not sleep under a roof. They will not clothe themselves: a girdle with a few pockets hanging to it to carry things about in is all they wear: they will sit down on the wet moss or in a gorse bush when there is dry heather within two yards of them. Two years ago, when you were born, I did not understand this. Now I feel that I would not put myself to the trouble of walking two paces for all the comfort in the world.
Strephon | But you don’t know what this means to me. It means that you are dying to me: yes, just dying. Listen to me. He puts his arm around her.
The Maiden | Extricating herself. Don’t. We can talk quite as well without touching one another.
Strephon | Horrified. Chloe! Oh, this is the worst symptom of all! The ancients never touch one another.
The Maiden | Why should they?
Strephon | Oh, I don’t know. But don’t you want to touch me? You used to.
The Maiden | Yes: that is true: I used to. We used to think it would be nice to sleep in one another’s arms; but we never could go to sleep because our weight stopped our circulations just above the elbows. Then somehow my feeling began to change bit by bit. I kept a sort of interest in your head and arms long after I lost interest in your whole body. And now that has gone.
Strephon | You no longer care for me at all, then?
The Maiden | Nonsense! I care for you much more seriously than before; though perhaps not so much for you in particular. I mean I care more for everybody. But I don’t want to touch you unnecessarily; and I certainly don’t want you to touch me.
Strephon | Rising decisively. That finishes it. You dislike me.
The Maiden | Impatiently. I tell you again, I do not dislike you; but you bore me when you cannot understand; and I think I shall be happier by myself in future. You had better get a new companion. What about the girl who is to be born today?
Strephon | I do not want the girl who is to be born today. How do I know what she will be like? I want you.
The Maiden | You cannot have me. You must recognize facts and face them. It is no use running after a woman twice your age. I cannot make my childhood last to please you. The age of love is sweet; but it is short; and I must pay nature’s debt. You no longer attract me; and I no longer care to attract you. Growth is too rapid at my age: I am maturing from week to week.
Strephon | You are maturing, as you call it—I call it ageing—from minute to minute. You are going much further than you did when we began this conversation.
The Maiden | It is not the ageing that is so rapid. It is the realization of it when it has actually happened. Now that I have made up my mind to the fact that I have left childhood behind me, it comes home to me in leaps and bounds with every word you say.
Strephon | But your vow. Have you forgotten that? We all swore together in that temple: the temple of love. You were more earnest than any of us.
The Maiden | With a grim smile. Never to let our hearts grow cold! Never to become as the ancients! Never to let the sacred lamp be extinguished! Never to change or forget! To be remembered forever as the first company of true lovers faithful to this vow so often made and broken by past generations! Ha! ha! Oh, dear!
Strephon | Well, you need not laugh. It is a beautiful and holy compact; and I will keep it whilst I live. Are you going to break it?
The Maiden | Dear child: it has broken itself. The change has come in spite of my childish vow. She rises. Do you mind if I go into the woods for a walk by myself? This chat of ours seems to me an unbearable waste of time. I have so much to think of.
Strephon | Again collapsing on the altar and covering his eyes with his hands. My heart is broken. He weeps.
The Maiden | With a shrug. I have luckily got through my childhood without that experience. It shows how wise I was to choose a lover half my age. She goes towards the grove, and is disappearing among the trees, when another youth, older and manlier than Strephon, with crisp hair and firm arms, comes from the temple, and calls to her from the threshold.
The Temple Youth | I say, Chloe. Is there any sign of the Ancient yet? The hour of birth is overdue. The baby is kicking like mad. She will break her shell prematurely.
The Maiden | Looks across to the hill path; then points up it, and says. She is coming, Acis.
The Maiden turns away through the grove and is lost to sight among the trees.
Acis | Coming to Strephon. What’s the matter? Has Chloe been unkind?
Strephon | She has grown up in spite of all her promises. She deceived us about her age. She is four.
Acis | Four! I am sorry, Strephon. I am getting on for three myself; and I know what old age is. I hate to say “I told you so”; but she was getting a little hard set and flat-chested and thin on the top, wasn’t she?
Strephon | Breaking down. Don’t.
Acis | You must pull yourself together. This is going to be a busy day. First the birth. Then the Festival of the Artists.
Strephon | Rising. What is the use of being born if we have to decay into unnatural, heartless, loveless, joyless monsters in four short years? What use are the artists if they cannot bring their beautiful creations to life? I have a great mind to die and have done with it all. He moves away to the corner of the curved seat farthest from the theatre, and throws himself moodily into it.
An Ancient Woman has descended the hill path during Strephon’s lament, and has heard most of it. She is like the He-Ancient, equally bald, and equally without sexual charm, but intensely interesting and rather terrifying. Her sex is discoverable only by her voice, as her breasts are manly, and her figure otherwise not very different. She wears no clothes, but has draped herself rather perfunctorily with a ceremonial robe, and carries two implements like long slender saws. She comes to the altar between the two young men.
The She-Ancient | To Strephon. Infant: you are only at the beginning of it all. To Acis. Is the child ready to be born?
Acis | More than ready, Ancient. Shouting and kicking and cursing. We have called to her to be quiet and wait until you come; but of course she only half understands, and is very impatient.
The She-Ancient | Very well. Bring her out into the sun.
Acis | Going quickly into the temple. All ready. Come along.
Joyous processional music strikes up in the temple.
The She-Ancient | Going close to Strephon. Look at me.
Strephon | Sulkily keeping his face averted. Thank you; but I don’t want to be cured. I had rather be miserable in my own way than callous in yours.
The She-Ancient | You like being miserable? You will soon grow out of that. She returns to the altar.
The procession, headed by Acis, emerges from the temple. Six youths carry on their shoulders a burden covered with a gorgeous but light pall. Before them certain official maidens carry a new tunic, ewers of water, silver dishes pierced with holes, cloths, and immense sponges. The rest carry wands with ribbons, and strew flowers. The burden is deposited on the altar, and the pall removed. It is a huge egg.
The She-Ancient | Freeing her arms from her robe, and placing her saws on the altar ready to her hand in a businesslike manner. A girl, I think you said?
Acis | Yes.
The Tunic Bearer | It is a shame. Why can’t we have more boys?
Several Youths | Protesting. Not at all. More girls. We want new girls.
A Girl’s Voice From The Egg | Let me out. Let me out. I want to be born. I want to be born. The egg rocks.
Acis | Snatching a wand from one of the others and whacking the egg with it. Be quiet, I tell you. Wait. You will be born presently.
The Egg | No, no: at once, at once. I want to be born: I want to be born. Violent kicking within the egg, which rocks so hard that it has to be held on the altar by the bearers.
The She-Ancient | Silence. The music stops; and the egg behaves itself.
The She-Ancient takes her two saws, and with a couple of strokes rips the egg open. The Newly Born, a pretty girl who would have been guessed as seventeen in our day, sits up in the broken shell, exquisitely fresh and rosy, but with filaments of spare albumen clinging to her here and there.
The Newly Born | As the world bursts on her vision. Oh! Oh!! Oh!!! Oh!!!! She continues this ad libitum during the following remonstrances.
Acis | Hold your noise, will you?
The washing begins. The Newly Born shrieks and struggles.
A Youth | Lie quiet, you clammy little devil.
A Maiden | You must be washed, dear. Now quiet, quiet, quiet: be good.
Acis | Shut your mouth, or I’ll shove the sponge in it.
The Maiden | Shut your eyes. It’ll hurt if you don’t.
Another Maiden | Don’t be silly. One would think nobody had ever been born before.
The Newly Born | Yells. !!!!!!
Acis | Serve you right! You were told to shut your eyes.
The Youth | Dry her off quick. I can hardly hold her. Shut it, will you; or I’ll smack you into a pickled cabbage.
The dressing begins. The Newly Born chuckles with delight.
The Maiden | Your arms go here, dear. Isn’t it pretty? Youll look lovely.
The Newly Born | Rapturously. Oh! Oh!! Oh!!! Oh!!!!
Another Youth | No: the other arm: you’re putting it on back to front. You are a silly little beast.
Acis | Here! That’s it. Now you’re clean and decent. Up with you! Oopsh! He hauls her to her feet. She cannot walk at first, but masters it after a few steps. Now then: march. Here she is, Ancient: put her through the catechism.
The She-Ancient | What name have you chosen for her?
Acis | Amaryllis.
The She-Ancient | To the Newly Born. Your name is Amaryllis.
The Newly Born | What does it mean?
A Youth | Love.
A Maiden | Mother.
Another Youth | Lilies.
The Newly Born | To Acis. What is your name?
Acis | Acis.
The Newly Born | I love you, Acis. I must have you all to myself. Take me in your arms.
Acis | Steady, young one. I am three years old.
The Newly Born | What has that to do with it? I love you; and I must have you or I will go back into my shell again.
Acis | You can’t. It’s broken. Look here! Pointing to Strephon, who has remained in his seal without looking round at the birth, wrapped up in his sorrow. Look at this poor fellow!
The Newly Born | What is the matter with him?
Acis | When he was born he chose a girl two years old for his sweetheart. He is two years old now himself; and already his heart is broken because she is four. That means that she has grown up like this Ancient here, and has left him. If you choose me, we shall have only a year’s happiness before I break your heart by growing up. Better choose the youngest you can find.
The Newly Born | I will not choose anyone but you. You must not grow up. We will love one another forever. They all laugh. What are you laughing at?
The She-Ancient | Listen, child—
The Newly Born | Do not come near me, you dreadful old creature. You frighten me.
Acis | Just give her another moment. She is not quite reasonable yet. What can you expect from a child less than five minutes old?
The Newly Born | I think I feel a little more reasonable now. Of course I was rather young when I said that; but the inside of my head is changing very rapidly. I should like to have things explained to me.
Acis | To the She-Ancient. Is she all right, do you think?
The She-Ancient looks at the Newly Born critically; feels her bumps like a phrenologist; grips her muscles and shakes her limbs; examines her teeth; looks into her eyes for a moment; and finally relinquishes her with an air of having finished her job.
The She-Ancient | She will do. She may live.
They all wave their hands and shout for joy.
The Newly Born | Indignant. I may live! Suppose there had been anything wrong with me?
The She-Ancient | Children with anything wrong do not live here, my child. Life is not cheap with us. But you would not have felt anything.
The Newly Born | You mean that you would have murdered me!
The She-Ancient | That is one of the funny words the newly born bring with them out of the past. You will forget it tomorrow. Now listen. You have four years of childhood before you. You will not be very happy; but you will be interested and amused by the novelty of the world; and your companions here will teach you how to keep up an imitation of happiness during your four years by what they call arts and sports and pleasures. The worst of your troubles is already over.
The Newly Born | What! In five minutes?
The She-Ancient | No: you have been growing for two years in the egg. You began by being several sorts of creatures that no longer exist, though we have fossils of them. Then you became human; and you passed in fifteen months through a development that once cost human beings twenty years of awkward stumbling immaturity after they were born. They had to spend fifty years more in the sort of childhood you will complete in four years. And then they died of decay. But you need not die until your accident comes.
The Newly Born | What is my accident?
The She-Ancient | Sooner or later you will fall and break your neck; or a tree will fall on you; or you will be struck by lightning. Something or other must make an end of you some day.
The Newly Born | But why should any of these things happen to me?
The She-Ancient | There is no why. They do. Everything happens to everybody sooner or later if there is time enough. And with us there is eternity.
The Newly Born | Nothing need happen. I never heard such nonsense in all my life. I shall know how to take care of myself.
The She-Ancient | So you think.
The Newly Born | I don’t think: I know. I shall enjoy life forever and ever.
The She-Ancient | If you should turn out to be a person of infinite capacity, you will no doubt find life infinitely interesting. However, all you have to do now is to play with your companions. They have many pretty toys, as you see: a playhouse, pictures, images, flowers, bright fabrics, music: above all, themselves; for the most amusing child’s toy is another child. At the end of four years, your mind will change: you will become wise; and then you will be entrusted with power.
The Newly Born | But I want power now.
The She-Ancient | No doubt you do; so that you could play with the world by tearing it to pieces.
The Newly Born | Only to see how it is made. I should put it all together again much better than before.
The She-Ancient | There was a time when children were given the world to play with because they promised to improve it. They did not improve it; and they would have wrecked it had their power been as great as that which you will wield when you are no longer a child. Until then your young companions will instruct you in whatever is necessary. You are not forbidden to speak to the ancients; but you had better not do so, as most of them have long ago exhausted all the interest there is in observing children and conversing with them. She turns to go.
The Newly Born | Wait. Tell me some things that I ought to do and ought not to do. I feel the need of education. They all laugh at her, except the She-Ancient.
The She-Ancient | You will have grown out of that by tomorrow. Do what you please. She goes away up the hill path.
The officials take their paraphernalia and the fragments of the egg back into the temple.
Acis | Just fancy: that old girl has been going for seven hundred years and hasn’t had her fatal accident yet; and she is not a bit tired of it all.
The Newly Born | How could anyone ever get tired of life?
Acis | They do. That is, of the same life. They manage to change themselves in a wonderful way. You meet them sometimes with a lot of extra heads and arms and legs: they make you split laughing at them. Most of them have forgotten how to speak: the ones that attend to us have to brush up their knowledge of the language once a year or so. Nothing makes any difference to them that I can see. They never enjoy themselves. I don’t know how they can stand it. They don’t even come to our festivals of the arts. That old one who saw you out of your shell has gone off to moodle about doing nothing; though she knows that this is Festival Day?
The Newly Born | What is Festival Day?
Acis | Two of our greatest sculptors are bringing us their latest masterpieces; and we are going to crown them with flowers and sing dithyrambs to them and dance round them.
The Newly Born | How jolly! What is a sculptor?
Acis | Listen here, young one. You must find out things for yourself, and not ask questions. For the first day or two you must keep your eyes and ears open and your mouth shut. Children should be seen and not heard.
The Newly Born | Who are you calling a child? I am fully a quarter of an hour old. She sits down on the curved bench near Strephon with her maturest air.
Voices In The Temple | All expressing protest, disappointment, disgust. Oh! Oh! Scandalous. Shameful. Disgraceful. What filth! Is this a joke? Why, they’re ancients! Ss-s-s-sss! Are you mad, Arjillax? This is an outrage. An insult. Yah! etc. etc. etc. The malcontents appear on the steps, grumbling.
Acis | Hullo: what’s the matter? He goes to the steps of the temple.
The two sculptors issue from the temple. One has a beard two feet long: the other is beardless. Between them comes a handsome nymph with marked features, dark hair richly waved, and authoritative bearing.
The Authoritative Nymph | Swooping down to the centre of the glade with the sculptors, between Acis and the Newly Born. Do not try to browbeat me, Arjillax, merely because you are clever with your hands. Can you play the flute?
Arjillax | The bearded sculptor on her right. No, Ecrasia: I cannot. What has that to do with it? He is half derisive, half impatient, wholly resolved not to take her seriously in spite of her beauty and imposing tone.
Ecrasia | Well, have you ever hesitated to criticize our best flute players, and to declare whether their music is good or bad? Pray have I not the same right to criticize your busts, though I cannot make images anymore than you can play?
Arjillax | Any fool can play the flute, or play anything else, if he practises enough; but sculpture is a creative art, not a mere business of whistling into a pipe. The sculptor must have something of the god in him. From his hand comes a form which reflects a spirit. He does not make it to please you, nor even to please himself, but because he must. You must take what he gives you, or leave it if you are not worthy of it.
Ecrasia | Scornfully. Not worthy of it! Ho! May I not leave it because it is not worthy of me?
Arjillax | Of you! Hold your silly tongue, you conceited humbug. What do you know about it?
Ecrasia | I know what every person of culture knows: that the business of the artist is to create beauty. Until today your works have been full of beauty; and I have been the first to point that out.
Arjillax | Thank you for nothing. People have eyes, haven’t they, to see what is as plain as the sun in the heavens without your pointing it out?
Ecrasia | You were very glad to have it pointed out. You did not call me a conceited humbug then. You stifled me with caresses. You modelled me as the genius of art presiding over the infancy of your master here, indicating the other sculptor Martellus.
Martellus | A silent and meditative listener, shudders and shakes his head, but says nothing.
Arjillax | Quarrelsomely. I was taken in by your talk.
Ecrasia | I discovered your genius before anyone else did. Is that true, or is it not?
Arjillax | Everybody knew I was an extraordinary person. When I was born my beard was three feet long.
Ecrasia | Yes; and it has shrunk from three feet to two. Your genius seems to have been in the last foot of your beard; for you have lost both.
Martellus | With a short sardonic cachinnation. Ha! My beard was three and a half feet long when I was born; and a flash of lightning burnt it off and killed the ancient who was delivering me. Without a hair on my chin I became the greatest sculptor in ten generations.
Ecrasia | And yet you come to us today with empty hands. We shall actually have to crown Arjillax here because no other sculptor is exhibiting.
Acis | Returning from the temple steps to behind the curved seat on the right of the three. What’s the row, Ecrasia? Why have you fallen out with Arjillax?
Ecrasia | He has insulted us! outraged us! profaned his art! You know how much we hoped from the twelve busts he placed in the temple to be unveiled today. Well, go in and look at them. That is all I have to say. She sweeps to the curved seat, and sits down just where Acis is leaning over it.
Acis | I am no great judge of sculpture. Art is not my line. What is wrong with the busts?
Ecrasia | Wrong with them! Instead of being ideally beautiful nymphs and youths, they are horribly realistic studies of—but I really cannot bring my lips to utter it.
The Newly Born, full of curiosity, runs to the temple, and peeps in.
Acis | Oh, stow it, Ecrasia. Your lips are not so squeamish as all that. Studies of what?
The Newly Born | From the temple steps. Ancients.
Acis | Surprised but not scandalized. Ancients!
Ecrasia | Yes, ancients. The one subject that is by the universal consent of all connoisseurs absolutely excluded from the fine arts. To Arjillax. How can you defend such a proceeding?
Arjillax | If you come to that, what interest can you find in the statues of smirking nymphs and posturing youths you stick up all over the place?
Ecrasia | You did not ask that when your hand was still skilful enough to model them.
Arjillax | Skilful! You high-nosed idiot, I could turn such things out by the score with my eyes bandaged and one hand tied behind me. But what use would they be? They would bore me; and they would bore you if you had any sense. Go in and look at my busts. Look at them again and yet again until you receive the full impression of the intensity of mind that is stamped on them; and then go back to the pretty-pretty confectionery you call sculpture, and see whether you can endure its vapid emptiness. He mounts the altar impetuously. Listen to me, all of you; and do you, Ecrasia, be silent if you are capable of silence.
Ecrasia | Silence is the most perfect expression of scorn. Scorn! That is what I feel for your revolting busts.
Arjillax | Fool: the busts are only the beginning of a mighty design. Listen.
Acis | Go ahead, old sport. We are listening.
Martellus stretches himself on the sward beside the altar. The Newly Born sits on the temple steps with her chin on her hands, ready to devour the first oration she has ever heard. The rest sit or stand at ease.
Arjillax | In the records which generations of children have rescued from the stupid neglect of the ancients, there has come down to us a fable which, like many fables, is not a thing that was done in the past, but a thing that is to be done in the future. It is a legend of a supernatural being called the Archangel Michael.
The Newly Born | Is this a story? I want to hear a story. She runs down the steps and sits on the altar at Arjillax’s feet.
Arjillax | The Archangel Michael was a mighty sculptor and painter. He found in the centre of the world a temple erected to the goddess of the centre, called Mediterranea. This temple was full of silly pictures of pretty children, such as Ecrasia approves.
Acis | Fair play, Arjillax! If she is to keep silent, let her alone.
Ecrasia | I shall not interrupt, Acis. Why should I not prefer youth and beauty to age and ugliness?
Arjillax | Just so. Well, the Archangel Michael was of my opinion, not yours. He began by painting on the ceiling the newly born in all their childish beauty. But when he had done this he was not satisfied; for the temple was no more impressive than it had been before, except that there was a strength and promise of greater things about his newly born ones than any other artist had attained to. So he painted all round these newly born a company of ancients, who were in those days called prophets and sybils, whose majesty was that of the mind alone at its intensest. And this painting was acknowledged through ages and ages to be the summit and masterpiece of art. Of course we cannot believe such a tale literally. It is only a legend. We do not believe in archangels; and the notion that thirty thousand years ago sculpture and painting existed, and had even reached the glorious perfection they have reached with us, is absurd. But what men cannot realize they can at least aspire to. They please themselves by pretending that it was realized in a golden age of the past. This splendid legend endured because it lived as a desire in the hearts of the greatest artists. The temple of Mediterranea never was built in the past, nor did Michael the Archangel exist. But today the temple is here; He points to the porch. and the man is here. He slaps himself on the chest. I, Arjillax, am the man. I will place in your theatre such images of the newly born as must satisfy even Ecrasia’s appetite for beauty; and I will surround them with ancients more august than any who walk through our woods.
Martellus | As before. Ha!
Arjillax | Stung. Why do you laugh, you who have come empty-handed, and, it seems, empty-headed?
Ecrasia | Rising indignantly. Oh, shame! You dare disparage Martellus, twenty times your master.
Acis | Be quiet, will you. He seizes her shoulders and thrusts her back into her seat.
Martellus | Let him disparage his fill, Ecrasia. Sitting up. My poor Arjillax, I too had this dream. I too found one day that my images of loveliness had become vapid, uninteresting, tedious, a waste of time and material. I too lost my desire to model limbs, and retained only my interest in heads and faces. I, too, made busts of ancients; but I had not your courage: I made them in secret, and hid them from you all.
Arjillax | Jumping down from the altar behind Martellus in his surprise and excitement. You made busts of ancients! Where are they, man? Will you be talked out of your inspiration by Ecrasia and the fools who imagine she speaks with authority? Let us have them all set up beside mine in the theatre. I have opened the way for you; and you see I am none the worse.
Martellus | Impossible. They are all smashed. He rises, laughing.
All | Smashed!
Arjillax | Who smashed them?
Martellus | I did. That is why I laughed at you just now. You will smash yours before you have completed a dozen of them. He goes to the end of the altar and sits down beside the Newly Born.
Arjillax | But why?
Martellus | Because you cannot give them life. A live ancient is better than a dead statue. He takes the Newly Born on his knee: she is flattered and voluptuously responsive. Anything alive is better than anything that is only pretending to be alive. To Arjillax. Your disillusion with your works of beauty is only the beginning of your disillusion with images of all sorts. As your hand became more skilful and your chisel cut deeper, you strove to get nearer and nearer to truth and reality, discarding the fleeting fleshly lure, and making images of the mind that fascinates to the end. But how can so noble an inspiration be satisfied with any image, even an image of the truth? In the end the intellectual conscience that tore you away from the fleeting in art to the eternal must tear you away from art altogether, because art is false and life alone is true.
The Newly Born | Flings her arms round his neck and kisses him enthusiastically.
Martellus | Rises; carries her to the curved bench on his left; deposits her beside Strephon as if she were his overcoat; and continues without the least change of tone. Shape it as you will, marble remains marble, and the graven image an idol. As I have broken my idols, and cast away my chisel and modelling tools, so will you too break these busts of yours.
Arjillax | Never.
Martellus | Wait, my friend. I do not come empty-handed today, as you imagined. On the contrary, I bring with me such a work of art as you have never seen, and an artist who has surpassed both you and me further than we have surpassed all our competitors.
Ecrasia | Impossible. The greatest things in art can never be surpassed.
Arjillax | Who is this paragon whom you declare greater than I?
Martellus | I declare him greater than myself, Arjillax.
Arjillax | Frowning. I understand. Sooner than not drown me, you are willing to clasp me round the waist and jump overboard with me.
Acis | Oh, stop squabbling. That is the worst of you artists. You are always in little squabbling cliques; and the worst cliques are those which consist of one man. Who is this new fellow you are throwing in one another’s teeth?
Arjillax | Ask Martellus: do not ask me. I know nothing of him. He leaves Martellus, and sits down beside Ecrasia, on her left.
Martellus | You know him quite well. Pygmalion.
Ecrasia | Indignantly. Pygmalion! That soulless creature! A scientist! A laboratory person!
Arjillax | Pygmalion produce a work of art! You have lost your artistic senses. The man is utterly incapable of modelling a thumb nail, let alone a human figure.
Martellus | That does not matter: I have done the modelling for him.
Arjillax | What on earth do you mean?
Martellus | Calling. Pygmalion: come forth.
Pygmalion, a square-fingered youth with his face laid out in horizontal blocks, and a perpetual smile of eager benevolent interest in everything, and expectation of equal interest from everybody else, comes from the temple to the centre of the group, who regard him for the most part with dismay, as dreading that he will bore them. Ecrasia is openly contemptuous.
Martellus | Friends: it is unfortunate that Pygmalion is constitutionally incapable of exhibiting anything without first giving a lecture about it to explain it; but I promise you that if you will be patient he will show you the two most wonderful works of art in the world, and that they will contain some of my own very best workmanship. Let me add that they will inspire a loathing that will cure you of the lunacy of art forever. He sits down next the Newly Born, who pouts and turns a very cold right shoulder to him, a demonstration utterly lost on him.
Pygmalion, with the smile of a simpleton, and the eager confidence of a fanatical scientist, climbs awkwardly on to the altar. They prepare for the worst.
Pygmalion | My friends: I will omit the algebra—
Acis | Thank God!
Pygmalion | Continuing.—because Martellus has made me promise to do so. To come to the point, I have succeeded in making artificial human beings. Real live ones, I mean.
Incredulous Voices | Oh, come! Tell us another. Really, Pyg! Get out. You haven’t. What a lie!
Pygmalion | I tell you I have. I will show them to you. It has been done before. One of the very oldest documents we possess mentions a tradition of a biologist who extracted certain unspecified minerals from the earth and, as it quaintly expresses it, “breathed into their nostrils the breath of life.” This is the only tradition from the primitive ages which we can regard as really scientific. There are later documents which specify the minerals with great precision, even to their atomic weights; but they are utterly unscientific, because they overlook the element of life which makes all the difference between a mere mixture of salts and gases and a living organism. These mixtures were made over and over again in the crude laboratories of the Silly-Clever Ages; but nothing came of them until the ingredient which the old chronicler called the breath of life was added by this very remarkable early experimenter. In my view he was the founder of biological science.
Arjillax | Is that all we know about him? It doesn’t amount to very much, does it?
Pygmalion | There are some fragments of pictures and documents which represent him as walking in a garden and advising people to cultivate their gardens. His name has come down to us in several forms. One of them is Jove. Another is Voltaire.
Ecrasia | You are boring us to distraction with your Voltaire. What about your human beings?
Arjillax | Aye: come to them.
Pygmalion | I assure you that these details are intensely interesting. Cries of No! They are not! Come to the human beings! Conspuez Voltaire! Cut it short, Pyg! interrupt him from all sides. You will see their bearing presently. I promise you I will not detain you long. We know, we children of science, that the universe is full of forces and powers and energies of one kind and another. The sap rising in a tree, the stone holding together in a definite crystalline structure, the thought of a philosopher holding his brain in form and operation with an inconceivably powerful grip, the urge of evolution: all these forces can be used by us. For instance, I use the force of gravitation when I put a stone on my tunic to prevent it being blown away when I am bathing. By substituting appropriate machines for the stone we have made not only gravitation our slave, but also electricity and magnetism, atomic attraction, repulsion, polarization, and so forth. But hitherto the vital force has eluded us; so it has had to create machinery for itself. It has created and developed bony structures of the requisite strength, and clothed them with cellular tissue of such amazing sensitiveness that the organs it forms will adapt their action to all the normal variations in the air they breathe, the food they digest, and the circumstances about which they have to think. Yet, as these live bodies, as we call them, are only machines after all, it must be possible to construct them mechanically.
Arjillax | Everything is possible. Have you done it? that is the question.
Pygmalion | Yes. But that is a mere fact. What is interesting is the explanation of the fact. Forgive my saying so; but it is such a pity that you artists have no intellect.
Ecrasia | Sententiously. I do not admit that. The artist divines by inspiration all the truths that the so-called scientist grubs up in his laboratory slowly and stupidly long afterwards.
Arjillax | To Ecrasia, quarrelsomely. What do you know about it? You are not an artist.
Acis | Shut your heads, both of you. Let us have the artificial men. Trot them out, Pygmalion.
Pygmalion | It is a man and a woman. But I really must explain first.
All | Groaning. !!!
Pygmalion | Yes: I—
Acis | We want results, not explanations.
Pygmalion | Hurt. I see I am boring you. Not one of you takes the least interest in science. Goodbye. He descends from the altar and makes for the temple.
Several Youths And Maidens | Rising and rushing to him. No, no. Don’t go. Don’t be offended. We want to see the artificial pair. We will listen. We are tremendously interested. Tell us all about it.
Pygmalion | Relenting. I shall not detain you two minutes.
All | Half an hour if you like. Please go on, Pygmalion. They rush him back to the altar, and hoist him on to it. Up you go.
They return to their former places.
Pygmalion | As I told you, lots of attempts were made to produce protoplasm in the laboratory. Why were these synthetic plasms, as they called them, no use?
Ecrasia | We are waiting for you to tell us.
The Newly Born | Modelling herself on Ecrasia, and trying to outdo her intellectually. Clearly because they were dead.
Pygmalion | Not bad for a baby, my pet. But dead and alive are very loose terms. You are not half as much alive as you will be in another month or so. What was wrong with the synthetic protoplasm was that it could not fix and conduct the Life Force. It was like a wooden magnet or a lightning conductor made of silk: it would not take the current.
Acis | Nobody but a fool would make a wooden magnet, and expect it to attract anything.
Pygmalion | He might if he were so ignorant as not to be able to distinguish between wood and soft iron. In those days they were very ignorant of the differences between things, because their methods of analysis were crude. They mixed up messes that were so like protoplasm that they could not tell the difference. But the difference was there, though their analysis was too superficial and incomplete to detect it. You must remember that these poor devils were very little better than our idiots: we should never dream of letting one of them survive the day of its birth. Why, the Newly Born there already knows by instinct many things that their greatest physicists could hardly arrive at by forty years of strenuous study. Her simple direct sense of space-time and quantity unconsciously solves problems which cost their most famous mathematicians years of prolonged and laborious calculations requiring such intense mental application that they frequently forgot to breathe when engaged in them, and almost suffocated themselves in consequence.
Ecrasia | Leave these obscure prehistoric abortions; and come back to your synthetic man and woman.
Pygmalion | When I undertook the task of making synthetic men, I did not waste my time on protoplasm. It was evident to me that if it were possible to make protoplasm in the laboratory, it must be equally possible to begin higher up and make fully evolved muscular and nervous tissues, bone, and so forth. Why make the seed when the making of the flower would be no greater miracle? I tried thousands of combinations before I succeeded in producing anything that would fix high-potential Life Force.
Arjillax | High what?
Pygmalion | High-po-tential. The Life Force is not so simple as you think. A high-potential current of it will turn a bit of dead tissue into a philosopher’s brain. A low-potential current will reduce the same bit of tissue to a mass of corruption. Will you believe me when I tell you that, even in man himself, the Life Force used to slip suddenly down from its human level to that of a fungus, so that men found their flesh no longer growing as flesh, but proliferating horribly in a lower form which was called cancer, until the lower form of life killed the higher, and both perished together miserably?
Martellus | Keep off the primitive tribes, Pygmalion. They interest you; but they bore these young things.
Pygmalion | I am only trying to make you understand. There was the Life Force raging all round me: there was I, trying to make organs that would capture it as a battery captures electricity, and tissues that would conduct it and operate it. It was easy enough to make eyes more perfect than our own, and ears with a larger range of sound; but they could neither see nor hear, because they were not susceptible to the Life Force. But it was far worse when I discovered how to make them susceptible; for the first thing that happened was that they ceased to be eyes and ears and turned into heaps of maggots.
Ecrasia | Disgusting! Please stop.
Acis | If you don’t want to hear, go away. You go ahead, Pyg.
Pygmalion | I went ahead. You see, the lower potentials of the Life Force could make maggots, but not human eyes or ears. I improved the tissue until it was susceptible to a higher potential.
Arjillax | Intensely interested. Yes; and then?
Pygmalion | Then the eyes and ears turned into cancers.
Ecrasia | Oh, hideous!
Pygmalion | Not at all. That was a great advance. It encouraged me so much that I put aside the eyes and ears, and made a brain. It wouldn’t take the Life Force at all until I had altered its constitution a dozen times; but when it did, it took a much higher potential, and did not dissolve; and neither did the eyes and ears when I connected them up with the brain. I was able to make a sort of monster: a thing without arms or legs; and it really and truly lived for half-an-hour.
The Newly Born | Half-an-hour! What good was that? Why did it die?
Pygmalion | Its blood went wrong. But I got that right; and then I went ahead with a complete human body: arms and legs and all. He was my first man.
Arjillax | Who modelled him?
Pygmalion | I did.
Martellus | Do you mean to say you tried your own hand before you sent for me?
Pygmalion | Bless you, yes, several times. My first man was the ghastliest creature: a more dreadful mixture of horror and absurdity than you who have not seen him can conceive.
Arjillax | If you modelled him, he must indeed have been a spectacle.
Pygmalion | Oh, it was not his shape. You see I did not invent that. I took actual measurements and moulds from my own body. Sculptors do that sometimes, you know; though they pretend they don’t.
Martellus | Hm!
Arjillax | Hah!
Pygmalion | He was all right to look at, at first, or nearly so. But he behaved in the most appalling manner; and the subsequent developments were so disgusting that I really cannot describe them to you. He seized all sorts of things and swallowed them. He drank every fluid in the laboratory. I tried to explain to him that he must take nothing that he could not digest and assimilate completely; but of course he could not understand me. He assimilated a little of what he swallowed; but the process left horrible residues which he had no means of getting rid of. His blood turned to poison; and he perished in torments, howling. I then perceived that I had produced a prehistoric man; for there are certain traces in our own bodies of arrangements which enabled the earlier forms of mankind to renew their bodies by swallowing flesh and grains and vegetables and all sorts of unnatural and hideous foods, and getting rid of what they could not digest.
Ecrasia | But what a pity he died! What a glimpse of the past we have lost! He could have told us stories of the Golden Age.
Pygmalion | Not he. He was a most dangerous beast. He was afraid of me, and actually tried to kill me by snatching up things and striking at me with them. I had to give him two or three pretty severe shocks before I convinced him that he was at my mercy.
The Newly Born | Why did you not make a woman instead of a man? She would have known how to behave herself.
Martellus | Why did you not make a man and a woman? Their children would have been interesting.
Pygmalion | I intended to make a woman; but after my experience with the man it was out of the question.
Ecrasia | Pray why?
Pygmalion | Well, it is difficult to explain if you have not studied prehistoric methods of reproduction. You see the only sort of men and women I could make were men and women just like us as far as their bodies were concerned. That was how I killed the poor beast of a man. I hadn’t provided for his horrible prehistoric methods of feeding himself. Suppose the woman had reproduced in some prehistoric way instead of being oviparous as we are? She couldn’t have done it with a modern female body. Besides, the experiment might have been painful.
Ecrasia | Then you have nothing to show us at all?
Pygmalion | Oh yes I have. I am not so easily beaten as that. I set to work again for months to find out how to make a digestive system that would deal with waste products and a reproductive system capable of internal nourishment and incubation.
Ecrasia | Why did you not find out how to make them like us?
Strephon | Crying out in his grief for the first time. Why did you not make a woman whom you could love? That was the secret you needed.
The Newly Born | Oh yes. How true! How great of you, darling Strephon! She kisses him impulsively.
Strephon | Passionately. Let me alone.
Martellus | Control your reflexes, child.
The Newly Born | My what!
Martellus | Your reflexes. The things you do without thinking. Pygmalion is going to show you a pair of human creatures who are all reflexes and nothing else. Take warning by them.
The Newly Born | But won’t they be alive, like us?
Pygmalion | That is a very difficult question to answer, my dear. I confess I thought at first I had created living creatures; but Martellus declares they are only automata. But then Martellus is a mystic: I am a man of science. He draws a line between an automaton and a living organism. I cannot draw that line to my own satisfaction.
Martellus | Your artificial men have no self-control. They only respond to stimuli from without.
Pygmalion | But they are conscious. I have taught them to talk and read; and now they tell lies. That is so very lifelike.
Martellus | Not at all. If they were alive they would tell the truth. You can provoke them to tell any silly lie; and you can foresee exactly the sort of lie they will tell. Give them a clip below the knee, and they will jerk their foot forward. Give them a clip in their appetites or vanities or any of their lusts and greeds, and they will boast and lie, and affirm and deny, and hate and love without the slightest regard to the facts that are staring them in the face, or to their own obvious limitations. That proves that they are automata.
Pygmalion | Unconvinced. I know, dear old chap; but there really is some evidence that we are descended from creatures quite as limited and absurd as these. After all, the baby there is three-quarters an automaton. Look at the way she has been going on!
The Newly Born | Indignantly. What do you mean? How have I been going on?
Ecrasia | If they have no regard for truth, they can have no real vitality.
Pygmalion | Truth is sometimes so artificial: so relative, as we say in the scientific world, that it is very hard to feel quite sure that what is false and even ridiculous to us may not be true to them.
Ecrasia | I ask you again, why did you not make them like us? Would any true artist be content with less than the best?
Pygmalion | I couldn’t. I tried. I failed. I am convinced that what I am about to show you is the very highest living organism that can be produced in the laboratory. The best tissues we can manufacture will not take as high potentials as the natural product: that is where Nature beats us. You don’t seem to understand, any of you, what an enormous triumph it was to produce consciousness at all.
Acis | Cut the cackle; and come to the synthetic couple.
Several Youths And Maidens | Yes, yes. No more talking. Let us have them. Dry up, Pyg; and fetch them along. Come on: out with them! The synthetic couple.
Pygmalion | Waving his hands to appease them. Very well, very well. Will you please whistle for them? They respond to the stimulus of a whistle.
All who can, whistle like streetboys.
Ecrasia | Makes a wry face and puts her fingers in her ears. !
Pygmalion | Sh-sh-sh! That’s enough: that’s enough: that’s enough. Silence. Now let us have some music. A dance tune. Not too fast.
The flutists play a quiet dance.
Martellus | Prepare yourselves for something ghastly.
Two figures, a man and woman of noble appearance, beautifully modelled and splendidly attired, emerge hand in hand from the temple. Seeing that all eyes are fixed on them, they halt on the steps, smiling with gratified vanity. The woman is on the man’s left.
Pygmalion | Rubbing his hands with the purring satisfaction of a creator. This way, please.
The Figures advance condescendingly and pose themselves centrally between the curved seats.
Pygmalion | Now if you will be so good as to oblige us with a little something. You dance so beautifully, you know. He sits down next Martellus, and whispers to him. It is extraordinary how sensitive they are to the stimulus of flattery.
The Figures, with a gracious air, dance pompously, but very passably. At the close they bow to one another.
On All Hands | Clapping. Bravo! Thank you. Wonderful! Splendid. Perfect.
The Figures acknowledge the applause in an obvious condition of swelled head.
The Newly Born | Can they make love?
Pygmalion | Yes: they can respond to every stimulus. They have all the reflexes. Put your arm round the man’s neck, and he will put his arm round your body. He cannot help it.
The Female Figure | Frowning. Round mine, you mean.
Pygmalion | Yours, too, of course, if the stimulus comes from you.
Ecrasia | Cannot he do anything original?
Pygmalion | No. But then, you know, I do not admit that any of us can do anything really original, though Martellus thinks we can.
Acis | Can he answer a question?
Pygmalion | Oh yes. A question is a stimulus, you know. Ask him one.
Acis | To the Male Figure. What do you think of what you see around you? Of us, for instance, and our ways and doings?
The Male Figure | I have not seen the newspaper today.
The Female Figure | How can you expect my husband to know what to think of you if you give him his breakfast without his paper?
Martellus | You see. He is a mere automaton.
The Newly Born | I don’t think I should like him to put his arm round my neck. I don’t like them. The Male Figure looks offended, and the Female jealous. Oh, I thought they couldn’t understand. Have they feelings?
Pygmalion | Of course they have. I tell you they have all the reflexes.
The Newly Born | But feelings are not reflexes.
Pygmalion | They are sensations. When the rays of light enter their eyes and make a picture on their retinas, their brains become conscious of the picture and they act accordingly. When the waves of sound started by your speaking enter their ears and record a disparaging remark on their keyboards, their brains become conscious of the disparagement and resent it accordingly. If you did not disparage them they would not resent it. They are merely responding to a stimulus.
The Male Figure |

We are part of a cosmic system. Free will is an illusion. We are the children of Cause and Effect. We are the Unalterable, the Irresistible, the Irresponsible, the Inevitable.

My name is Ozymandias, king of kings:
Look on my works, ye mighty, and despair.

There is a general stir of curiosity at this.

Acis | What the dickens does he mean?
The Male Figure | Silence, base accident of Nature. This taking the hand of the Female Figure and introducing her is Cleopatra-Semiramis, consort of the king of kings, and therefore queen of queens. Ye are things hatched from eggs by the brainless sun and the blind fire; but the king of kings and queen of queens are not accidents of the egg: they are thought-out and handmade to receive the sacred Life Force. There is one person of the king and one of the queen; but the Life Force of the king and queen is all one: the glory equal, the majesty coeternal. Such as the king is so is the queen, the king thought-out and handmade, the queen thought-out and handmade. The actions of the king are caused, and therefore determined, from the beginning of the world to the end; and the actions of the queen are likewise. The king logical and predetermined and inevitable, and the queen logical and predetermined and inevitable. And yet they are not two logical and predetermined and inevitable, but one logical and predetermined and inevitable. Therefore confound not the persons, nor divide the substance: but worship us twain as one throne, two in one and one in two, lest by error ye fall into irretrievable damnation.
The Female Figure | And if any say unto you “Which one?” remember that though there is one person of the king and one of the queen, yet these two persons are not alike, but are woman and man, and that as woman was created after man, the skill and practice gained in making him were added to her, wherefore she is to be exalted above him in all personal respects, and—
The Male Figure | Peace, woman; for this is a damnable heresy. Both Man and Woman are what they are and must do what they must according to the eternal laws of Cause and Effect. Look to your words; for if they enter my ear and jar too repugnantly on my sensorium, who knows that the inevitable response to that stimulus may not be a message to my muscles to snatch up some heavy object and break you in pieces.
The Female Figure picks up a stone and is about to throw it at her consort.
Arjillax | Springing up and shouting to Pygmalion, who is fondly watching the Male Figure. Look out, Pygmalion! Look at the woman!
Pygmalion, seeing what is happening, hurls himself on the Female Figure and wrenches the stone out of her hand. All spring up in consternation.
Arjillax | She meant to kill him.
Strephon | This is horrible.
The Female Figure | Wrestling with Pygmalion. Let me go. Let me go, will you. She bites his hand.
Pygmalion | Releasing her and staggering. Oh!
A general shriek of horror echoes his exclamation. He turns deadly pale, and supports himself against the end of the curved seat.
The Female Figure | To her consort. You would stand there and let me be treated like this, you unmanly coward.
Pygmalion falls dead.
The Newly Born | Oh! What’s the matter? Why did he fall! What has happened to him?
They look on anxiously as Martellus kneels down and examines the body of Pygmalion.
Martellus | She has bitten a piece out of his hand nearly as large as a finger nail: enough to kill ten men. There is no pulse, no breath.
Ecrasia | But his thumb is clinched.
Martellus | No: it has just straightened out. See! He has gone. Poor Pygmalion!
The Newly Born | Oh! She weeps.
Strephon | Hush, dear: that’s childish.
The Newly Born | Subsiding with a sniff. !!
Martellus | Rising. Dead in his third year. What a loss to Science!
Arjillax | Who cares about Science? Serve him right for making that pair of horrors!
The Male Figure | Glaring. Ha!
The Female Figure | Keep a civil tongue in your head, you.
The Newly Born | Oh, do not be so unkind, Arjillax. You will make water come out of my eyes again.
Martellus | Contemplating the Figures. Just look at these two devils. I modelled them out of the stuff Pygmalion made for them. They are masterpieces of art. And see what they have done! Does that convince you of the value of art, Arjillax!
Strephon | They look dangerous. Keep away from them.
Ecrasia | No need to tell us that, Strephon. Pf! They poison the air.
The Male Figure | Beware, woman. The wrath of Ozymandias strikes like the lightning.
The Female Figure | You just say that again if you dare, you filthy creature.
Acis | What are you going to do with them, Martellus? You are responsible for them, now that Pygmalion has gone.
Martellus | If they were marble it would be simple enough: I could smash them. As it is, how am I to kill them without making a horrible mess?
The Male Figure |

Posing heroically. Ha! He declaims:

Come one: come all: this rock shall fly
From its firm base as soon as I.

The Female Figure | Fondly. My man! My hero husband! I am proud of you. I love you.
Martellus | We must send out a message for an ancient.
Acis | Need we bother an ancient about such a trifle? It will take less than half a second to reduce our poor Pygmalion to a pinch of dust. Why not calcine the two along with him?
Martellus | No: the two automata are trifles; but the use of our powers of destruction is never a trifle. I had rather have the case judged.
The He-Ancient emerges from the grove. The Figures are panic-stricken.
The He-Ancient | Mildly. Am I wanted? I feel called. Seeing the body of Pygmalion, and immediately taking a sterner tone. What! A child lost! A life wasted! How has this happened?
The Female Figure | Frantically. I didn’t do it. It was not me. May I be struck dead if I touched him! It was he. Pointing to the Male Figure.
All | Amazed at the lie. Oh!
The Male Figure | Liar. You bit him. Everyone here saw you do it.
The He-Ancient | Silence. Going between the Figures. Who made these two loathsome dolls?
The Male Figure | Trying to assert himself with his knees knocking. My name is Ozymandias, king of—
The He-Ancient | With a contemptuous gesture. Pooh!
The Male Figure | Falling on his knees. Oh don’t, sir. Don’t. She did it, sir: indeed she did.
The Female Figure | Howling lamentably. Boohoo! oo! ooh!
The He-Ancient | Silence, I say.
He knocks the Male Automaton upright by a very light flip under the chin. The Female Automaton hardly dares to sob. The immortals contemplate them with shame and loathing. The She-Ancient comes from the trees opposite the temple.
The She-Ancient | Somebody wants me. What is the matter? She comes to the left hand of the Female Figure, not seeing the body of Pygmalion. Pf! Severely. You have been making dolls. You must not: they are not only disgusting: they are dangerous.
The Female Figure | Snivelling piteously. I’m not a doll, mam. I’m only poor Cleopatra-Semiramis, queen of queens. Covering her face with her hands. Oh, don’t look at me like that, mam. I meant no harm. He hurt me: indeed he did.
The He-Ancient | The creature has killed that poor youth.
The She-Ancient | Seeing the body of Pygmalion. What! This clever child, who promised so well!
The Female Figure | He made me. I had as much right to kill him as he had to make me. And how was I to know that a little thing like that would kill him? I shouldn’t die if he cut off my arm or leg.
Ecrasia | What nonsense!
Martellus | It may not be nonsense. I daresay if you cut off her leg she would grow another, like the lobsters and the little lizards.
The He-Ancient | Did this dead boy make these two things?
Martellus | He made them in his laboratory. I moulded their limbs. I am sorry. I was thoughtless: I did not foresee that they would kill and pretend to be persons they were not, and declare things that were false, and wish evil. I thought they would be merely mechanical fools.
The Male Figure | Do you blame us for our human nature?
The Female Figure | We are flesh and blood and not angels.
The Male Figure | Have you no hearts?
Arjillax | They are mad as well as mischievous. May we not destroy them?
Strephon | We abhor them.
The Newly Born | We loathe them.
Ecrasia | They are noisome.
Acis | I don’t want to be hard on the poor devils; but they are making me feel uneasy in my inside. I never had such a sensation before.
Martellus | I took a lot of trouble with them. But as far as I am concerned, destroy them by all means. I loathed them from the beginning.
All | Yes, yes: we all loathe them. Let us calcine them.
The Female Figure | Oh, don’t be so cruel. I’m not fit to die. I will never bite anyone again. I will tell the truth. I will do good. Is it my fault if I was not made properly? Kill him; but spare me.
The Male Figure | No! I have done no harm: she has. Kill her if you like: you have no right to kill me.
The Newly Born | Do you hear that? They want to have one another killed.
Arjillax | Monstrous! Kill them both.
The He-Ancient | Silence. These things are mere automata: they cannot help shrinking from death at any cost. You see that they have no self-control, and are merely shuddering through a series of reflexes. Let us see whether we cannot put a little more life into them. He takes the Male Figure by the hand, and places his disengaged hand on its head. Now listen. One of you two is to be destroyed. Which of you shall it be?
The Male Figure | After a slight convulsion during which his eyes are fixed on the He-Ancient. Spare her; and kill me.
Strephon | That’s better.
The Newly Born | Much better.
The She-Ancient | Handling the Female Automaton in the same manner. Which of you shall we kill?
The Female Figure | Kill us both. How could either of us live without the other?
Ecrasia | The woman is more sensible than the man.
The Ancients release the Automata.
The Male Figure | Sinking to the ground. I am discouraged. Life is too heavy a burden.
The Female Figure | Collapsing. I am dying. I am glad. I am afraid to live.
The Newly Born | I think it would be nice to give the poor things a little music.
Arjillax | Why?
The Newly Born | I don’t know. But it would.
The Musicians play.
The Female Figure | Ozymandias: do you hear that? She rises on her knees and looks raptly into space. Queen of queens! She dies.
The Male Figure | Crawling feebly towards her until he reaches her hand. I knew I was really a king of kings. To the others. Illusions, farewell: we are going to our thrones. He dies.
The music stops. There is dead silence for a moment.
The Newly Born | That was funny.
Strephon | It was. Even the Ancients are smiling.
The Newly Born | Just a little.
The She-Ancient | Quickly recovering her grave and peremptory manner. Take these two abominations away to Pygmalion’s laboratory, and destroy them with the rest of the laboratory refuse. Some of them move to obey. Take care: do not touch their flesh: it is noxious: lift them by their robes. Carry Pygmalion into the temple; and dispose of his remains in the usual way.
The three bodies are carried out as directed, Pygmalion into the temple by his bare arms and legs, and the two Figures through the grove by their clothes. Martellus superintends the removal of the Figures, Acis that of Pygmalion. Ecrasia, Arjillax, Strephon, and the Newly Born sit down as before, but on contrary benches; so that Strephon and the Newly Born now face the grove, and Ecrasia and Arjillax the temple. The Ancients remain standing at the altar.
Ecrasia | As she sits down. Oh for a breeze from the hills!
Strephon | Or the wind from the sea at the turn of the tide!
The Newly Born | I want some clean air.
The He-Ancient | The air will be clean in a moment. This doll flesh that children make decomposes quickly at best; but when it is shaken by such passions as the creatures are capable of, it breaks up at once and becomes horribly tainted.
The She-Ancient | Let it be a lesson to you all to be content with lifeless toys, and not attempt to make living ones. What would you think of us ancients if we made toys of you children?
The Newly Born | Coaxingly. Why do you not make toys of us? Then you would play with us; and that would be very nice.
The She-Ancient | It would not amuse us. When you play with one another you play with your bodies, and that makes you supple and strong; but if we played with you we should play with your minds, and perhaps deform them.
Strephon | You are a ghastly lot, you ancients. I shall kill myself when I am four years old. What do you live for?
The He-Ancient | You will find out when you grow up. You will not kill yourself.
Strephon | If you make me believe that, I shall kill myself now.
The Newly Born | Oh no. I want you. I love you.
Strephon | I love someone else. And she has gone old, old. Lost to me forever.
The He-Ancient | How old?
Strephon | You saw her when you barged into us as we were dancing. She is four.
The Newly Born | How I should have hated her twenty minutes ago! But I have grown out of that now.
The He-Ancient | Good. That hatred is called jealousy, the worst of our childish complaints.
Martellus, dusting his hands and puffing, returns from the grove.
Martellus | Ouf! He sits down next the Newly Born. That job’s finished.
Arjillax | Ancients: I should like to make a few studies of you. Not portraits, of course: I shall idealize you a little. I have come to the conclusion that you ancients are the most interesting subjects after all.
Martellus | What! Have those two horrors, whose ashes I have just deposited with peculiar pleasure in poor Pygmalion’s dustbin, not cured you of this silly image-making!
Arjillax | Why did you model them as young things, you fool? If Pygmalion had come to me, I should have made ancients of them for him. Not that I should have modelled them any better. I have always said that no one can beat you at your best as far as handwork is concerned. But this job required brains. That is where I should have come in.
Martellus | Well, my brainy boy, you are welcome to try your hand. There are two of Pygmalion’s pupils at the laboratory who helped him to manufacture the bones and tissues and all the rest of it. They can turn out a couple of new automatons; and you can model them as ancients if this venerable pair will sit for you.
Ecrasia | Decisively. No. No more automata. They are too disgusting.
Acis | Returning from the temple. Well, that’s done. Poor old Pyg!
Ecrasia | Only fancy, Acis! Arjillax wants to make more of those abominable things, and to destroy even their artistic character by making ancients of them.
The Newly Born | You won’t sit for them, will you? Please don’t.
The He-Ancient | Children, listen.
Acis | Striding down the steps to the bench and seating himself next Ecrasia. What! Even the Ancient wants to make a speech! Give it mouth, O Sage.
Strephon | For heaven’s sake don’t tell us that the earth was once inhabited by Ozymandiases and Cleopatras. Life is hard enough for us as it is.
The He-Ancient | Life is not meant to be easy, my child; but take courage: it can be delightful. What I wanted to tell you is that ever since men existed, children have played with dolls.
Ecrasia | You keep using that word. What are dolls, pray?
The She-Ancient | What you call works of art. Images. We call them dolls.
Arjillax | Just so. You have no sense of art; and you instinctively insult it.
The He-Ancient | Children have been known to make dolls out of rags, and to caress them with the deepest fondness.
The She-Ancient | Eight centuries ago, when I was a child, I made a rag doll. The rag doll is the dearest of all.
The Newly Born | Eagerly interested. Oh! Have you got it still?
The She-Ancient | I kept it a full week.
Ecrasia | Even in your childhood, then, you did not understand high art, and adored your own amateur crudities.
The She-Ancient | How old are you?
Ecrasia | Eight months.
The She-Ancient | When you have lived as long as I have—
Ecrasia | Interrupting rudely. I shall worship rag dolls, perhaps. Thank heaven I am still in my prime.
The He-Ancient | You are still capable of thanking, though you do not know what you thank. You are a thanking little animal, a blaming little animal, a—
Acis | A gushing little animal.
Arjillax | And, as she thinks, an artistic little animal.
Ecrasia | Nettled. I am an animated being with a reasonable soul and human flesh subsisting. If your Automata had been properly animated, Martellus, they would have been more successful.
The She-Ancient | That is where you are wrong, my child. If those two loathsome things had been rag dolls, they would have been amusing and lovable. The Newly Born here would have played with them; and you would all have laughed and played with them too until you had torn them to pieces; and then you would have laughed more than ever.
The Newly Born | Of course we should. Isn’t that funny?
The He-Ancient | When a thing is funny, search it for a hidden truth.
Strephon | Yes; and take all the fun out of it.
The She-Ancient | Do not be so embittered because your sweetheart has outgrown her love for you. The Newly Born will make amends.
The Newly Born | Oh yes: I will be more than she could ever have been.
Strephon | Psha! Jealous!
The Newly Born | Oh no. I have grown out of that. I love her now because she loved you, and because you love her.
The He-Ancient | That is the next stage. You are getting on very nicely, my child.
Martellus | Come! what is the truth that was hidden in the rag doll?
The He-Ancient | Well, consider why you are not content with the rag doll, and must have something more closely resembling a real living creature. As you grow up you make images and paint pictures. Those of you who cannot do that make stories about imaginary dolls. Or you dress yourselves up as dolls and act plays about them.
The She-Ancient | And, to deceive yourself the more completely, you take them so very very seriously that Ecrasia here declares that the making of dolls is the holiest work of creation, and the words you put into the mouths of dolls the sacredest of scriptures and the noblest of utterances.
Ecrasia | Tush!
Arjillax | Tosh!
The She-Ancient | Yet the more beautiful they become the further they retreat from you. You cannot caress them as you caress the rag doll. You cannot cry for them when they are broken or lost, or when you pretend they have been unkind to you, as you could when you played with rag dolls.
The He-Ancient | At last, like Pygmalion, you demand from your dolls the final perfection of resemblance to life. They must move and speak.
The She-Ancient | They must love and hate.
The He-Ancient | They must think that they think.
The She-Ancient | They must have soft flesh and warm, blood.
The He-Ancient | And then, when you have achieved this as Pygmalion did; when the marble masterpiece is dethroned by the automaton and the homo by the homunculus; when the body and the brain, the reasonable soul and human flesh subsisting, as Ecrasia says, stand before you unmasked as mere machinery, and your impulses are shown to be nothing but reflexes, you are filled with horror and loathing, and would give worlds to be young enough to play with your rag doll again, since every step away from it has been a step away from love and happiness. Is it not true?
The She-Ancient | Speak, Martellus: you who have travelled the whole path.
Martellus | It is true. With fierce joy I turned a temperature of a million degrees on those two things I had modelled, and saw them vanish in an instant into inoffensive dust.
The She-Ancient | Speak, Arjillax: you who have advanced from imitating the lightly living child to the intensely living ancient. Is it true, so far?
Arjillax | It is partly true: I cannot pretend to be satisfied now with modelling pretty children.
The He-Ancient | And you, Ecrasia: you cling to your highly artistic dolls as the noblest projections of the Life Force, do you not?
Ecrasia | Without art, the crudeness of reality would make the world unbearable.
The Newly Born | Anticipating the She-Ancient, who is evidently going to challenge her. Now you are coming to me, because I am the latest arrival. But I don’t understand your art and your dolls at all. I want to caress my darling Strephon, not to play with dolls.
Acis | I am in my fourth year; and I have got on very well without your dolls. I had rather walk up a mountain and down again than look at all the statues Martellus and Arjillax ever made. You prefer a statue to an automaton, and a rag doll to a statue. So do I; but I prefer a man to a rag doll. Give me friends, not dolls.
The He-Ancient | Yet I have seen you walking over the mountains alone. Have you not found your best friend in yourself?
Acis | What are you driving at, old one? What does all this lead to?
The He-Ancient | It leads, young man, to the truth that you can create nothing but yourself.
Acis | Musing. I can create nothing but myself. Ecrasia: you are clever. Do you understand it? I don’t.
Ecrasia | It is as easy to understand as any other ignorant error. What artist is as great as his own works? He can create masterpieces; but he cannot improve the shape of his own nose.
Acis | There! What have you to say to that, old one?
The He-Ancient | He can alter the shape of his own soul. He could alter the shape of his nose if the difference between a turned-up nose and a turned-down one were worth the effort. One does not face the throes of creation for trifles.
Acis | What have you to say to that, Ecrasia?
Ecrasia | I say that if the ancients had thoroughly grasped the theory of fine art they would understand that the difference between a beautiful nose and an ugly one is of supreme importance: that it is indeed the only thing that matters.
The She-Ancient | That is, they would understand something they could not believe, and that you do not believe.
Acis | Just so, mam. Art is not honest: that is why I never could stand much of it. It is all make-believe. Ecrasia never really says things: she only rattles her teeth in her mouth.
Ecrasia | Acis: you are rude.
Acis | You mean that I won’t play the game of make-believe. Well, I don’t ask you to play it with me; so why should you expect me to play it with you?
Ecrasia | You have no right to say that I am not sincere. I have found a happiness in art that real life has never given me. I am intensely in earnest about art. There is a magic and mystery in art that you know nothing of.
The She-Ancient | Yes, child: art is the magic mirror you make to reflect your invisible dreams in visible pictures. You use a glass mirror to see your face: you use works of art to see your soul. But we who are older use neither glass mirrors nor works of art. We have a direct sense of life. When you gain that you will put aside your mirrors and statues, your toys and your dolls.
The He-Ancient | Yet we too have our toys and our dolls. That is the trouble of the ancients.
Arjillax | What! The ancients have their troubles! It is the first time I ever heard one of them confess it.
The He-Ancient | Look at us. Look at me. This is my body, my blood, my brain; but it is not me. I am the eternal life, the perpetual resurrection; but striking his body this structure, this organism, this makeshift, can be made by a boy in a laboratory, and is held back from dissolution only by my use of it. Worse still, it can be broken by a slip of the foot, drowned by a cramp in the stomach, destroyed by a flash from the clouds. Sooner or later, its destruction is certain.
The She-Ancient | Yes: this body is the last doll to be discarded. When I was a child, Ecrasia, I, too, was an artist, like your sculptor friends there, striving to create perfection in things outside myself. I made statues: I painted pictures: I tried to worship them.
The He-Ancient | I had no such skill; but I, like Acis, sought perfection in friends, in lovers, in nature, in things outside myself. Alas! I could not create if. I could only imagine it.
The She-Ancient | I, like Arjillax, found out that my statues of bodily beauty were no longer even beautiful to me; and I pressed on and made statues and pictures of men and women of genius, like those in the old fable of Michelangelo. Like Martellus, I smashed them when I saw that there was no life in them: that they were so dead that they would not even dissolve as a dead body does.
The He-Ancient | And I, like Acis, ceased to walk over the mountains with my friends, and walked alone; for I found that I had creative power over myself but none over my friends. And then I ceased to walk on the mountains; for I saw that the mountains were dead.
Acis | Protesting vehemently. No. I grant you about the friends perhaps; but the mountains are still the mountains, each with its name, its individuality, its upstanding strength and majesty, its beauty—
Ecrasia | What! Acis among the rhapsodists!
The He-Ancient | Mere metaphor, my poor boy: the mountains are corpses.
All The Young | Repelled. Oh!
The He-Ancient | Yes. In the hardpressed heart of the earth, where the inconceivable heat of the sun still glows, the stone lives in fierce atomic convulsion, as we live in our slower way. When it is cast out to the surface it dies like deep-sea fish: what you see is only its cold dead body. We have tapped that central heat as prehistoric man tapped water springs; but nothing has come up alive from those flaming depths: your landscapes, your mountains, are only the world’s cast skins and decaying teeth on which we live like microbes.
Ecrasia | Ancient: you blaspheme against Nature and against Man.
The She-Ancient | Child, child, how much enthusiasm will you have for man when you have endured eight centuries of him, as I have, and seen him perish by an empty mischance that is yet a certainty? When I discarded my dolls as he discarded his friends and his mountains, it was to myself I turned as to the final reality. Here, and here alone, I could shape and create. When my arm was weak and I willed it to be strong, I could create a roll of muscle on it; and when I understood that, I understood that I could without any greater miracle give myself ten arms and three heads.
The He-Ancient | I also came to understand such miracles. For fifty years I sat contemplating this power in myself and concentrating my will.
The She-Ancient | So did I; and for five more years I made myself into all sorts of fantastic monsters. I walked upon a dozen legs: I worked with twenty hands and a hundred fingers: I looked to the four quarters of the compass with eight eyes out of four heads. Children fled in amazement from me until I had to hide myself from them; and the ancients, who had forgotten how to laugh, smiled grimly when they passed.
The He-Ancient | We have all committed these follies. You will all commit them.
The Newly Born | Oh, do grow a lot of arms and legs and heads for us. It would be so funny.
The He-Ancient | My child: I am just as well as I am. I would not lift my finger now to have a thousand heads.
The She-Ancient | But what would I not give to have no head at all?
All The Young | What’s that? No head at all? Why? How?
The He-Ancient | Can you not understand?
All The Young | Shaking their heads. No.
The She-Ancient | One day, when I was tired of learning to walk forward with some of my feet and backwards with others and sideways with the rest all at once, I sat on a rock with my four chins resting on four of my palms, and four or my elbows resting on four of my knees. And suddenly it came into my mind that this monstrous machinery of heads and limbs was no more me than my statues had been me, and that it was only an automaton that I had enslaved.
Martellus | Enslaved? What does that mean?
The She-Ancient | A thing that must do what you command it is a slave; and its commander is its master. These are words you will learn when your turn comes.
The He-Ancient | You will also learn that when the master has come to do everything through the slave, the slave becomes his master, since he cannot live without him.
The She-Ancient | And so I perceived that I had made myself the slave of a slave.
The He-Ancient | When we discovered that, we shed our superfluous heads and legs and arms until we had our old shapes again, and no longer startled the children.
The She-Ancient | But still I am the slave of this slave, my body. How am I to be delivered from it?
The He-Ancient | That, children, is the trouble of the ancients. For whilst we are tied to this tyrannous body we are subject to its death, and our destiny is not achieved.
The Newly Born | What is your destiny?
The He-Ancient | To be immortal.
The She-Ancient | The day will come when there will be no people, only thought.
The He-Ancient | And that will be life eternal.
Ecrasia | I trust I shall meet my fatal accident before that day dawns.
Arjillax | For once, Ecrasia, I agree with you. A world in which there were nothing plastic would be an utterly miserable one.
Ecrasia | No limbs, no contours, no exquisite lines and elegant shapes, no worship of beautiful bodies, no poetic embraces in which cultivated lovers pretend that their caressing hands are wandering over celestial hills and enchanted valleys, no—
Acis | Interrupting her disgustedly. What an inhuman mind you have, Ecrasia!
Ecrasia | Inhuman!
Acis | Yes: inhuman. Why don’t you fall in love with someone?
Ecrasia | I! I have been in love all my life. I burned with it even in the egg.
Acis | Not a bit of it. You and Arjillax are just as hard as two stones.
Ecrasia | You did not always think so, Acis.
Acis | Oh, I know. I offered you my love once, and asked for yours.
Ecrasia | And did I deny it to you, Acis?
Acis | You didn’t even know what love was.
Ecrasia | Oh! I adored you, you stupid oaf, until I found that you were a mere animal.
Acis | And I made no end of a fool of myself about you until I discovered that you were a mere artist. You appreciated my contours! I was plastic, as Arjillax says. I wasn’t a man to you: I was a masterpiece appealing to your tastes and your senses. Your tastes and senses had overlaid the direct impulse of life in you. And because I cared only for our life, and went straight to it, and was bored by your calling my limbs fancy names and mapping me into mountains and valleys and all the rest of it, you called me an animal. Well, I am an animal, if you call a live man an animal.
Ecrasia | You need not explain. You refused to be refined. I did my best to lift your prehistoric impulses on to the plane of beauty, of imagination, of romance, of poetry, of art, of—
Acis | These things are all very well in their way and in their proper places. But they are not love. They are an unnatural adulteration of love. Love is a simple thing and a deep thing: it is an act of life and not an illusion. Art is an illusion.
Arjillax | That is false. The statue comes to life always. The statues of today are the men and women of the next incubation. I hold up the marble figure before the mother and say, “This is the model you must copy.” We produce what we see. Let no man dare to create in art a thing that he would not have exist in life.
Martellus | Yes: I have been through all that. But you yourself are making statues of ancients instead of beautiful nymphs and swains. And Ecrasia is right about the ancients being inartistic. They are damnably inartistic.
Ecrasia | Triumphant. Ah! Our greatest artist vindicates me. Thanks, Martellus.
Martellus | The body always ends by being a bore. Nothing remains beautiful and interesting except thought, because the thought is the life. Which is just what this old gentleman and this old lady seem to think too.
The She-Ancient | Quite so.
The He-Ancient | Precisely.
The Newly Born | To the He-Ancient. But you can’t be nothing. What do you want to be?
The He-Ancient | A vortex.
The Newly Born | A what?
The She-Ancient | A vortex. I began as a vortex: why should I not end as one?
Ecrasia | Oh! That is what you old people are, Vorticists.
Acis | But if life is thought, can you live without a head?
The He-Ancient | Not now perhaps. But prehistoric men thought they could not live without tails. I can live without a tail. Why should I not live without a head?
The Newly Born | What is a tail?
The He-Ancient | A habit of which your ancestors managed to pure themselves.
The She-Ancient | None of us now believe that all this machinery of flesh and blood is necessary. It dies.
The He-Ancient | It imprisons us on this petty planet and forbids us to range through the stars.
Acis | But even a vortex is a vortex in something. You can’t have a whirlpool without water; and you can’t have a vortex without gas, or molecules or atoms or ions or electrons or something, not nothing.
The He-Ancient | No: the vortex is not the water nor the gas nor the atoms: it is a power over these things.
The She-Ancient | The body was the slave of the vortex; but the slave has become the master; and we must free ourselves from that tyranny. It is this stuff, indicating her body this flesh and blood and bone and all the rest of it, that is intolerable. Even prehistoric man dreamed of what he called an astral body, and asked who would deliver him from the body of this death.
Acis | Evidently out of his depth. I shouldn’t think too much about it if I were you. You have to keep sane, you know.
The two Ancients look at one another; shrug their shoulders; and address themselves to their departure.
The He-Ancient | We are staying too long with you, children. We must go.
All the young people rise rather eagerly.
Arjillax | Don’t mention it.
The She-Ancient | It is tiresome for us, too. You see, children, we have to put things very crudely to you to make ourselves intelligible.
The He-Ancient | And I am afraid we do not quite succeed.
Strephon | Very kind of you to come at all and talk to us, I’m sure.
Ecrasia | Why do the other ancients never come and give us a turn?
The She-Ancient | It is difficult for them. They have forgotten how to speak; how to read; even how to think in your fashion. We do not communicate with one another in that way or apprehend the world as you do.
The He-Ancient | I find it more and more difficult to keep up your language. Another century or two and it will be impossible. I shall have to be relieved by a younger shepherd.
Acis | Of course we are always delighted to see you; but still, if it tries you very severely, we could manage pretty well by ourselves, you know.
The She-Ancient | Tell me, Acis: do you ever think of yourself as having to live perhaps for thousands of years?
Acis | Oh, don’t talk about it. Why, I know very well that I have only four years of what any reasonable person would call living; and three and a half of them are already gone.
Ecrasia | You must not mind our saying so; but really you cannot call being an ancient living.
The Newly Born | Almost in tears. Oh, this dreadful shortness of our lives! I cannot bear it.
Strephon | I made up my mind on that subject long ago. When I am three years and fifty weeks old, I shall have my fatal accident. And it will not be an accident.
The He-Ancient | We are very tired of this subject. I must leave you.
The Newly Born | What is being tired?
The She-Ancient | The penalty of attending to children. Farewell.
The two Ancients go away severally, she into the grove, he up to the hills behind the temple.
All | Ouf! A great sigh of relief.
Ecrasia | Dreadful people!
Strephon | Bores!
Martellus | Yet one would like to follow them; to enter into their life; to grasp their thought; to comprehend the universe as they must.
Arjillax | Getting old, Martellus?
Martellus | Well, I have finished with the dolls; and I am no longer jealous of you. That looks like the end. Two hours sleep is enough for me. I am afraid I am beginning to find you all rather silly.
Strephon | I know. My girl went off this morning. She hadn’t slept for weeks. And she found mathematics more interesting than me.
Martellus | There is a prehistoric saying that has come down to us from a famous woman teacher. She said: “Leave women; and study mathematics.” It is the only remaining fragment of a lost scripture called The Confessions of St. Augustin, the English Opium Eater. That primitive savage must have been a great woman, to say a thing that still lives after three hundred centuries. I too will leave women and study mathematics, which I have neglected too long. Farewell, children, my old playmates. I almost wish I could feel sentimental about parting from you; but the cold truth is that you bore me. Do not be angry with me: your turn will come. He passes away gravely into the grove.
Arjillax | There goes a great spirit. What a sculptor he was! And now, nothing! It is as if he had cut off his hands.
The Newly Born | Oh, will you all leave me as he has left you?
Ecrasia | Never. We have sworn it.
Strephon | What is the use of swearing? She swore. He swore. You have sworn. They have sworn.
Ecrasia | You speak like a grammar.
Strephon | That is how one ought to speak, isn’t it? We shall all be forsworn.
The Newly Born | Do not talk like that. You are saddening us; and you are chasing the light away. It is growing dark.
Acis | Night is falling. The light will come back tomorrow.
The Newly Born | What is tomorrow?
Acis | The day that never comes. He turns towards the temple.
All begin trooping into the temple.
The Newly Born | Holding Acis back. That is no answer. What—
Arjillax | Silence. Little children should be seen and not heard.
The Newly Born | Putting out her tongue at him. !
Ecrasia | Ungraceful. You must not do that.
The Newly Born | I will do what I like. But there is something the matter with me. I want to lie down. I cannot keep my eyes open.
Ecrasia | You are falling asleep. You will wake up again.
The Newly Born | Drowsily. What is sleep?
Acis | Ask no questions; and you will be told no lies. He takes her by the ear, and leads her firmly towards the temple.
The Newly Born | Ai! oi! ai! Don’t. I want to be carried. She reels into the arms of Acis, who carries her into the temple.
Ecrasia | Come, Arjillax: you at least are still an artist. I adore you.
Arjillax | Do you? Unfortunately for you, I am not still a child. I have grown out of cuddling. I can only appreciate your figure. Does that satisfy you?
Ecrasia | At what distance?
Arjillax | Arm’s length or more.
Ecrasia | Thank you: not for me. She turns away from him.
Arjillax | Ha! ha! He strides off into the temple.
Ecrasia | Calling to Strephon, who is on the threshold of the temple, going in. Strephon.
Strephon | No. My heart is broken. He goes into the temple.
Ecrasia | Must I pass the night alone? She looks round, seeking another partner; but they have all gone. After all, I can imagine a lover nobler than any of you. She goes into the temple.
It is now quite dark. A vague radiance appears near the temple and shapes itself into the ghost of Adam.
A Woman’s Voice | In the grove. Who is that?
Adam | The ghost of Adam, the first father of mankind. Who are you?
The Voice | The ghost of Eve, the first mother of mankind.
Adam | Come forth, wife; and show yourself to me.
Eve | Appearing near the grove. Here I am, husband. You are very old.
A Voice | In the hills. Ha! ha! ha!
Adam | Who laughs? Who dares laugh at Adam?
Eve | Who has the heart to laugh at Eve?
The Voice | The ghost of Cain, the first child, and the first murderer. He appears between them; and as he does so there is a prolonged hiss. Who dares hiss at Cain, the lord of death?
A Voice | The ghost of the serpent, that lived before Adam and before Eve, and taught them how to bring forth Cain. She becomes visible, coiled in the trees.
A Voice | There is one that came before the serpent.
The Serpent | That is the voice of Lilith, in whom the father and mother were one. Hail, Lilith!
Lilith becomes visible between Cain and Adam.
Lilith | I suffered unspeakably; I tore myself asunder; I lost my life, to make of my one flesh these twain, man and woman. And this is what has come of it. What do you make of it, Adam, my son?
Adam | I made the earth bring forth by my labor, and the woman bring forth by my love. And this is what has come of it. What do you make of it, Eve, my wife?
Eve | I nourished the egg in my body and fed it with my blood. And now they let it fall as the birds did, and suffer not at all. What do you make of it, Cain, my firstborn?
Cain | I invented killing and conquest and mastery and the winnowing out of the weak by the strong. And now the strong have slain one another; and the weak live forever; and their deeds do nothing for the doer more than for another. What do you make of it, snake?
The Serpent | I am justified. For I chose wisdom and the knowledge of good and evil; and now there is no evil; and wisdom and good are one. It is enough. She vanishes.
Cain | There is no place for me on earth any longer. You cannot deny that mine was a splendid game while it lasted. But now! Out, out, brief candle! He vanishes.
Eve | The clever ones were always my favorites. The diggers and the fighters have dug themselves in with the worms. My clever ones have inherited the earth. All’s well. She fades away.
Adam | I can make nothing of it, neither head nor tail. What is it all for? Why? Whither? Whence? We were well enough in the garden. And now the fools have killed all the animals; and they are dissatisfied because they cannot be bothered with their bodies! Foolishness, I call it. He disappears.
Lilith | They have accepted the burden of eternal life. They have taken the agony from birth; and their life does not fail them even in the hour of their destruction. Their breasts are without milk: their bowels are gone: the very shapes of them are only ornaments for their children to admire and caress without understanding. Is this enough; or shall I labor again? Shall I bring forth something that will sweep them away and make an end of them as they have swept away the beasts of the garden, and made an end of the crawling things and the flying things and of all them that refuse to live forever? I had patience with them for many ages: they tried me very sorely. They did terrible things: they embraced death, and said that eternal life was a fable. I stood amazed at the malice and destructiveness of the things I had made: Mars blushed as he looked down on the shame of his sister planet: cruelty and hypocrisy became so hideous that the face of the earth was pitted with the graves of little children among which living skeletons crawled in search of horrible food. The pangs of another birth were already upon me when one man repented and lived three hundred years; and I waited to see what would come of that. And so much came of it that the horrors of that time seem now but an evil dream. They have redeemed themselves from their vileness, and turned away from their sins. Best of all, they are still not satisfied: the impulse I gave them in that day when I sundered myself in twain and launched Man and Woman on the earth still urges them: after passing a million goals they press on to the goal of redemption from the flesh, to the vortex freed from matter, to the whirlpool in pure intelligence that, when the world began, was a whirlpool in pure force. And though all that they have done seems but the first hour of the infinite work of creation, yet I will not supersede them until they have forded this last stream that lies between flesh and spirit, and disentangled their life from the matter that has always mocked it. I can wait: waiting and patience mean nothing to the eternal. I gave the woman the greatest of gifts: curiosity. By that her seed has been saved from my wrath; for I also am curious; and I have waited always to see what they will do tomorrow. Let them feed that appetite well for me. I say, let them dread, of all things, stagnation; for from the moment I, Lilith, lose hope and faith in them, they are doomed. In that hope and faith I have let them live for a moment; and in that moment I have spared them many times. But mightier creatures than they have killed hope and faith, and perished from the earth; and I may not spare them forever. I am Lilith: I brought life into the whirlpool of force, and compelled my enemy, Matter, to obey a living soul. But in enslaving Life’s enemy I made him Life’s master; for that is the end of all slavery; and now I shall see the slave set free and the enemy reconciled, the whirlpool become all life and no matter. And because these infants that call themselves ancients are reaching out towards that, I will have patience with them still; though I know well that when they attain it they shall become one with me and supersede me, and Lilith will be only a legend and a lay that has lost its meaning. Of Life only is there no end; and though of its million starry mansions many are empty and many still unbuilt, and though its vast domain is as yet unbearably desert, my seed shall one day fill it and master its matter to its uttermost confines. And for what may be beyond, the eyesight of Lilith is too short. It is enough that there is a beyond. She vanishes.